<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-06-16T18:42:53+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Optional Rule</title><subtitle>Optional Rule is a blog for DMs and Players alike of DnD 5e and any tabletop  roleplaying game. It offers rules, insight, analysis, and resources that help people run games and enhance their play.</subtitle><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><entry><title type="html">Embracing the Enigma - The Abstract Nature of Armor Class in D&amp;amp;D</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/16/abstract-nature-of-ac/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embracing the Enigma - The Abstract Nature of Armor Class in D&amp;amp;D" /><published>2023-06-16T12:17:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-16T12:17:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/16/abstract-nature-of-ac</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/16/abstract-nature-of-ac/"><![CDATA[<p>Delving into the oft-debated mechanics of Dungeons and Dragons (D&amp;D), it’s hard to overlook the perennial discussion points: Armor Class (AC) and Hit Points (HP). While they may seem simple on the surface, these fundamental aspects of D&amp;D often engender misunderstandings and heated debates. Armor Class, though instinctively viewed as a gauge of whether a character is struck or not, is in fact a more abstract concept. Following my recent post <a href="/2023/06/02/what-are-hit-points-in-dnd/">What are HP in D&amp;D anyway?</a>, it’s fitting that we now unpack the intricacies of AC and its symbiotic relationship with HP - the two crucial pillars that underpin the game’s combat system.</p>
<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix p-3 mb-5">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/the_duel_480x720.png" alt="Black and white art of two women dueling." height="720" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Rock, Paper, Greatsword!</figcaption>
    
</figure>
<h2 id="the-genesis-of-armor-class">The Genesis of Armor Class</h2>

<p>The genesis of Armor Class (AC) in Dungeons &amp; Dragons (D&amp;D) dates back to the game’s wargaming origins, where combat was typically a binary concept - either a unit was victorious or it was defeated. But as D&amp;D emerged, focusing on individual combat encounters instead of unit battles, a more intricate system was called for. To build and sustain tension for individual characters throughout an adventure, a ‘tug of war’ mechanic was introduced, wherein the game sought to quantify both a character’s resilience (HP) and the time needed to overcome them. Hence, Armor Class was born.</p>

<p>In Original D&amp;D (OD&amp;D), AC represented the challenge of landing a damaging hit on your character. However, it left the concept of a ‘hit’ undefined. Was it a sword deflecting off plate armor? A deft evasion? A streak of divine luck? The rulebook intentionally remained silent on these specifics, emphasizing AC’s inherent abstraction.</p>

<p>It’s important to appreciate that the architects of D&amp;D were well aware of the ‘swinginess’ of D20s. They understood that setting up a damage over time mechanic, regulated by the frequency of hits and the strength of attacks, was the most effective way to offset this inherent randomness. This allowed Adventures to be risky, but not random. An incredibly important element of TTRPG game design, if you wanted players to invest in their characters.</p>

<h2 id="armor-class-defining-its-abstraction">Armor Class: Defining its Abstraction</h2>

<p>As the D&amp;D editions evolved, the ambiguity of AC continued. Some players interpreted it as purely physical protection - the better the armor, the higher the AC. But armor could be bulky and restrictive. How would that account for the nimbleness of an unarmored monk? Or the ability of a rogue to evade attacks? Here’s where the abstraction comes into play.</p>

<p>AC is not just about physical armor. It encapsulates all the factors that might prevent a character from taking damage - natural agility, training, magical protection, divine favor, sheer luck, and yes, wearing a sturdy suit of armor. But, like HP, it’s not literally any of these things. It’s a mechanical tool that enables players to visualize their characters surviving in a dangerous world.</p>

<h2 id="the-dance-of-ac-and-hp">The Dance of AC and HP</h2>

<p>The relationship between AC and HP forms the basis of the D&amp;D Damage Over Time system. A character’s AC determines how likely they are to evade damage, while HP defines how much damage they can withstand before being defeated.</p>

<p>To illustrate, imagine a heavily armored knight (high AC, high HP) and a lightly armored rogue (lower AC, lower HP). The knight, with their superior armor, can absorb more hits before their HP depletes. In contrast, the rogue relies on their agility to avoid hits, mitigating the need for a large HP pool. Neither is invincible - the knight might face a foe with an accurate strike, and the rogue could encounter an enemy with an area attack that’s hard to dodge.</p>

<p>However, it’s vital to understand that AC isn’t a literal damage reduction. A higher AC doesn’t directly decrease the damage you take - but higher AC does mean you’ll take less damage over time. In this way, the single simple AC value serves the narrative role of damage reduction, as miss, or just toughing it out. Similarly, a high HP doesn’t mean you can shrug off a dragon’s fire breath - it represents your ability to avoid the worst of the attack, keep going despite the pain, or recover quickly.</p>

<h2 id="unshackling-the-abstraction">Unshackling the Abstraction</h2>

<p>It’s worth repeating that both AC and HP are mechanical tools for the game, not narrative shackles. They offer a game-friendly way to handle the complex, chaotic nature of combat without bogging down in ultra-realism that could hinder gameplay.</p>

<p>As the Dungeon Master, it’s your job to interpret these mechanics to best fit your campaign’s tone. You could emphasize the dodges and near misses for a rogue with high AC, or describe the punishing blows that a knight absorbs but powers through thanks to their high HP. In other words, the mechanics tension and provides momentum to a scene without getting in the way of the narrative tone of the game.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion-embrace-the-abstract">Conclusion: Embrace the Abstract</h2>

<p>Attempting to pin down Armor Class in literal terms is a path to confusion. Much like Hit Points, AC is best understood as an abstraction, a representative of various factors contributing to your character’s survivability in combat. It’s not simply the quality of a character’s armor, nor their ability to dodge, but a mix of physical, skillful, and even supernatural factors.</p>

<p>And so, dear reader, as with Hit Points, I encourage you to embrace the abstract nature of Armor Class. It’s a tool, a game mechanic designed to simulate the unpredictability and risk of combat in a fantasy world. It’s a tool to serve the narrative, because you don’t need a lesson in impact physics, you need a trilling duel in the streets of Neverwinter!  Use it as such, and weave it into your narrative in a way that enhances your game, not restricts it. Happy gaming!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="Analysis" /><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the abstraction of Armor Class in D&D, its roots in wargaming, and its dance with Hit Points.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/the_duel_480x720.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/the_duel_480x720.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Malevolent Monsters - Rage Husk</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/16/monster-rage-husk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Malevolent Monsters - Rage Husk" /><published>2023-06-16T11:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-16T11:45:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/16/monster-rage-husk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/16/monster-rage-husk/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome, intrepid Dungeon Masters, to the next thrilling addition to our bespoke bestiary: <strong>The Rage Husk</strong>. This terrifying creature is no standard zombie; it’s a psychic construct, the haunting aftermath of a <a href="/2023/05/24/monster-mind-reaver/">Mind Reaver</a>’s psychic assault. Incorporating elements of D&amp;D 4e’s Minion mechanics, Rage Husks serve as a swarm of formidable adversaries that, while dispatched with a single blow, offer a uniquely relentless and ruthless challenge. Join us as we delve into the grim lore of these dreadful entities and explore how they can elevate your campaign, introducing fresh layers of tension, suspense, and strategic complexity. Embrace the dread, harness the horror, and let your adventurers feel the chill of the Mind Reaver’s shadow with the introduction of the Rage Husk.</p>

<h2 id="rage-husks">Rage Husks</h2>
<p>In the labyrinthine depths of chaotic realms, there dwell malevolent entities known as a <a href="/2023/05/24/monster-mind-reaver/">Mind Reaver</a>. These beings, aberrations formed from failed attempts to create Mind Flayers, weave their own brand of dark, psychic terror. It’s in their destructive wake that the unfortunate victims are morphed into the monstrosities known as Rage Husks.</p>

<p>Robbed of their sanity and consciousness by the Mind Reavers, the victims are left with nothing but an echo of the pain and fury experienced in their final cognizant moments. This torment is reshaped into a fearsome determination to destroy, creating a formidable, mindless husk fueled by pure rage.</p>

<p>Rage Husks are often found scattered across the aftermath of a Mind Reaver attack, a chilling reminder of their terrifying power. Furthermore, within the treacherous lairs of these vile creatures, the Mind Reavers maintain a fragile control over the Rage Husks, utilizing them as part of their defensive strategies. As your group delves deeper into these chaotic territories, brace yourself for encounters with these tortured beings, their relentless pursuit a testament to the horrors of the Mind Reaver’s touch.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/monsters/RageHusk_407x610.png" alt="A raging and twisted humanoid running toward the viewer." height="610" width="407" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">A Rage Husk</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<blockquote class="stat-block wide">
  <h2 id="rage-husk">Rage Husk</h2>
  <p><em>Medium abomination, chaotic evil; (Minion)</em></p>

  <hr />

  <ul>
    <li><strong>Armor Class</strong> 11</li>
    <li><strong>Hit Points</strong> 19 (3d8 + 6)</li>
    <li><strong>Speed</strong> 30 ft.</li>
  </ul>

  <hr />

  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th style="text-align: center">STR</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">DEX</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">CON</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">INT</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">WIS</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">CHA</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: center">13 (+1)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">14 (+2)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">12 (+1)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">3 (-4)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">6 (-2)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">5 (-3)</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>

  <hr />
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Saving Throws</strong> DEX +4</li>
    <li><strong>Damage Vulnerabilities</strong> Psychic</li>
    <li><strong>Condition Immunities</strong> Charmed, Frightened</li>
    <li><strong>Senses</strong> Passive perception 8</li>
    <li><strong>Languages</strong> –</li>
    <li><strong>Challenge</strong> 1/2 (100 XP)</li>
  </ul>

  <h3 id="abilities">Abilities</h3>
  <p><strong><em>Mindless Aggression.</em></strong> As a bonus action, the rage husk can move up to its speed toward a hostile creature that it can see.</p>

  <p><strong><em>Tackler.</em></strong> The rage husk has advantage on any shove or grapple action if it has moved 10 feet or more in a straight line toward the target that turn.</p>
  <h3 id="actions">Actions</h3>
  <p><strong><em>Multiattack.</em></strong> The rage husk makes two slam attacks.</p>

  <p><strong><em>Slam.</em></strong> Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 4 (1d6 + 1) bludgeoning damage.</p>

  <h3 id="reactions">Reactions</h3>
  <p><strong><em>Overwhelm.</em></strong>  The rage husk may make a single slam attack against a creature as soon as it successfully grapples them or knocks them prone.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="mastering-minions-a-page-from-dds-4e-playbook">Mastering Minions: A Page from D&amp;D’s 4e Playbook</h3>

<p>Calling all Dungeon Masters seeking to elevate their combat encounters! Let’s revisit a technique from D&amp;D’s 4th edition that’s making a modern comeback, including in <a href="https://shop.mcdmproductions.com/collections/flee-mortals-the-mcdm-monster-book" target="_blank">MCDM’s ‘Flee Mortals’</a> book: the mighty Minion rule. This simple rule is your key to creating scenes of epic, heroic battles: minions, despite behaving like standard monsters, fall with just one successful hit. But don’t discard the minion’s hit points just yet. These still matter for spells like Sleep, which operate based on HP.</p>

<p>Whether it’s a horde of minions, or adding spice to a boss battle, the Minion rule can turn a routine encounter into a memorable tale of heroic warfare. Harness this tool, and let’s take your game to the next level!</p>

<h2 id="using-rage-husks">Using Rage Husks</h2>
<p>Imagine unleashing a torrent of Rage Husks against your unsuspecting party, creating a frantic and intense combat scenario where waves of these formidable yet easily dispatchable enemies push the heroes to their limits. Even the mightiest of warriors can be overwhelmed by sheer numbers, testing not just their strength, but their endurance and tactical acumen as well. Rage Husks also serve as formidable minions when under the control of a powerful adversary like a Mind Reaver, adding a dangerous layer to an already challenging boss fight. But don’t limit yourself to what’s written here - let your imagination run wild! These psychic zombies could be the consequence of a cursed item, a magical effect gone wrong, or a myriad of other creative plot devices. So go ahead, unleash the Rage Husks and let the heroic chaos unfold!</p>

<h3 id="adventure-seeds">Adventure Seeds</h3>
<p>Here are some adventure seeds you can use to incorporate Rage Husks into your adventure.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Cursed Heirloom:</strong> An antique necklace recently acquired by a noble family is actually a cursed item that transforms its wearers into Rage Husks. Can the party find a way to reverse the curse before the entire family is affected?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Madness Below:</strong> A mining town reports strange occurrences in the depths of their mines – miners turning into Rage Husks. The party must delve into the depths and discover the cause before it’s too late.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Blood Moon Ritual:</strong> During every Blood Moon, a deranged wizard’s failed experiments result in the creation of Rage Husks. Can the party stop the wizard before the next moon rise?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Crumbling Stronghold:</strong> In an ancient fortress, the party finds a horde of Rage Husks, mindlessly guarding something. What secrets are they protecting and can the party uncover them?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Towering Silence:</strong> An entire city suddenly falls quiet, and an army of Rage Husks are the only residents. The party must uncover what turned the citizens and if there’s a way to restore them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Lost Expedition:</strong> An archaeological expedition in ancient ruins has disappeared. Their last message spoke of strange, rage-filled creatures. Can the party rescue the lost archaeologists and confront the Rage Husks?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Wailing Forest:</strong> A haunted forest has started birthing Rage Husks from its mists. The party must find the source of this curse and put an end to it.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Puppeteer’s Game:</strong> A Mind Reaver is using Rage Husks as pawns in its deadly game. Can the party navigate the treacherous lair, defeat the Rage Husks, and stop the Mind Reaver?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Abandoned Monastery:</strong> Monks of a secluded monastery have become Rage Husks after dabbling with forbidden magic. Can the party cleanse the monastery and break the cycle of transformation?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Plagued Harbor:</strong> A cursed artifact brought into a bustling port city is slowly transforming its inhabitants into Rage Husks. The party must identify the artifact and break its curse to save the city.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Now get out there and run some great games!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><category term="Monsters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Unearth the chilling world of Rage Husks in DnD! Discover lore, encounter tactics, and adventure seeds for these psychic zombies of the Underdark.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/monsters/RageHusk_407x610.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/monsters/RageHusk_407x610.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Pitch Perfect - Using a Pitch Deck for Your D&amp;amp;D Campaign</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/10/campaign-pitch-decks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pitch Perfect - Using a Pitch Deck for Your D&amp;amp;D Campaign" /><published>2023-06-10T10:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-10T10:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/10/campaign-pitch-decks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/10/campaign-pitch-decks/"><![CDATA[<p>Launching a new Dungeons &amp; Dragons campaign is no small feat. It requires not only the arduous task of finding players, but also identifying those who are the perfect fit for your envisioned adventure. Even before delving into character backgrounds, safety tools, or other vital session zero elements, a Dungeon Master’s first hurdle is convincing potential players to invest their precious time and energy into the unfolding saga. This initial step bears striking similarity to pitching a fresh product or service. Just as entrepreneurs entice investors with the promise of innovation and value, DMs need to captivate potential players with a compelling campaign concept. Enter the Pitch Deck - a tool commonly used in the business world, but equally potent in setting the stage for a thrilling D&amp;D campaign.</p>

<p>Indeed, a Pitch Deck isn’t mandatory. You could create a written summary instead. The advantage of a deck, however, is its brevity and focus on essentials. Regardless of format, the aim stays the same. We’ll conclude with a template to help you craft your own pitch, be it a Deck or a Summary.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix p-3 mb-5">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/CharactersCelebratingAtTable_480x480.png" alt="A group of adventurers in a tavern with a leader giving an inspirational speech." height="480" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Run the game in your heart.</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h2 id="what-is-a-pitch-deck">What is a Pitch Deck?</h2>

<p>A pitch deck is a short presentation that shows off your unique game idea. It gives people a sneak peek into your game’s style, story, changes to rules, schedule, and other key parts that make your game special.</p>

<p>Although your D&amp;D game doesn’t need money from investors, a pitch deck is still very useful. It helps you get people excited to play and willing to spend their valuable time on your game.</p>

<h2 id="creating-a-dd-campaign-pitch-deck">Creating a D&amp;D Campaign Pitch Deck</h2>

<p>The contents of a pitch deck can vary based on firm a concept the DM has for the game they’re looking to run, but it often includes several key elements. First, it establishes the premise, tone, and style of the game, providing relevant examples. Second, it delves into how the party will interact with each other and their surrounding world. Third, it outlines how the game will engage with its mechanics. Finally, it sets certain baseline boundaries and expected norms within the group, laying the groundwork for future collaboration or safety tools.</p>

<h3 id="the-campaign-pitch-summary">The Campaign Pitch Summary</h3>

<p><strong>The essence of your pitch lies in just one slide - this is it!</strong> Captivating your audience involves inciting curiosity for more, so focus on broad strokes and highlights. Tease the plot, evoke the action, and convey the tone of the game. If the players you’re pitching to aren’t familiar with each other, share a few insights about your DMing style, the humor at the table, and the particular rules you’re implementing. Save the details for follow-up questions or Session Zero. Your primary goal is to pique the players’ interest and steer their thinking in the right direction from the start.</p>

<p>Here’s what I recommend:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Campaign Title and Tagline:</strong> Consider examples like “Rime of the Frostmaiden: A chilling struggle for survival in the heart of fantasy horror” or “Trouble on the Triboar Trail: Frontier justice meets rugged survival in the untamed Sword Mountains.”</li>
  <li><strong>Setting:</strong> Include a brief mention of the setting, landscape, travel logistics, or how players will interact with the world.</li>
  <li><strong>System:</strong> Outline the system, edition, any specific versions, and sources the game will use. Example: “5e D&amp;D, minor house rules apply. Core books, Xanathar’s, &amp; Tasha’s acceptable. No Unearthed Arcana, please.”</li>
  <li><strong>Inspiration:</strong> Reference a few films, books, or other media that capture the campaign’s intended ambiance. If relevant, consider including a film-like rating for the campaign.</li>
  <li><strong>Campaign Style:</strong> Indicate how Roleplaying, Lore, Action, and Combat will factor into the campaign. You might also want to mention the degree of consequence in the game. Adding a note about humor’s place can be helpful – e.g., “Significant lore and roleplay. Light humor. Minimize metagaming.” or “Intense lore and roleplaying, grim-dark setting, no phones at the table.”</li>
  <li><strong>Schedule &amp; Venue:</strong> Be upfront about your proposed schedule, as this can often be a hurdle for campaigns. Also, specify whether the game will be online, in-person, or a mix. This is akin to “the ask” in pitches - be explicit. E.g., “Online via Roll20, weekly for 3 hours, Saturdays 5pm EST. Please commit to regular attendance”, “In-person at my home, biweekly Sundays at 2pm, flexible attendance.”</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="additional-topics">Additional Topics</h3>

<p>The Campaign Pitch Summary is the essential part of your game pitch. Ideally, if your presentation includes more than one slide, the first one should captivate your players enough to prompt them to view the subsequent slides. The following are some additional slides that could provide players with more context. Out of these, I’d highly recommend “Game Boundaries &amp; Tools.” While many TTRPG players refer to these as Safety &amp; Consent, I believe the term “Boundaries” is more apt.</p>

<p><strong>Suggested Additional Slides or Topics:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Tools &amp; Resources:</strong> If your game is online or employs extensive tooling, this is the place to list those out. DnDBeyond, VTT, Text Chat, Voice Chat, and any other tools players will be using during the game. Differentiate between optional and mandatory tools. You might also consider mentioning your boundaries regarding other tools.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Table Styles:</strong> If you have specific expectations about game flow or table norms, outline them here. Whether you use an hourglass during play, ask players not to offer advice during others’ turns, or expect players to select their spells before their turn - these details belong on this slide.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Optional and House Rules:</strong> House Rules are quite common in D&amp;D, and even the core rules offer different variations a DM might adopt. Highlight these here, especially if a rule significantly impacts certain classes or players.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Baseline Boundaries:</strong> As touched on earlier, this would be my first choice for an additional slide after the summary. Boundaries are crucial in TTRPGs and can significantly affect the game’s enjoyment. While DMs should undoubtedly discuss player boundaries in session zero, it’s also essential to establish baseline expectations or non-negotiables ahead of that discussion. This sets a clear foundation and prevents any false sense of flexibility during session zero. For instance, I’m not fond of overly sexualized or evil play; it doesn’t mesh with my style. Your preferences and the nature of your game may differ. If you plan to run a particularly grim setting like Dark Sun, players should be aware of that before session zero. This slide is the place for such disclosures.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix p-3 mb-5">
    
        <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1kjaK9Q9p90P54E2ITZPf0DHGyaZZMHXYAg52Ar19zp4/edit?usp=sharing" target="_blank">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/ROTFM_PitchDeck.gif" alt="Animated GIF of the pitch deck I used in my Rime of the Frostmaiden Campaign." width="480" />
    
        </a>
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Example Pitch for my RotF Campaign</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h2 id="other-resources">Other Resources</h2>

<p>Creating a TTRPG Pitch Deck can be as elaborate or as straightforward as the DM prefers. Personally, I enjoy developing a deck adorned with images to add a bit of flair to the pitch. However, a text summary could be just as effective. Choose the format that suits you, your game, and the target players best.</p>

<p>Here are a few useful resources:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/assets/downloads/TTRPG_Pitch_Deck_Template.pptx"><strong>Pitch Deck Template</strong></a> I’ve designed this simple pitch deck template, complete with prompts for a one-page summary. It’s provided in PowerPoint format, but you can upload it to Google Drive or open it with LibreOffice.
    <ul>
      <li>For a real-world example, take a look at this <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1kjaK9Q9p90P54E2ITZPf0DHGyaZZMHXYAg52Ar19zp4/edit?usp=sharing" target="_blank">Rime of the Frostmaiden Pitch Deck</a> I used for my campaign.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://slyflourish.com/one_page_campaign_guide.html" target="_blank"><strong>Writing a One-Page Campaign Guide</strong></a> by Mike ‘Sly Flourish’ Shea offers another perspective. While I prefer using the pitch to pique interest and then this tool to provide more context prior to session zero, you could begin with this if you’ve already garnered sufficient interest.</li>
  <li><a href="https://youtu.be/MtH1SP1grxo" target="_blank"><strong>Pitching Your Campaign</strong></a> by Matt Colville is a fantastic video from his Running the Game series.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Getting player investment from the start can be a powerful tool for launching your campaign on the right foot. It not only helps identify players who are a good fit for your style of game,  but also directs their creative energies from the get-go. While session zero tends to get the limelight, we shouldn’t overlook engaging the right players even before we reach that point. Pitching your game in a fun and engaging way can help you navigate past common challenges by aligning with the right players from the beginning.</p>

<p>Now get out there and run some great games!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><category term="TTRPG" /><category term="DnD" /><category term="Player Recruitment" /><category term="Safety Tools" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Pitch your D&D campaign like a start-up. Use a pitch deck to attract the right players, align expectations and kickstart a successful game.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/CharactersCelebratingAtTable_480x480.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/CharactersCelebratingAtTable_480x480.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Decoding D&amp;amp;D - What the heck are Hit Points Anyway?</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/02/what-are-hit-points-in-dnd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decoding D&amp;amp;D - What the heck are Hit Points Anyway?" /><published>2023-06-02T08:51:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-02T08:51:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/02/what-are-hit-points-in-dnd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/02/what-are-hit-points-in-dnd/"><![CDATA[<p>The conversation around what Hit Points (HP) are and what they represent in Dungeons &amp; Dragons (D&amp;D) is a cyclical one. It’s a concept that periodically bubbles up in the tabletop role-playing game (TTRPG) community, like an ancient dragon in its cyclical slumber, and we seem to be in the midst of another awakening.</p>

<p>It’s no surprise that understanding HP often seems like trying to learn Draconic without a spell of Comprehend Languages. Table Top Roleplaying Games are narrative adventures, so we naturally want to weave a compelling story around every game element. And therein lies the enigma of Hit Points - no matter how you narrate them, you’re likely to walk into a wall of confusion and pile of contradictions.</p>

<div class="d-inline-flex flex-column float-end">
<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix shadow p-3 mb-5 bg-body-tertiary rounded">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/hitpoints/ODnD_p18_480.png" alt="Text on HP from the original DnD book." width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Original and B/X D&amp;D</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix shadow p-3 mb-5 bg-body-tertiary rounded">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/hitpoints/1stEditionDnD480.png" alt="Text on HP from AD&amp;D." width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">The AD&amp;D PHB</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix shadow p-3 mb-5 bg-body-tertiary rounded">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/hitpoints/2ndEditionDnD480.png" alt="Text on HP from 2nd Edition AD&amp;D." width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">The 2nd Edition AD&amp;D PHB</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix shadow p-3 mb-5 bg-body-tertiary rounded">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/hitpoints/5thEditionDnD480.png" alt="Text on HP from 5E D&amp;D." width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">The 5e PHB</figcaption>
    
</figure>
</div>

<h2 id="a-historical-perspective">A Historical Perspective</h2>

<p>Many D&amp;D elements, including HP, sprung from the hobby’s wargaming roots. In those days, units usually had a defensive score and an offensive score. The outcomes were binary: units either lived or died. But when these concepts morphed into the individual tactical combat that defined Original D&amp;D (OD&amp;D), there was a need for a way to track the progress towards defeat, thus giving birth to Armor Class (AC) and Hit Points (HP).</p>

<p>In OD&amp;D, AC denoted how challenging you were to hit, and HP showed how close you were to defeat. The game simply states, “Your hit points determine how hard your character is to kill.” And that’s it. That’s the HP origin story. They’re an arbitrary, abstract measurement of how difficult you are to kill and how far along the game is in achieving that.</p>

<h2 id="the-evolution-of-hp">The Evolution of HP</h2>

<p>Later D&amp;D editions got increasingly philosophical about HP. Advanced D&amp;D acknowledged physical punishment, but clarified that “a significant portion of hit points, especially at higher levels, stands for skill, luck, and/or magical factors.” It even said it would be “ridiculous” to assume characters could endure such physical punishment, further emphasizing that HP are not intended to be taken literally.</p>

<p>2nd Edition D&amp;D kept the abstract theme, defining damage as an abstract concept that allows characters to be heroic. It didn’t dwell on the semantics of HP. 3rd Edition, on the other hand, leaned into the mechanics and didn’t provide a narrative explanation for HP and damage at all. 4th Edition tried to have the best of both worlds, setting a base number of hit points representing “real” damage, while anything over was the old dance of skill, luck, and magic.</p>

<p>By the time 5th edition D&amp;D came around, we’re back in the abstract realm, with the game stating, “Hit Points represent a combination of physical and mental durability, the will to live, and luck.”</p>

<h2 id="hit-points-setting-the-stage-not-defining-the-genre">Hit Points: Setting the Stage, Not defining the Genre</h2>

<p>Hit Point mechanics are integral, but the presence of HP doesn’t force your game into a specific genre. That job is for the Dungeon Master, who tailors how this mechanic comes into play. For instance, early D&amp;D editions painted a grim, risky scene with low HP and tight damage thresholds, providing a sword-and-sorcery feel. In contrast, 5th Edition, with its generous HP pools and high-damage exploits, resonates with high-fantasy heroics.</p>

<p>Remember, it’s not the existence of HP that set these styles; it’s their application. As the DM, you have the freedom to adjust this tool to shape your campaign’s tone, from injecting grimdark elements into a 5th Edition game by reducing HP, to amping up the heroics in a 1st Edition game by increasing HP totals. At the end of the day, HP is a vital but flexible aspect of the D&amp;D universe.</p>

<h2 id="hit-points-tools-not-shackles">Hit Points: Tools, Not Shackles</h2>

<p>It’s crucial to remember that Hit Points are a mechanic, not a set of shackles for the DM. They have their boundaries and are not designed to simulate everything could befall a character. Every edition of D&amp;D underscores this, suggesting that the DM delineates these limits.</p>

<p>For instance, if a character decides to take a dip in a lava pool or plunge from a mile-high cliff, many DMs might opt not to roll damage, deeming these situations unsurvivable. In such cases, the official material often advises DMs to declare character death outright, instead of getting tangled in the mire of damage dice. <em>However, if these drastic scenarios occur frequently in your game, it might be worth reassessing your game design.</em></p>

<p>On the flip side, some DMs might channel a superhero vibe, letting characters brush off falls from great heights. That’s equally valid. As with any ruling in a tabletop RPG, maintaining an internally consistent world is the important part.</p>

<p>The bottom line? Understanding the tone of your game and setting appropriate limits is key when navigating the world of Hit Points. Keep this in mind as you weave your epic tales of adventure.</p>

<h2 id="living-with-the-hp-conundrum">Living with the HP Conundrum</h2>

<p>Trying to define Hit Points is like grappling with a Mind Flayer — it’s a sure path to madness. Make it too abstract, and you create a narrative disconnect. Make it too literal, and you grapple with the absurdities of surviving a lava bath or healing from the brink of death overnight.</p>

<p>In my humble opinion, D&amp;D intends for players to embrace the vagueness of Hit Points. They’re not ‘meat points’ or a measure of your plot armor, but more an abstraction of your character’s struggle to survive. Like most time travel plotlines, it’s nonsensical. So, just wave your hand, enjoy the game, and let the Hit Points fall where they may. Their purpose is to serve the adventure, the narrative, and ultimately, the fun. Because, in the end, who needs a physics lesson in the thermal dynamics of lava when you can have a daring escape from a volcano instead?</p>

<p>Now get out there and run some great games!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="Analysis" /><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post unravels the history of D&D's Hit Points (HP), from wargaming roots to 5th Ed's abstract system. And it looks into what the heck hit points are supposed to be anyway.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/mandy-jurgens-female-plate_475x672.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/mandy-jurgens-female-plate_475x672.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">You Have the Power - Places of Power in D&amp;amp;D</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/31/places-of-power/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You Have the Power - Places of Power in D&amp;amp;D" /><published>2023-05-31T08:54:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-31T08:54:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/31/places-of-power</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/31/places-of-power/"><![CDATA[<p>The untamed forces of magic in Dungeons and Dragons have long held the power to both awe and terrify, a duality echoed in the narrative threads of fantasy literature. This house rule invites players to embrace this paradox, offering a high-stakes opportunity to amplify their spells beyond conventional limits. But, this isn’t a risk to be taken lightly; mastery comes with potential for both magnificent success and cataclysmic failure. This high-risk, high-reward dynamic is not universal, but rather tethered to Places of Power - locations within the game world steeped in raw, wild magical energy. Here, spellcasters can attempt to weave this abundant power into their own spells, pushing the boundaries of what they could usually achieve. However, the road to arcane supremacy is fraught with peril, and the volatile energies of these places can lead to unexpected and dangerous consequences.</p>

<p>As a Dungeon Master, this house rule offers a unique narrative tool to manage the use of these amplified abilities and build compelling encounters. Villains, drawn to the immense power offered by these locations, might set up their lairs in Places of Power, adding an extra layer of challenge and strategy to confrontations. Moreover, these magical nexuses can become focal points in your campaign, driving the narrative as players might actively seek these places out, eager to tap into their vast potential. This is not just a rule - it is a lore, a plot device, and a tantalizing challenge all rolled into one, offering new avenues for character development and world-building. Embark on this arcane journey, and let your game be infused with the volatile and awe-inspiring power of raw magic.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/PlaceOfPower._480x720.jpg" alt="A ruin teaming with magical energy." height="720" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<h2 id="places-of-power">Places of Power</h2>

<p>Places of Power are distinctive locations saturated with arcane or divine energies. A competent spellcaster can tap into these energies, enhancing their own spells and abilities. To utilize a Place of Power, a spellcaster must first identify a location that aligns with their specific magical or divine influence. Following discovery, the caster must engage in a period of study and attunement to effectively harness the location’s power. Place types may or may not make a difference in terms of access and attunement, as determined by the DM.</p>

<p>Here are the common types of Places of Power:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Leyline Nodes:</strong> Leyline Nodes serve as focal points where natural currents of arcane energy converge, forming reservoirs of magical energy. Wizards can utilize these nodes, but only if their school of magic aligns with the particular energy of the node.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Holy Sites:</strong> These locations bear a distinct significance to a specific god, religion, or holy ideal. Clerics can tap into these sites, provided their divine domain aligns with the site’s sacred affiliation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Primal Refuges:</strong> These are areas that brim with the untouched, primal energies of nature, drawing power directly from the Feywild. Druids can utilize these refuges, but their Circle must align with the refuge’s primal energy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Pure Essence:</strong> These locations have been previously inhabited by potent supernatural entities, and their residual essence remains infused within these places. Sorcerers can tap into these locations, but their bloodline must correspond to the essence of the entity that once inhabited the location.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finding-and-attuning-to-a-place-of-power">Finding and Attuning to a Place of Power</h2>
<p>Places of power may be detected with the Detect Magic spell. Alternatively a combination of a study of the history of the place or careful examination may allow a History or Investigation check to realize a location is a place of power.</p>

<p>Once discovered, a spellcaster can take a short rest and attempt to attune to a Place of Power by making a check using their primary spellcasting ability. The DC for this check is set by the DM and typically ranges from 10 for common or well-known Places of Power, to 20 or more for extremely rare or unique locations. Importantly, attuning to a location does not count against the character’s maximum item attunement limit. However, this attunement isn’t permanent and may fade over time, necessitating reattunement after a significant period.</p>

<p>Remember, Places of Power should be treated as significant elements within your world, and their discovery and utilization should carry corresponding narrative weight.</p>

<h2 id="rarity--effects">Rarity &amp; Effects</h2>
<p>Places of Power in D&amp;D can enhance, modify or even provide entirely new abilities, offering a boost to spellcasters and creatures alike. DMs are encouraged to get creative with the effects of these power locations, making their campaigns even more engaging. Many wizards position their towers, creatures make lairs, and churches build their foundations upon these mystical spots, all seeking to harness their power.</p>

<p>Places of Power have a rarity system, akin to that of magic items, ranging from Common to Legendary. Here’s a brief overview of each category:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Common:</strong> These Places of Power are frequently encountered, and their effects, while beneficial, are relatively minor. Examples might include an area providing something akin to the Guidance spell or Song of Rest ability once per day. Roadside inns, small shrines, and minor monster lairs often occupy these sites.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Uncommon:</strong> Less common than their counterparts, these Places of Power provide slightly more potent effects or a broader range of minor effects. Typical examples might include Spell Weaving (see below), halving the time of spell scribing or alchemical production, providing an extra hit die of healing during a short rest once a day, or a small bonus to attack. Large shrines or small chapels, houses of healing, fortifications, libraries, and lairs often occupy these sites.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Rare:</strong> Rare Places of Power are challenging to find, but their beneficial effects are considerably more potent and impactful. Typical effects might include providing an increase to hit points, resistance to a type of damage, sustaining low-level spell effects, doubling healing, and more. Churches, organizational headquarters, strong castles, and powerful monster lairs often occupy these sites.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Very Rare:</strong> These Places of Power are seldom encountered. Their effects are significantly powerful, offering substantial benefits to those able to tap into them. These sites may provide regeneration, multiple resistances, spell resistance, control of regional weather, and more. Grand temples, state capitals, powerful citadels, and ancient dragon lairs often occupy these sites.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Legendary:</strong> The most elusive of all, Legendary Places of Power offer truly awe-inspiring and mind-bending abilities. They’re often tied to significant historical or world events and form the stuff of myths and legends. These sites provide total damage resistance or some damage immunities, combinations of spell-like abilities, the ability to alter terrain or control animals or beings in the region. Locations are almost always unique and heavily contested, leaving a legacy of woe.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>The possibilities are truly limitless, and Dungeon Masters are encouraged to get creative. Perhaps these locations house portals, serve as communion points for Warlocks and their patrons, or even provide coveted power sources for diligent Wizards. They could also imbue lair-dwelling monsters with abilities they might not typically possess. Use these Places of Power to enhance your game, provide players with intriguing new goals and mysteries, and above all, enjoy the journey. Gear up to elevate your gaming experience!</p>

<h3 id="spell-weaving-uncommon">Spell Weaving (Uncommon)</h3>

<p>When a spellcaster is within an attuned Place of Power, they may tap into its energy to enhance their spellcasting. As part of casting a spell, the caster can choose add one or more Metamagic-like effects. To do so, the caster must make a spellcasting ability check. The DC for this check is 10 + the level of the spell being cast + 2 for each Metamagic effect selected.</p>

<p>The available effects at a Place of Power typically include Distant Spell, Empower Spell, Extended Spell, and Subtle Spell, as per the descriptions provided in the Sorcerer class, but with references to Charisma replaced by the caster’s primary spellcasting ability.</p>

<p>If the character fails the check, the spell fails and the caster loses the spell slot. Additionally, if they fail the roll by 5 or more, they suffer one randomly rolled spell failure plus one additional failure effect for every additional 5 points they fail the Check by.</p>

<p>Roll a d6 to determine the type of failure:</p>

<p><strong>Spell Failure</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Mana Burn:</strong> The caster loses a spell slot of the spell’s level. If they have no more spell slots of that level, the player may choose to lose a spell slot of the next highest level, or two slots from the level below - it’s the player’s choice. If none are available, roll again.</li>
  <li><strong>Exhaustion:</strong> The caster gains a level of exhaustion as they’ve overtaxed their body.</li>
  <li><strong>Soul Shock:</strong> The caster has disadvantage on all checks with their primary casting ability until they complete a long rest. Rolling this effect again extends the duration by one additional long rest.</li>
  <li><strong>Sensory Overload:</strong> The caster is blinded, deafened, or loses the ability to speak (player’s choice) until the end of their next long rest. Rolling this effect again allows the player to select another effect or extends the duration of an existing effect by one additional long rest.</li>
  <li><strong>System Shock:</strong> The caster must succeed on a Constitution saving throw (DC 10 + spell level) or become stunned until the end of their next turn. Rolling this effect again means the condition lasts until the wizard makes a successful save, repeating this save at the end of each turn. If this effect is rolled a 3rd time, roll again instead.</li>
  <li><strong>Mana Feedback:</strong> The caster takes 1d8 force damage per level of the spell they attempted to cast.</li>
</ol>

<p>As always, adjust this system as necessary to fit your campaign and your players’ preferences.</p>

<h4 id="sorcerer-metamagic-in-a-place-of-power">Sorcerer Metamagic in a Place of Power</h4>

<p>When a sorcerer attuned to a Place of Power uses a Metamagic ability, they reduce the Sorcery Point cost by 1. If this adjustment would bring the cost below 1, there’s still a 50% chance they expend 1 Sorcery Point. Sorcerers can choose to use the standard Place of Power rules instead, particularly if they’re out of Sorcery Points or willing to embrace the risk.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="sample-places-of-power">Sample Places of Power</h2>
<p>The following examples offer a peek into what Places of Power might look like in your game. Remember, these descriptions aren’t exhaustive, and we urge all Dungeon Masters to inject their own creativity into these magical locales. Our goal is for these sites to spark your imagination, providing your players with thrilling incentives to delve deeper into the world. Also, don’t forget about the potential threats posed by creatures that might call these power-infused locales their home. Let’s dive in!</p>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="comforting-hearth">Comforting Hearth</h3>
  <h4 id="common-universal">Common, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>This welcoming place resonates with soothing energies, offering deep rest and restoration to those weary from their journeys.</em></p>

  <p>A character attuned to this site can recover an extra level of exhaustion after completing a Long Rest here, feeling their weariness melt away faster than usual. This effect can be used once per Long Rest. Additionally, any attuned character may roll with advantage to recover from a disease or poison while resting here.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="shrine-of-guided-grace">Shrine of Guided Grace</h3>
  <h4 id="common-holy-site">Common, Holy Site</h4>
  <p><em>This humble shrine is steeped in divine favor, bestowing a touch of guidance on those who pray here.</em></p>

  <p>An attuned character who spends time in prayer or contemplation at this holy site can receive a divine boon: a 1d4 bonus to a single skill roll for a specific task. This blessing must be invoked before the character’s next Long Rest or it dissipates, the divine favor waiting to be called upon another day.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="alchemists-reservoir">Alchemist’s Reservoir</h3>
  <h4 id="uncommon-universal">Uncommon, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>This enchanting site adorned with ancient, ornate distilleries, filled with swirling, shimmering vials of vibrant liquids, all bathed in the soft, multi-hued glow of arcane energy that pulses from the earth and air around it.</em></p>

  <p>Imbued with ancient alchemical energy, alchemists and herbalists attuned to this location can brew potions in half the time.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="the-echoing-library">The Echoing Library</h3>
  <h4 id="uncommon-leyline-node">Uncommon, Leyline Node</h4>
  <p><em>Echoes of arcane knowledge radiate from every shelf in this vast library, accelerating the study pace of those who delve into its treasures.</em></p>

  <p>Attuned spellcasters can prepare an additional spell of a level they can cast for each day they spend here, up to their proficiency bonus. This bonus lasts until the next long rest.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="the-vibrant-henge">The Vibrant Henge</h3>
  <h4 id="uncommon-universal-1">Uncommon, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>Constructed from ancient monoliths, these stones hum with ley line energy, amplifying the powers of those attuned to them.</em></p>

  <p>Arcane practitioners can draw on the raw power of this location to amplify their spells. Some Henges are aligned with a specific school of magic. When casting a spell within this school, practitioners can benefit from an advantageous Spell Weaving roll.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="haven-of-healing">Haven of Healing</h3>
  <h4 id="uncommon-holy-site-primal-refuge">Uncommon, Holy Site, Primal Refuge</h4>
  <p><em>Restorative energies suffuse this location, accelerating recovery and invigorating those who rest within.</em></p>

  <p>Those attuned to this sanctuary recover one level of exhaustion following a short rest. Furthermore, any spell or potion that restores Hit Points, when used within the haven, yields its maximum possible value. These benefits can each be claimed once per long rest.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="sanctuary-of-solitude">Sanctuary of Solitude</h3>
  <h4 id="uncommon-universal-2">Uncommon, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>Ancient wisdom lingers in this tranquil locale, inspiring profound insights for those who meditate here.</em></p>

  <p>Individuals attuned to this place can inscribe scrolls or copy spells into their spell book in half the usual time.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="celestial-observatory">Celestial Observatory</h3>
  <h4 id="rare-universal">Rare, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>This ancient observatory, filled with cryptic glyphs and celestial maps, resonates with whispers from the stars, enhancing the divination skills of those attuned to its energies.</em></p>

  <p>Attuned individuals within the Celestial Observatory gain a deep connection with the cosmos. They can channel this bond to cast the spell Message once per day. Attuned spellcasters in this location also gain the ability to use Spell Weaving, with divination spells providing an advantage to their Spell Weaving checks, enhancing their pursuit of knowledge and insights.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="feywild-glade">Feywild Glade</h3>
  <h4 id="rare-universal-1">Rare, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>Mystical energies from the Feywild permeate this location, empowering those who are attuned to it.</em></p>

  <p>Attuned characters may utilize the Spell Weaving ability here. When casting enchantment spells, they can apply Spell Weaving with an advantage.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="mana-oasis">Mana Oasis</h3>
  <h4 id="rare-universal-2">Rare, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>Overflowing with raw magical energy, this place replenishes the reserves of any attuned spellcaster resting here.</em></p>

  <p>Spellcasters attuned to this location can recover a number of spell slots after a short rest. They regain one spell slot of a level up to their proficiency bonus at the end of a short rest or an hour into a long rest. This benefit is limited to once per long rest.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="moonshadow-glenn">Moonshadow Glenn</h3>
  <h4 id="rare-primal-refuge">Rare, Primal Refuge</h4>
  <p><em>As a nexus of raw, wild power, this place resonates with the primal aspects of nature.</em></p>

  <p>Attuned characters can use their Wild Shape ability to transform into a beast with a Challenge Rating 1 higher than they normally could, once per long rest.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="stoneheart-bastion">Stoneheart Bastion</h3>
  <h4 id="rare-universal-3">Rare, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>Deep beneath the mountain’s roots, this subterranean bastion imbues those within with resilience, mirroring the earth’s unyielding strength.</em></p>

  <p>Any character or beast attuned to this place of power, or who has laired here for more than a full moon cycle, gains the fortitude of the earth itself. This manifests as resistance to non-magical bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage. The boon fades if they leave the site for more than a day or if their attunement is broken.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="primordial-nexus">Primordial Nexus</h3>
  <h4 id="very-rare-primal-refuge">Very Rare, Primal Refuge</h4>
  <p><em>A verdant haven echoing with the vibrant life force of nature, this place empowers attuned druids to embody a vast range of creatures inhabiting these lands.</em></p>

  <p>The Primordial Nexus allows attuned characters who can Wildshape to form deeper connections with creatures in the region. By performing a ritual with a trophy from a Monstrosity or Fey, the character can add that creature to their Wildshape options, as long as it falls within the normal Hit Dice and movement restrictions of their Wildshape ability.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="sanctuary-of-spirits">Sanctuary of Spirits</h3>
  <h4 id="very-rare-universal">Very Rare, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>The spirits of the departed are bound to this sacred refuge, allowing them to linger beyond their natural existence.</em></p>

  <p>When an attuned spellcaster casts Animate Dead on beings that met their end within this sanctuary, it doesn’t count towards their control limit. Instead, they can control a number of undead equal to their primary casting ability score. These undead are bound to the sanctuary and cannot leave its confines; the caster loses control if they lose their attunement.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="echoing-cavern-of-the-berzerker">Echoing Cavern of The Berzerker</h3>
  <h4 id="very-rare-universal-1">Very Rare, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>Legend speaks of a place where reality and illusion refuse to merge; this echoing cavern bolsters mental fortitude and instils clarity amidst deceptive influences.</em></p>

  <p>Characters or beasts that are attuned to this place, or have made it their lair for more than a lunar cycle, become extremely difficult to mislead. They gain advantage on saving throws against illusion spells and mind control effects. Furthermore, those capable of raging can maintain their rage for an additional round without taking damage or attacking an opponent, their resolve empowered by the steadfast spirit of the cavern.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Dive into D&D's magic with our guide on Places of Power. Explore how to find, attune, and harness these unique locations to enhance your game.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/PlaceOfPower._480x720.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/PlaceOfPower._480x720.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Reimagining the Mark Option in D&amp;amp;D 5E - Empowering Martial Characters</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/27/improved-mark-option/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reimagining the Mark Option in D&amp;amp;D 5E - Empowering Martial Characters" /><published>2023-05-27T10:28:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-27T10:28:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/27/improved-mark-option</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/27/improved-mark-option/"><![CDATA[<p>Dungeons and Dragons 5th Edition’s Dungeon Master’s Guide (DMG) presents an array of optional rules that, regrettably, often recede into obscurity. One such overlooked provision, nestled within Chapter 9 of the DMG, is the “Mark” option. This rule, seemingly promising on the surface, is burdened with unnecessary complexities, offering marginal benefit.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/OpportunityAttack_480x720.jpg" alt="A fighter slashing at the back of an enemy as they run away. Black and white line art." height="720" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">No Running!</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>The original Mark option requires a character to ‘mark’ a target each turn and diligently keep track of this choice. The upside? The ability to execute an Opportunity Attack without consuming a reaction - a beneficial yet sporadic occurrence. However, the tediousness of marking a target every round, coupled with the relative rarity of Opportunity Attacks, seems needlessly complex and limiting, making this rule an unwieldy addition to many campaigns.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, with a sprinkle of creativity and modification, we believe this rule harbors the potential to significantly enhance the gameplay experience, especially for martial characters. Here, we propose a tweak aimed at simplifying the Mark option and boosting its relevance in melee combat dynamics:</p>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h2 id="mark-improved">Mark (Improved)</h2>
  <p>This option amplifies the capability of melee combatants to challenge each other with opportunity attacks.</p>

  <p>An Opportunity Attack against a creature that the attacker has struck with a Melee Attack since their last turn does not consume the attacker’s reaction. Characters are still limited to one Opportunity Attack per round.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This alteration doesn’t bog down gameplay with added choices, applies uniformly to all melee characters, provides the most substantial impact to characters with multiple attacks, and spares the added complexity of tracking marked targets. It retains the viability of Opportunity Attacks while synergizing well with abilities such as Protect, Intercept, Hide in Plain Sight, and many others, making martial characters, particularly fighters, far more dynamic.</p>

<p>That’s my take on this potential enhancement to the Mark rule, but what about you? Do you see the value this could bring to your game? We’re all ears for your thoughts, so let’s start a conversation.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore a proposed revision to D&D 5E's "Mark" option to boost martial gameplay, simplifying rules and enriching combat dynamics.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/OpportunityAttack_480x720.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/OpportunityAttack_480x720.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Malevolent Monsters - The Mind Reaver</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/24/monster-mind-reaver/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Malevolent Monsters - The Mind Reaver" /><published>2023-05-24T08:43:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-24T08:43:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/24/monster-mind-reaver</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/24/monster-mind-reaver/"><![CDATA[<p>In the thrilling realm of Dungeons &amp; Dragons, where weI’ve crafted epic battles and monstrous foes, I’m thrilled to introduce my latest creation, the Mind Reaver. This new entity is a nightmarish variation of the classic Mind Flayer. It’s not just a twisted iteration but an entirely different beast that thrives in chaos and malice, unlike its lawful evil kin. The Mind Reaver promises to surprise, challenge, and instill a sense of dread in even the most seasoned adventurers. As I bring this unpredictable creature into our stories, I aim to add another layer of depth to our collective adventures. So get ready, fellow Dungeon Masters and players, as we dive headlong into the chaotic and terrifying world of the Mind Reaver.</p>

<h2 id="the-mind-reaver">The Mind Reaver</h2>

<p>The process of creating a Mind Flayer is a precise and delicate one, carefully conducted by Illithid elders in their dark and hidden laboratories beneath the earth. However, when this procedure is tainted by volatile energies, the resulting creature is a grotesque and chaotic aberration known as a Mind Reaver.</p>

<p>Unlike their fully formed brethren, Mind Reavers bear the hideous marks of their flawed creation. Their bodies are twisted and warped, with elongated limbs, a disproportionate number of writhing tentacles, and skin mottled with pulsating patches of unnatural color. Their eyes, usually two in number, can vary in placement and quantity, giving them an unsettling gaze that seems to penetrate into one’s very soul.</p>

<h3 id="lore">Lore</h3>

<p>Mind Reavers are an anathema within Illithid society. Their chaotic tendencies make them unpredictable and dangerously volatile, both to enemies and their own kind. As such, they are typically exiled upon their creation, sent to wander the Underdark or any place far from the organized colonies of the Mind Flayers.</p>

<p>Though they lack the refined psionic prowess of a typical Mind Flayer, these creatures are not to be underestimated. Their chaotic nature fuels a raw, unrestrained psychic power, making them erratic but potent foes. This, coupled with their innate bitterness towards a world that has rejected them, makes them exceedingly dangerous.</p>

<p>It’s rumored that these creatures, despite their volatile and chaotic behavior, hold a profound hatred for their fully-formed Illithid brethren, and tales speak of them rallying other Underdark denizens to their cause. In rare instances, they have been known to form aberrant ‘colonies’ of their own, bringing together various misfit and outcast creatures of the Underdark under their warped rule.</p>

<p>In the end, the Mind Reaver is a tragic figure. Born of a process meant to create perfection, they are instead left as imperfect beings in a world that shuns them. Yet it’s this imperfection, this deviation from the norm, that makes them a force to be reckoned with. One should be wary when traversing the dark recesses of the Underdark, for you never know when you might cross paths with a Mind Reaver.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/monsters/mind_reaver_500x500.jpg" alt="A twisted creature with tenticles." height="500" width="500" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">A Mind Reaver (with jazz hands)</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<blockquote class="stat-block wide">
  <h2 id="mind-reaver">Mind Reaver</h2>
  <p><em>Medium aberration, chaotic evil</em></p>

  <hr />

  <ul>
    <li><strong>Armor Class</strong> 14 (natural armor)</li>
    <li><strong>Hit Points</strong> 45 (6d8 + 18)</li>
    <li><strong>Speed</strong> 30 ft.</li>
  </ul>

  <hr />

  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th style="text-align: center">STR</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">DEX</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">CON</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">INT</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">WIS</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">CHA</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: center">11 (+0)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">12 (+1)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">16 (+3)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">16 (+3)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">14 (+2)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">14 (+2)</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>

  <hr />

  <ul>
    <li><strong>Saving Throws</strong> Int +5, Wis +4, Cha +4</li>
    <li><strong>Skills</strong> Perception +4, Deception +4, Arcana +5</li>
    <li><strong>Damage Resistances</strong> psychic</li>
    <li><strong>Senses</strong> darkvision 120 ft., passive Perception 14</li>
    <li><strong>Languages</strong> Deep Speech, Undercommon, telepathy 120 ft.</li>
    <li><strong>Challenge</strong> 4 (1,100 XP)</li>
  </ul>

  <h3 id="abilities">Abilities</h3>
  <p><strong>Innate Spellcasting (Psionics).</strong> The Mind Reaver’s innate spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no components:</p>

  <p>At will: <em>detect thoughts, levitate</em></p>

  <p>1/day each: <em>cause fear, sleep</em></p>

  <p><strong>Magic Resistance.</strong> The Mind Reaver has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</p>
  <h3 id="actions">Actions</h3>
  <p><strong>Tentacles.</strong> Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. Hit: 7 (1d8 + 3) psychic damage. If the target is Medium or smaller, it is grappled (escape DC 13) and must succeed on a DC 13 Intelligence saving throw or be stunned until this grapple ends. The Mind Reaver gains temporary hit points equal to the damage done to any creature that fails the Intelligence saving throw for being stunned.</p>

  <p><strong>Psychic Scream (Recharge 6).</strong> The Mind Reaver emits psychic energy in a 30-foot radius. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 13 Intelligence saving throw or take 16 (3d8 + 3) psychic damage and be stunned for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="using--mind-reavers">Using  Mind Reavers</h2>
<p>The Mind Reaver, with its Challenge Rating (CR) of 5, serves as an ideal boss monster for low-level parties or as a group threat for more advanced players. It embodies the very essence of malevolent chaos, destruction, resentment, and bitter betrayal, providing a gripping and intense encounter in any campaign. Whether it’s the primary antagonist in a dark story arc or a surprise menace lurking in the depths of your dungeon, the Mind Reaver promises an unforgettable encounter.</p>

<h3 id="adventure-seed-ideas">Adventure Seed Ideas</h3>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>City of Nightmares</strong>: City leaders are experiencing sudden, violent episodes at night, instigating chaos, with a Mind Reaver secretly causing it all from the sewers. The party must brave the depths, confront the Mind Reaver, and halt the spreading pandemonium.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Lost Expedition</strong>: An adventuring party went missing in a series of mysterious caves. Their last message spoke of strange creatures with tentacles and psychic powers.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Cult of Chaos</strong>: A cult has been attempting to summon a Mind Reaver to spread chaos and destruction in the region.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Mind-locked Prison</strong>: The heroes are imprisoned in a psychic jail by a Mind Reaver and must use their wits to escape.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Mad Mage</strong>: A mage driven to chaos and destruction by a Mind Reaver’s psychic influence threatens a peaceful village.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Raiders from the Underdark</strong>: Mind Reavers lead a Drow Outcast raiding party from the Underdark, wreaking havoc in the countryside. They have been kidnapping victims to create more of their vile kind.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Bitter Betrayal</strong>: A once-trusted ally turns out to be controlled by a Mind Reaver disguised as servant, plotting the downfall of the local government.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Abyssal Portal</strong>: Strange creatures are terrorizing the countryside, seemingly appearing out of nowhere. A Mind Reaver plans to open a portal to the Abyss, aiming to let chaotic entities into the realm.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Revenge of the Mind Slaves</strong>: People who were once enthralled by a Mind Reaver are now free and seeking vengeance, but they fear the creature’s return. Can the party heal and integrate the former captives and end the threat of the Mind Reaver’s return.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Relic of Chaos</strong>: An ancient artifact that holds the essence of a powerful Mind Reaver has been stolen, threatening to unleash the beast if not recovered in time.</p>
  </li>
</ol>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><category term="Monsters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Mind Reaver, a chaos driven twisted creature from the Underdark.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/monsters/mind_reaver_500x500.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/monsters/mind_reaver_500x500.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Vathirond City of Wild Inspiration</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/19/vathirond-city-of-wild-inspiration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vathirond City of Wild Inspiration" /><published>2023-05-19T12:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-19T12:38:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/19/vathirond-city-of-wild-inspiration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/19/vathirond-city-of-wild-inspiration/"><![CDATA[<div class="text-bg-light mb-3 p-3 lead">As a Dungeon Master, there's nothing quite as enticing as the prospect of molding a lesser-known city into a stage for unforgettable adventures. In 2019, I found myself drawn to the city of Vathirond, tucked away in far eastern Breeland, on the fringes of Eberron's haunting Mournlands. With the Brey River's southern bank underfoot and the specter of the Gray Mist as a backdrop, Vathirond was an irresistible canvas for my homebrew campaign. Yet, as fate would have it, our journey through this enigmatic city was cut short due to the COVID pandemic. Now, after a couple of years, I've dusted off my notes and decided to share them with the world. Whether you're a seasoned Dungeon Master or a curious reader, I hope you find these glimpses into Vathirond - the city on the edge of the Mournlands - as fascinating as I did while crafting them.
</div>

<p>Situated amidst the low, rolling hills of the northern Dunvar Valley, the city of Vathirond was once a vibrant hub of creativity and artistry, where inspiration flowed as freely as the wind. The city, renowned across Khorvaire for its extravagant displays of artistic prowess, was known to entice artists and creators from all corners of the continent. They were drawn not only by the vibrancy of Vathirond’s culture but also by the city’s minor manifest zone to Xoriat, the plane of madness, which imbued the city with an aura of wild inspiration.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/VathirondInspiration4.png" alt="A once elegant but now devistated city of complex and stacked buildings." height="480" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">The Crown of Masks</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>However, the Last War has left the city a shadow of its former self, its once-gleaming Crowns now scarred by conflict and its streets haunted by memories of a brighter past. The Mournlands loom ominously on the eastern horizon, a stark, ever-present reminder of the devastation wrought by the Last War. From the city’s highest points, one can see the unnatural, eerie glow that seems to perpetually hang over the scarred landscape. This spectral vista casts a pall over Vathirond, a constant reminder of a cataclysm yet to be fully understood. The very sight of it evokes a mix of dread, sorrow, and grim fascination among the city’s inhabitants. Its unnerving presence fuels a sense of urgency among the residents of Vathirond, a constant reminder of the fragility of peace and the cost of conflict. Yet, in a testament to the indomitable spirit of the city’s people, the looming specter of the Mournlands also inspires a defiant determination. They see the Mournlands not just as a symbol of past horrors, but also as a challenge to be overcome, a puzzle to be solved, and a destiny they must prevent for their own city.</p>

<h2 id="the-shattered-crowns">The Shattered Crowns</h2>

<p>Nestled within the city of Vathirond, six semi-autonomous districts – known as the Crowns – stand prominently, each perched atop its own hill and fortified by formidable walls. This unique arrangement provided strategic defense throughout the ravages of The Last War, each Crown bearing the brunt of the conflict and experiencing a different outcome. Each Crown was originally dedicated to a particular artistic discipline, fostering a unique culture and identity that has persisted amidst turmoil. These districts are more than just geographic divisions; they represent the diverse tapestry of Vathirond’s spirit, embodying the resilience, creativity, and individuality of the city’s past and present. The Crowns serve as unique reminders of the city’s artistic heritage, even as they evolve in response to the aftermath of war.</p>

<h3 id="crown-of-masks-applause-and-back-stage-deals">Crown of Masks: Applause and Back Stage Deals</h3>

<p>The stage for stories, the canvas for compelling characters, and the sounding board for stirring soliloquies – the Crown of Masks has been the heart of theater and drama in Vathirond. Despite the ruinous touch of the war, it has retained a faded grandeur. Its buildings are reminiscent of an era of creativity and artistry, their embellished facades narrating tales of yesteryears. This Crown was fortunate to have survived the worst of the Last War, maintaining a semblance of its former glory.</p>

<p>The ward now serves as the militaristic nucleus of Vathirond’s fragmented government. It’s a command hub for military logistics, but also a political stage that hosts heated debates on the city’s future. It is from here that the populist Narani Laseur has polarized the city’s sentiment over refugee resettlement and rebuilding rights.</p>

<p>Laseur’s controversial administration is backed by a private security force, the Firehawk Legion. These goblinoid mercenaries from Darguun are a jarring sight against the backdrop of dramatic mosaics and grand theater facades. However, their presence is a stark reminder of the city’s current reality - a stage where the drama of survival unfolds daily.</p>

<p>The Crown of Masks, once a hub of artistic endeavor, now mirrors the city’s resilience amidst adversity. It’s a poignant testament to the spirit of Vathirond - a city holding onto its identity, its memory of past glory, even as it faces an uncertain future.</p>

<h3 id="crown-of-satyrs-twists-turns-and-triumph">Crown of Satyrs: Twists, Turns, and Triumph</h3>

<p>Among the dance of shadows and the glow of the lantern light, the Crown of Satyrs spins a tale of grace in the face of ruin. The streets here twist and turn like a dancer mid-routine, unraveling onto expansive squares that once pulsated with the rhythm of impromptu performances. This Crown’s spirit proved as nimble as its inhabitants, retaining a significant portion of its population through the throes of The Last War. Community bonds, stronger than the aged stones of their homes, anchor the people in a warm embrace of shared experience and stubborn resilience.</p>

<p>Here, House Phiarlan stands as an enduring symbol of the district’s tenacity, operating from a smaller yet still magnificent corner of their once sprawling complex. Their performers, the city’s mesmerizing heartbeats, still captivate with their tales of sorrow and survival. This Crown, however, does more than dance. It watches. From the city’s underbelly to the swelling tide of refugees, from the ghostly echoes of The Mournlands to the subtle shifts in power within Vathirond, nothing escapes the watchful eyes of the Satyrs.</p>

<h3 id="crown-of-sirens-echoes-of-a-melodious-past">Crown of Sirens: Echoes of a Melodious Past</h3>

<p>The Crown of Sirens, once the jewel of Vathirond’s vibrant music scene, now wears a cloak of desolation. The last notes of harmony faded away during the tumult of the Last War, replaced by the dissonant chords of silence and decay.</p>

<p>In its prime, the Crown of Sirens echoed with melodies that transcended language and culture. It was home to the Lonteu Opera House, a grand stage where performers from across Khorvaire gathered to serenade audiences with their songs. Music was the lifeblood of the ward; it flowed from its concert halls, meandered through its streets, and suffused the air with a symphony of shared emotions - joy, sorrow, love, and longing.  Heavily damaged during the ware, the Opera House is not the headquarters for the Korranberg Institute for Mournlands Research (KIMR).</p>

<p>However, the crescendo of the Last War proved too overwhelming. The Crown’s defenses were breached, and the once-thriving ward bore the brunt of relentless assaults. Its grand architecture was marred by the scars of war, its harmonious rhythm disrupted by the cacophony of destruction.</p>

<p>Today, the Crown of Sirens stands as a testament to the impermanence of glory and the inevitable cycle of creation and ruin. The ward, though a shadow of its former self, has not been completely abandoned. The ruins of once great townhouses serve as a shelter for those displaced by the war. Migrants from Cyre, the Dunvar Valley, and veterans who could not leave the battlefield behind have found solace within its broken walls. Their stories of loss and longing lend a new, melancholic melody to the ward, as poignant as the songs once sung on the opera stage.</p>

<p>House Tharashk, utilizing their unique dragonmarked talents for finding people and things, offer their services to refugees and travelers desperately searching for lost loved ones or belongings in the blighted expanses of the Dunvar Valley and the enigmatic Mournlands. The enclave, while a stark reminder of the tragedies of the past, embodies a spirit of resilience and the enduring hope of reconnection.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/vathirondpinspriation2.png" alt="A once elegant but now devistated city of complex and stacked buildings." height="480" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">The Crown of Crafts</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h3 id="crown-of-crafts-from-artistry-to-industry">Crown of Crafts: From Artistry to Industry</h3>

<p>Once a flourishing hub of creative expression, the Crown of Crafts served as the canvas for Vathirond’s sculptors and painters. Its streets were lined with grand architecture, adorned with vibrant murals and intricate statues that reflected the heart and soul of its citizens. Now, this Crown bears the telltale signs of war’s toll and the relentless march of industry.</p>

<p>The Crown of Crafts, in its heyday, was a living testament to the artistic spirit of Vathirond. Every street corner boasted an artisan’s shop, and the air was suffused with the scent of fresh paint, chiseled stone, and the underlying sense of creation. The once-colorful facades were a riot of artistic expression, every mural telling a story, each statue capturing a moment frozen in time.</p>

<p>However, the Last War brought change - the vibrant strokes of paint and chisel strokes gave way to the clang of metal and the grind of machinery. The Crown, once a sanctuary for artists, was transformed into a massive forge to fuel the war effort and, in its aftermath, the city’s reconstruction.</p>

<p>The Crown of Crafts, once under House Cannith’s influential sway, found new leadership in independent crafters and salvage gangs following the house’s abandonment during the final years of the Last War. House Cannith’s attempts to return and reassert its authority meets strong resistance, as these crafters and gangs who filled the void fiercely defend their hard-earned independence. This struggle has created a cauldron of tension, as the Crown teeters between acknowledging House Cannith’s legacy and embracing their newfound autonomy.</p>

<h3 id="crown-of-sphinxes-watchful-sentries-and-hidden-enigmas">Crown of Sphinxes: Watchful Sentries and Hidden Enigmas</h3>

<p>The Crown of Sphinxes was once a lyrical sanctuary, home to riddlers and poets who spun mysteries into verse and shrouded wisdom in enigma. Its labyrinthine streets held a mystique that whispered of cryptic puzzles and enticing riddles. However, the grandeur of this district was not immune to the ravages of the Last War. In the strategic turmoil, the Moonfox Brigade, soldiers from House Deneith under the command of the Brelish King, claimed this Crown as their military base.</p>

<p>This militarization has stripped the Crown of Sphinxes of some of its old-world charm. The dazzling and enigmatic architecture has been refitted to serve practical, utilitarian purposes, yet echoes of its former glory persist. Faded etchings, inscriptions of old poems, riddles, and sage wisdom, still adorn the worn stone, serving as a poignant reminder of the Crown’s vibrant past.</p>

<p>Access to the Crown of Sphinxes is strictly regulated. Its streets are patrolled day and night by the ever-watchful eyes of the Moonfox Brigade, maintaining a tight rein on security and order. In this austere environment, House Kundarak maintains its presence, a stalwart amidst the change.</p>

<p>While the Crown of Sphinxes has lost some of its whimsical charm, it stands today as a symbol of resilience and adaptation, a testament to Vathirond’s spirit in the face of adversity. Its layered history has left a rich tapestry of tales, a myriad of riddles yet to be solved.</p>

<h3 id="the-crown-of-jests-echos-of-laugher--whispers-of-pain">The Crown of Jests: Echos of Laugher &amp; Whispers of Pain</h3>

<p>The Crown of Jests once rang with peals of laughter and the clamor of revelry, its streets a lively theater of camaraderie and mirth. Where bars, taverns, and burlesque shows were once the heart of Vathirond’s nightlife, an air of strained cheerfulness now prevails. Laughter and music still flow from its many establishments, but they serve more as a balm for the weary souls seeking an escape from the city’s woes than genuine festivity.</p>

<p>Despite the trials of war and its aftermath, the Crown of Jests sees the most traffic among all the Crowns. It offers a welcome respite for residents and visitors alike, a haven where they can briefly forget their troubles amidst the lively taverns, grand townhouses, and street performances.</p>

<p>In this bustling district, House Ghallanda stands as a beacon of hospitality and resilience. Its enclave thrives amidst the revelry and recovery, the house members taking pride in their steadfast support of Vathirond throughout the hardships. The members of House Ghallanda are considered the unofficial caretakers of the Crown of Jests, their establishments serving as a haven for the city’s weary.</p>

<p>House Orien, on the other hand, holds a dwindling presence around the lightning rail line. Once a thriving nexus connecting the far reaches of Khorvaire, the rail line now ends abruptly at the outskirts of Vathirond, cut off by the hauntingly mysterious wall of mist that is the Mournland. Yet even in its decline, the outpost stands as a testament to a more connected era, a time before war and calamity shattered the unity of the continent.</p>

<p>While the Crown of Jests may have lost some of its former vibrancy, its spirit remains undeterred. It serves as a testament to Vathirond’s enduring will to find joy amidst sorrow, to laugh in the face of despair, and to retain a spark of hope amidst the ruins.</p>

<h3 id="the-gutters-resilience-amid-ruin">The Gutters: Resilience Amid Ruin</h3>

<p>Nestled between the walls of Vathirond’s Crowns, away from the majestic hilltops, lie “The Gutters.” This labyrinth of alleyways and improvised dwellings sprawls across the lower depressions of the city, a stark contrast to the high walls and grand structures above.</p>

<p>The Gutters were once home to the laborers and workers whose toil and sweat fueled the life and vibrancy of the Crowns. These hard-working individuals lived and thrived in the shadow of the hilltops, unshielded by the protective walls that enveloped the Crowns. During the Last War, this vulnerability was exploited, and the Gutters bore the brunt of destruction, time and time again. Buildings were razed, families were uprooted, and the streets echoed with the toll of loss.</p>

<p>In the war’s aftermath, however, The Gutters did not stay silent for long. The area quickly became a refuge for the displaced, the downtrodden, and those holding onto the memories of homes lost to the war. Its winding streets and damaged buildings filled up with makeshift homes, erected by refugees and the city’s poorest citizens. Each structure, no matter how frail or makeshift, stands as a monument to human resilience.</p>

<p>Many of the refugees from Cyre found a haven in The Gutters following The Mourning. Struggling with the memory of their fallen kingdom and unable to move on, they have built a life among the ruins, infusing the area with the spirit of their lost homeland. Despite the hardship, or perhaps because of it, a strong sense of community binds the residents of The Gutters. This unity, borne out of shared suffering and hope, has turned The Gutters into a beating heart of survival within Vathirond.</p>

<p>Now, The Gutters are a testament to the human will to endure. Amidst the battered and patched structures, in the narrow alleyways teeming with life, you find stories of courage, resilience, and the undying hope for a better tomorrow. Even in the bleakest of places, the spirit of Vathirond — indomitable and ever enduring — continues to shine.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/VathirondWarSalvage.png" alt="A human and dwarf woman resting amid piles of salvage." height="480" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Salvagers Resting</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h2 id="dunvar-valley-from-fertile-lands-to-haunted-battlegrounds">Dunvar Valley: From Fertile Lands to Haunted Battlegrounds</h2>

<p>The Dunvar Valley, extending hundreds of miles southeast of Vathirond, is a poignant reminder of the cost of war. Once a lush, verdant gem, it was known for its fertile fields and abundant harvests. The valley was a symbol of prosperity, a testament to the bounty of Khorvaire’s heartlands. But the Last War changed everything.</p>

<p>As one of the most hotly contested frontlines, the Dunvar Valley was transformed into a brutal battleground. The soil, once nurturing crops and life, was stained with the blood of soldiers, churned under the weight of war machines, and scarred by the devastating spells of battle mages. The once peaceful landscape was marred by trenches and fortifications, its tranquility shattered by the relentless drumbeat of conflict.</p>

<p>Today, the Dunvar Valley is a treacherous expanse, a haunting vista of war’s devastating aftermath. The skeletal remains of arcane constructs, broken weapons, and discarded munitions litter the land like grim monuments to the lives lost and the peace that was shattered. This battlefield-turned-graveyard is eerily silent, the quiet only broken by the occasional whistle of the wind or the distant cry of a scavenging bird.</p>

<p>Despite its grim nature, the valley has become a source of livelihood for many of Vathirond’s residents. Salvage crews, hardened by their grim work and driven by necessity, comb through the wreckage, risking their lives to recover anything of value. These individuals, often refugees or those unable to find other work, brave the hidden dangers of the valley - unstable magic, booby traps, rogue constructs, and more. Bitter rivalries between salvage crews often spilling over into violent confrontations, echo the conflicts of the past.</p>

<p>The Dunvar Valley serves as a harsh lesson and a bleak memorial to the Last War. Its shattered landscape is a testament to the destructive force of conflict, a warning of the price of ambition and aggression. Yet, amidst the ruins and desolation, the resilience of its people persists. Despite the hardships, they continue to find ways to survive and even hope for a brighter future. In this, the spirit of the Dunvar Valley, much like Vathirond itself, remains unbroken.</p>

<h2 id="faith-in-vathirond-a-beacon-amid-ruin">Faith in Vathirond: A Beacon Amid Ruin</h2>

<p>Religion and faith play a crucial role in the daily lives of Vathirond’s citizens. The city, though shadowed by devastation and strife, remains a place of profound spiritual diversity and resilience. It is in their faith that many find the strength to face the trials of each day, the courage to endure, and the hope to rebuild.</p>

<p>Vathirond boasts numerous temples dedicated to the Sovereign Host, a testament to the enduring popularity of Khorvaire’s principal religion. These grand structures, though weathered by war and time, continue to be places of comfort, guidance, and community. Worship of the Silver Flame, owing to Vathirond’s proximity to Thrane, is also strongly represented. Despite the damage suffered during the Last War, the city’s largest cathedral remains a shining beacon of faith and charity, a source of healing and solace for the weary and the wounded.</p>

<p>In the wake of the refugee influx following the Last War, the city’s spiritual landscape has become even more diverse. Small shrines devoted to lesser deities have sprouted throughout Vathirond, each a testament to the steadfast faith of its followers. The blend of cultures and traditions brought by the refugees has added to the spiritual tapestry of the city, creating a mosaic of faiths living side by side.</p>

<p>Adding to the city’s spiritual depth are the whispered legends of ancient Dhakaani runes and secret shrines to The Dark Six. These rumors speak of hidden places deep beneath the city, mystical relics from a bygone era. While few can confirm the truth of these tales, they continue to fuel the city’s folklore, piquing the interest of adventurers and scholars alike. Some fear the influence of The Dark Six, while others are drawn to the promise of ancient knowledge and power.</p>

<p>Religion in Vathirond is not just a matter of personal belief, but a cornerstone of community identity and solidarity. Amid the ruins of their city, the people of Vathirond cling to their faith, drawing strength from their deities and from one another. Their unbroken spirit, reflected in their enduring religious practices, lights the way towards a hopeful future.</p>

<h2 id="the-shadow-of-house-phiarlan">The Shadow of House Phiarlan</h2>

<p>House Phiarlan’s schism, which gave rise to House Thuranni, was a wound inflicted on the very heart of Vathirond. With the house’s close ties to the arts, Vathirond was a stronghold for Phiarlan, its vibrant culture a camouflage for the house’s covert activities. The schism turned the city into a battlefield overnight, the conflict fought not on open fields but in shadowed corners and behind closed doors.</p>

<p>This silent, deadly night is now referred to as the “Moonlight Murders” among Vathirond’s citizens. It was a ballet of death as spies and assassins moved like wraiths through the city, leaving a trail of bodies in their wake. The next morning, Vathirond woke to an unspoken horror, death having visited its homes, taverns, brothels, and bathhouses alike.</p>

<p>Despite the horrific events of that night, many believe that not all of House Phiarlan’s secrets were laid bare. Whispers of lost dragonmarked artifacts or vaults of stolen knowlege persist, hidden throughout the city, lying in wait to be discovered by the worthy or the fortunate. These artifacts are said to hold immense power, their recovery a matter of pride and prestige within House Phiarlan.</p>

<p>Today, Vathirond is considered a cursed city by House Phiarlan. The scars of the schism run deep, a constant reminder of the house’s internal strife and the lives lost. Despite this, a small outpost remains in the city, its members performing their duties with a bittersweet mix of resolve and resignation. Sent there as a form of punishment, these Phiarlan members continue their work, providing much-needed cheer through their artistic endeavors and keeping an eye on the developments at the edge of the Mournland. The presence of House Phiarlan, albeit nominal, is a testament to Vathirond’s importance and the house’s resilience in the face of adversity.</p>

<h2 id="factions-in-the-fray">Factions in the Fray</h2>

<p>In the wake of the Last War, new powers have risen within Vathirond:</p>

<p><strong>The Moonfox Brigade</strong>, a formidable assembly of House Deneith mercenaries, operates as the bulwark between Vathirond and the ominous threats emanating from The Mournland. Commissioned directly by the Brelish crown, the Brigade’s presence and authority reverberate across the surrounding lands, instilling a sense of guarded stability. Adorned in uniforms bearing their emblem, a fox silhouetted by a silver moon, these disciplined soldiers uphold their duty with unwavering commitment. Yet, beneath the surface of this professional alliance, an undercurrent of tension exists between the Moonfox Brigade, patrolling the rural outskirts, and the Firehawk Legion, who maintain order within the city’s boundaries. This friction not only reflects conflicting methodologies and jurisdictions, but also the broader political complexities that engulf Vathirond.</p>

<p><strong>Narani Laseur</strong>, the enigmatic figurehead of Vathirond, ascended to her position through a veneer of populism that belied her insatiable hunger for power and wealth. Possessing a shrewd ability to capitalize on the city’s dire straits, she turned the tragedies of war into her own profiteering enterprise, harvesting the spoils from the devastated Dunvar Valley and the skeletal remains of The Mournlands. Such voracious exploitation bred deep fissures within the social fabric of Vathirond, exacerbating the divide between the haves and have-nots. Underpinning her reign, the <strong>Firehawk Legion</strong>, a cadre of Darguun Goblinoid mercenaries, serve as the city’s ostensible protectors. Yet, beneath the surface, they are the clawed arm of Laseur’s cabal, bending the rule of law to the will of their matron, enforcing her decrees without question, and ensuring her tainted prosperity thrives amidst the ruins.</p>

<p><strong>The Goonswarm</strong>, Vathirond’s most formidable salvage gang, casts an imposing shadow over the battered expanse of the Dunvar Valley. Their territory spans the sprawling mudfields and makeshift camps that house scores of migrant workers, many refugees from The Mournlands or displaced from the ravages of the Last War. At the helm of this formidable operation is the indomitable Evalin MacTanni, a figure equally feared and respected. Her unyielding ruthlessness and sharp cunning transformed the Goonswarm from a ragtag assembly of scavengers into a well-oiled salvage machine. MacTanni’s charisma has turned the Dunvar Valley into a kingdom of salvage, extracting wealth from the wreckage, remnants, and refuse of battles past. The scars of war have become her treasure trove, promising riches to those desperate enough to risk life and limb amidst the rusted debris and lingering dangers that permeate the region.</p>

<p><strong>The Odd Fellows</strong> exert their influence in the labyrinthine alleys and shadowy corners of Vathirond. This once-disorganized Thieves Guild, composed of neighborhood gangs, banded together in the wake of the city’s devastation during the Last War, forging order from chaos. Under their flag, smuggling routes thrived, clandestine gambling dens buzzed, and a vibrant black market emerged from the ashes. The Odd Fellows have become an intricate part of Vathirond’s post-war fabric, operating as a shadow government within the city, navigating its underworld with unparalleled savvy. However, this rise to power has sparked tension and conflict, particularly with the Goonswarm. These two formidable entities now stand at odds, clashing over the invaluable territory and the highly lucrative market of “salvaged” goods that the ruined city and its surrounding landscapes provide. The Odd Fellows, masters of stealth and subterfuge, are always prepared to play the long game, their moves as unpredictable as the city’s uncertain future.</p>

<p><strong>The Korranberg Institute for Mournlands Research (KIMR)</strong> is a beacon of hope amidst the ruins of Vathirond. Occupying the remains of the once grand Lonteu Opera House in the Crown of Sirens, KIMR is a huddle of academic rigor and unwavering determination. Comprised of intrepid scholars, skilled wizards, and a cadre of brave souls unafraid to probe the enigmatic Mournlands, they have transformed this erstwhile cultural edifice into a nerve center of knowledge and discovery. Amidst the grandeur of fallen arches and dilapidated galleries, they pursue a mission that’s as daunting as it is crucial: to understand the Mournlands, to peel back the layers of mystery shrouding it, and, ultimately, to unearth ways to heal the scars left by the Last War. The scholars of KIMR, though working in the face of unimaginable devastation and under the shadow of the Mournlands, persist, their pursuits lighting the path towards potential restoration and redemption for Vathirond and perhaps all of Khorvaire.</p>

<div class="text-bg-light mb-3 p-3 lead">
And there you have it – the bones and sinews of a city teetering on the brink, waiting to rise from the ashes or be forever consumed. Should your curiosity be piqued by these broad strokes of Vathirond, I'd be more than willing to delve into the labyrinth of adventures and encounters that were conceived within its Crowns. It's a testament to the city's captivating allure that I find myself yearning to return to its scarred yet resilient streets in any future explorations of Eberron.

Your thoughts and queries are the lifeblood that fuels this chronicle. Don't hesitate to reach out via Twitter if Vathirond has caught your imagination or if you're grappling with burning questions. Your engagement breathes life into these words. Here's to shared adventures and stories yet untold. Until next time, Cheers!
</div>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><category term="Lore" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lore for the City of Vathirond in the Eberron setting.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/VathirondInspiration4.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/VathirondInspiration4.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Experience Matters - The benefits of XP in 5th edition</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/17/the-benefits-of-xp-in-5th-edition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Experience Matters - The benefits of XP in 5th edition" /><published>2023-05-17T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-17T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/17/the-benefits-of-xp-in-5th-edition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/17/the-benefits-of-xp-in-5th-edition/"><![CDATA[<p>In the diverse world of Tabletop Role-Playing Games (TTRPGs), the progression system you choose can significantly influence the way your campaign unfolds. In 5th edition Dungeons &amp; Dragons (D&amp;D), two popular methods of character progression exist: Experience Points (XP) and Milestone Advancement. While Milestone Advancement has its merits, I am here to make a case for XP, an often overlooked, but immensely beneficial system.</p>

<p>In a previous post I discussed the <a href="/2021/02/25/the-zen-of-awarding-experience-for-roleplaying/">Zen of Awarding Experience for Roleplaying</a> which demonstrates an easy method for awarding non-combat experience.  DMs can apply this to exploration or any activity beyond killing creatures. Chapters 8 and 3 of the 5e DMG also provide some guidance on this as well.  I had a recent exchange online that helped me summarize what I see the forgotten benefits of using XP are.  I thought I’d share them here.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/PlayerWithDiceAndPaper.jpg" alt="A player rolling dice and looking over their character sheets." height="480" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<p><strong>Building a World One XP at a Time</strong> <br />
XP connects characters to their actions within the world. Each monster slain, each trap disarmed, every cleverly negotiated encounter, earns the characters XP, helping them grow stronger and more skilled. This system offers a tangible reward for engaging with the world, breathing life into the setting and making it matter to the players.</p>

<p>Milestone advancement, on the other hand, rewards characters simply for reaching certain points in the narrative. While this can create a clear path of progression, it misses a fundamental aspect of immersive role-play: the player’s interaction with the world. Milestone Advancement risks reducing the world to a mere backdrop against which the narrative unfolds, rather than an integral part of the story.</p>

<p><strong>Pacing and Enjoying the Adventure with XP</strong>   <br />
An often overlooked benefit of using XP is its influence on the game’s pacing. By linking character progression to actions within the game, XP allows the pace to ebb and flow naturally. It’s not a rigid timer, but a flexible measure of progress that reflects the story’s rhythm and the players’ actions. This fluidity also encourages players to immerse themselves in the unfolding events rather than racing to level up every few sessions.</p>

<p>Moreover, the XP system allows players to savor the charm of lower level play. Personally, I find D&amp;D 5e most enjoyable at levels 7 or below, with a sweet spot between levels 3 to 5. Using XP slows down the game just enough to let players fully experience the content. It provides players, particularly newcomers, with ample time to familiarize themselves with their class abilities, deepening their connection to the game and enhancing their overall experience.</p>

<p><strong>A Diversity of Incentives</strong>   <br />
XP offers a flexible incentive system that can be tailored to the style of your campaign. Too often, DMs limit XP rewards to combat encounters. However, XP can be a motivating factor for a variety of actions. Award XP for clever problem-solving, negotiating with NPCs, or even for great role-playing moments. This diversity of incentives can drive engagement, encouraging players to think creatively and interact with the world in unique ways.</p>

<p><strong>A Log of Memories</strong>  <br />
Tracking XP can also provide an unexpected benefit: a log of your campaign’s major events. By noting down the sources of XP, you create a record of the group’s achievements and memorable moments. This can add depth to your campaign, fostering a sense of nostalgia and achievement as players look back on their journey.</p>

<p><strong>Addressing D&amp;D’s Reward Structure</strong> <br />
However, it’s also crucial to critique the overall reward structure in D&amp;D 5e. Wizards of the Coast, in their bid to make the game more appealing, have filled character classes with numerous abilities. While this empowers players and adds complexity, it also creates a potential issue.</p>

<p>The plethora of class features reduces the need for external rewards such as magical items or gold, thus diminishing the need for characters to interact with the world. This can lead to characters feeling disconnected from the setting or campaign.</p>

<p>Using XP is a small tool to combat this issue. By tying character progression to specific actions and outcomes, XP can reestablish a tangible connection between the characters and the world. It reintroduces the necessity of exploring, negotiating, and engaging with the campaign setting, fostering a more immersive role-playing experience.</p>

<p><strong>A Word of Caution</strong> <br />
While XP offers numerous benefits, it’s essential to be mindful of what you award XP for. Avoid giving XP for actions that undermine the spirit of the game, such as unnecessary aggression or disruptive behavior. XP is a tool to guide your players, encouraging them to engage in ways that enrich the campaign. Also, don’t fall into the trap of awarding XP to correct <strong>bad</strong> behavior at the table.  Many DMs who use XP look at negative player behavior and think and easy solution is to award experience for things like collaborating or showing up on time.  This seems attractive, but using in game incentives to address out of game issues will always come back to bite you. If there is behavior that needs to be address, do that, but don’t fall into the trap of thinking in game rules will correct bad player behavior.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion</strong>  <br />
In conclusion, XP is more than just a mechanic for character progression. It’s a tool that, when used correctly, can foster engagement, enhance immersion, and create a richer, more rewarding D&amp;D experience. In 5th edition, our tools for connecting players to the world are few. Finding fun ways to do that can help build a more holistic narrative and immersive experience for all.  What do you think though?  How has experience worked for you in the past? Would you be tempted to give XP a try after reading this or are you ride-or-die on Milestone?  Drop me a comment <a href="https://twitter.com/optionalrule" target="_blank">over on twitter</a> to let me know what you think.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Advocating for XP in D&D 5e. this post discusses its role in boosting engagement, diversifying actions, and improving game immersion.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/PlayerWithDiceAndPaper.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/PlayerWithDiceAndPaper.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Origins of the Astral and Ethereal Planes in D&amp;amp;D</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/15/origins-of-the-astral-and-etherial-planes-in-dnd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Origins of the Astral and Ethereal Planes in D&amp;amp;D" /><published>2023-05-15T13:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-15T13:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/15/origins-of-the-astral-and-etherial-planes-in-dnd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/15/origins-of-the-astral-and-etherial-planes-in-dnd/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, <a href="https://twitter.com/dmdavidblog/status/1658104726297165830" target="_blank">DMDavid</a> posed a fascinating question on Twitter about the origins of the <a href="https://www.dndbeyond.com/sources/basic-rules/appendix-d-the-planes-of-existence#TransitivePlanes" target="_blank">Astral and Ethereal Planes</a> in the early editions of Dungeons and Dragons (DnD). As a devoted Tabletop Roleplaying Game enthusiast, I’d like to delve into this intriguing query and shed some light on the cultural and historical influences that shaped these iconic facets of the game.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/transativeplanes.jpg" alt="A man sitting at a desk writing while surrounded by fantasy imagines from their imagination." height="480" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<p>As an side, if you haven’t had a chance to check out <a href="https://dmdavid.com/" target="_blank">DMDavid’s Blog</a>, I highly recommend it.</p>

<p><strong>Understanding the Historical Context</strong>
To truly appreciate the distinction between the Astral and Ethereal planes in DnD, we need to consider the historical context. The inception of DnD occurred during a transformative period in the United States, post the counter-culture revolution, which significantly influenced the game’s development.</p>

<p>This counter-culture era witnessed a surge in a form of pseudo-spiritualism, centered around mind enlightenment and contacting higher planes, starkly contrasting previous generations’ spiritual practices, which were more focused on spirit communication and ancient powers.</p>

<p><strong>The Ethereal and Astral Planes: Inspired by Cultural Icons</strong>
In the minds of the DnD creators, the Ethereal plane became a domain of ghosts and the dead, drawing inspiration from pop culture figures like Aleister Crowley and skeptics like Harry Houdini. Conversely, the Astral Plane symbolized the realm of the mind, influenced by counter-culture figures like Aldous Huxley and Timothy Leary, or popular culture authors like Carlos Castaneda.</p>

<p>As DMDavid rightly noted, the depiction of these planes in DnD also heavily reflects the nerd pop-culture of that time, including elements from comic book characters like Doctor Strange or from movies like the Hammer Horror Films. However, rather than tracing back to a single source, it’s more accurate to understand these planes as a reflection of the era’s prevailing thoughts and influences.</p>

<p><strong>The Game Design Perspective</strong>
From a game design viewpoint, the Ethereal and Astral planes provided a neat division between the realm of ghosts and the realm of psionics. This division addressed two main issues. First, it offered thematic consistency, neatly categorizing monsters and adventure themes. Second, it helped differentiate the rules for magic and ghosts from those for psionics, which were distinct in early D&amp;D.</p>

<p>Interestingly, the original Dungeon Master’s Guide had a staggering 24 planes, slicing not just along alignment lines but also across various narrative tones, such as emotion, thought, spirituality, and more.</p>

<p><strong>The Modern Perspective</strong>
Fast forward to modern D&amp;D, the distinction between the Astral and Ethereal planes seems to have lost much of its significance. The 5th edition (5e) appears to lean towards streamlining gameplay, favoring reduced complexity over the detailed cosmological intricacies of early D&amp;D. For instance, Asmodeus has been elevated as the face of all devils, and the Nine Hells is now the most often cited plane.</p>

<p>While 5e continues to reference other planes, its focus is more on simplifying references for seamless play. This approach contrasts with the early days of D&amp;D, where the cosmology’s complexity was part of the allure, sparking a sense of the unknown in its audience.</p>

<p>In the end, each player must decide whether this shift towards simplification is beneficial. Regardless of the answer, the origins and historical context of the Astral and Ethereal planes in DnD provide a fascinating glimpse into the game’s rich and diverse influences, adding another layer of depth to this already immersive game.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A history of the origins of the astral and ethereal plans in DnD and why they exist.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/transativeplanes.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/transativeplanes.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>