<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-11-09T19:59:52+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Optional Rule</title><subtitle>Optional Rule is a blog for DMs and Players alike of DnD 5e and any tabletop  roleplaying game. It offers rules, insight, analysis, and resources that help people run games and enhance their play.</subtitle><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Statistical Mirage of Advantage in D&amp;amp;D 5th Edition</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/11/09/the-advantage-of-knowing-modifiers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Statistical Mirage of Advantage in D&amp;amp;D 5th Edition" /><published>2023-11-09T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-09T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/11/09/the-advantage-of-knowing-modifiers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/11/09/the-advantage-of-knowing-modifiers/"><![CDATA[<p>Adventurers, gather ‘round the table as we delve into the often misunderstood mechanics of Advantage in Dungeons &amp; Dragons 5th Edition. Introduced as a streamlined method of bonus handling, Advantage allows players to roll a second d20 and choose the higher of the two. On the surface, it seems like a boon to the dice-rolling hopefuls, offering a second arrow in the quiver of chance. But does it truly elevate the players’ prospects, or is it a statistical sleight of hand?</p>

<p>Let’s address the elephant in the room—the Gambler’s Fallacy. This is the mistaken belief that a second roll inherently increases the likelihood of a higher result. Players often fall victim to this misconception, envisioning that elusive natural 20 as just one more roll away. Yet, the truth lies in the principle of Regression to the Mean, which, stripped of its mathematical grandeur, implies that rolling additional d20s is more likely to yield a result closer to the average of 10.5 than the peaks of 20 or the valleys of 1.</p>
<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix p-3 mb-3">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/PlayerWithDiceAndPaper.jpg" alt="A player confused by dice rolls." height="480" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>
<p>Imagine the collective sigh of disappointment if, instead of rolling for Advantage, we declared, “Assume you rolled a 10.” Not very heroic, is it? And yet, statistically, that’s closer to reality. Yes, Advantage provides a statistical bonus, but its impact is heavily skewed by the Difficulty Class (DC) of the task at hand. Lower DCs see an outsized benefit, inflating success rates on tasks that already favored the player, while the effect diminishes as the DC climbs. At a certain point, other bonuses, such as Bardic Inspiration, outshine Advantage, offering more consistent aid against the steeper challenges that heroes should face.</p>

<p>This is precisely where the design of 5th Edition stumbles. By tailoring the system around a DC threshold that rarely exceeds 15, it inadvertently shackles Dungeon Masters, constraining the breadth of difficulty and tension that can be woven into the campaign narrative. We find ourselves in a narrow corridor of challenge, where the drama of high stakes is dulled by the statistical safety net of Advantage.</p>

<p>Moreover, the non-stacking nature of Advantage and Disadvantage further complicates the battlefield. Once you’re locked in the grip of either, any additional factors that would normally tilt the scales become null and void. The result? A disincentive for players to seek creative solutions or take dynamic actions in combat. Why strive for that high ground or cunning feint if your current state of Disadvantage negates any potential benefits? Conversely, why not throw caution to the wind with a whimsical tactic if you’re already basking in the glow of Advantage?</p>

<p>In my 2021 article, “<a href="/2021/01/02/tools-for-effecting-rolls-in-dd/">Tools for Effecting Rolls</a>,” I explored various mechanisms that can influence dice outcomes. The insights gleaned there are particularly pertinent when considering Advantage’s place within the broader spectrum of roll-affecting tools available to players and DMs alike.</p>

<p>For the mathematically curious, the granular details of Advantage’s statistical effects are laid bare in an analysis I’ve set up on AnyDice, which you can explore <a href="https://anydice.com/program/32df7">here</a>. This model elucidates how Advantage impacts roll outcomes across different DCs, providing a clear visual representation of the mechanic’s limitations.</p>

<p>In conclusion, while Advantage was conceived as a simplification, its implications reverberate through the game, subtly undermining both the thrill of chance and the strategic depth of combat. It’s a mechanic that promises heroics but often delivers predictability, a comfort blanket that smothers the flames of daring when it should be fanning them. As we continue to craft our tales of valor and villainy, it’s worth pondering how to elevate our encounters beyond the realm of the ordinary—where the roll of the die is as unpredictable and exciting as the adventures we imagine.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="Analysis" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Adventurers, gather ‘round the table as we delve into the often misunderstood mechanics of Advantage in Dungeons &amp; Dragons 5th Edition. Introduced as a streamlined method of bonus handling, Advantage allows players to roll a second d20 and choose the higher of the two. On the surface, it seems like a boon to the dice-rolling hopefuls, offering a second arrow in the quiver of chance. But does it truly elevate the players’ prospects, or is it a statistical sleight of hand?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/PlayerWithDiceAndPaper.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/PlayerWithDiceAndPaper.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dungeon of the Grieving Mind - Not Your Typical Dungeon!</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/11/04/dungeon-of-the-grieving-mind/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dungeon of the Grieving Mind - Not Your Typical Dungeon!" /><published>2023-11-04T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-04T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/11/04/dungeon-of-the-grieving-mind</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/11/04/dungeon-of-the-grieving-mind/"><![CDATA[<p>Crafting dungeons that deeply resonate with the consequences of character choices? Now, that’s what I call top-notch Dungeon Mastering in Dungeons and Dragons. Inspired by a spirited discussion over on Reddit, I’ve crafted the dungeon you’re about to delve into. My hope? That you’ll find it a thrilling addition to your campaign. The premise is versatile enough to slide right into numerous D&amp;D storylines, whenever innocents have perished in the course of an adventure. An all too common occurrence in most campaigns.</p>

<p><strong>Setup</strong>: Your players, in the thick of battle or perhaps a morally grey situation, have inadvertently caused the death of innocent bystanders. Little do they know, one of the fallen had a sibling: a devoted warlock bound to a mysterious fey from the <a href="https://forgottenrealms.fandom.com/wiki/Shadowfell" target="_blank">Shadowfell</a>. Recognizing the warlock’s anguish, this fey bestows the dungeon you’re about to explore as a “gift” to their loyal servant. Whether your players stumble upon it by sheer chance, through haunting dreams, or any other creative twist you fancy, is all up to you.</p>

<p>This small dungeon is set up assuming a party of 5th level characters but mix and match to your group’s needs.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix p-3 mb-3">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/dungon-entrance_480x600.png" alt="A dark cave leading into a shadowy dungeon." height="600" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<p><strong>Dungeon Theme</strong>: <em>A Grieving Mind</em> - The dungeon is a representation of the vengeful sibling’s psyche. Each section is a manifestation of his grief, anger, and quest for vengeance. This gives you the chance to use environmental dangers, narrative encounters, and emotional challenges instead of relying heavily on traps.</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Entrance - Mourning</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>The entrance is surrounded by soft weeping echoes. Ghostly apparitions of the deceased peasant show their last moments, playing on a loop.</li>
      <li><strong>Enemies</strong> - 5 <a href="https://www.dndbeyond.com/monsters/17010-shadow" target="_blank">Shadows</a> (Yes, the CR is low but with the environmental effect I think it’s fine. Particularly for the first encounter.)</li>
      <li><strong>Environmental Hazard</strong>: A fog slows movement by half, and characters must make a DC 10 Wisdom saving throw at the start of each round or be overwhelmed by feelings of guilt (disadvantage on attacks and checks).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Second Chamber - Anger</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>The large chamber pulses with a fiery rage. Walls appear to be made of burning embers, and the heat is stifling. A guttural sound of someone screaming in rage periodically emanates from a random location in the room where flame erupts.</li>
      <li><strong>Enemies</strong>: None</li>
      <li><strong>Environmental Hazard</strong>: A jagged and uneven chamber, the players must succeed on 3 DC 13 Athletics or Acrobatics checks to successfully cross the room.  Each failure results in 1d10 fire damage.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Third Chamber - Reflection</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>A vast underground lake where the surface acts as a mirror, showing each adventurer their reflection committing their worst mistakes or sins. The players must traverse a narrow stone pathway that sits just at the lakes water level.</li>
      <li><strong>Enemies</strong>: <a href="https://www.dndbeyond.com/monsters/17208-water-weird" target="_blank">Water Weird</a> (see below)</li>
      <li><strong>Encounter</strong>: Each character sees their reflection in the surface of the water and is challenged by it, not as combatants but with questions and accusations, challenging their morals and decisions. If the character tries to respond and defend themselves, they must pass a DC 13 Persuasion check. For every 2 characters that either fail the check, or do not attempt to defend themselves, 1 Water Weird appears and tries to drag a character into the water and drown them. (min 1)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Fourth Chamber - Descent into Madness</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>A twisting labyrinth filled with whispering voices that doubt and belittle the adventurers, trying to make them doubt themselves. The environment and encounter are a recreation of whatever scene originally initiated this dungeon. For example, a party that fights a group of Kobolds but failed to stop them from sacrificing a group of peasants will encounter that scenario again.</li>
      <li><strong>Enemies</strong>: (Whatever enemy the group originally fought)</li>
      <li><strong>Encounter</strong>: The core of this encounter is for the players to relive the original encounter, this time randomly being transformed into the bystanders that lost their lives to realize the experience those people went through.  The characters have a hard time holding onto their sense of self. At the beginning of each round, the player must pass a DC 13 CHA save or be turned into a bystander for a round and are limited to the Commoners stat block.  If they are killed in this form, they return to their true self, prone on the ground, minus whatever damage they took, but can act normally.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Final Chamber - Heart of Darkness</strong>:
    <ul>
      <li>The center of the sibling’s grief. A blackened stone room where the shadow horror resides.</li>
      <li><strong>Enemies</strong>: Shadow Horror (use the <a href="https://www.dndbeyond.com/monsters/16971-oni" target="_blank">Oni</a> stat-block), 2 <a href="https://www.dndbeyond.com/monsters/17131-shadow-demon" target="_blank">Shadow Demons</a>.</li>
      <li><strong>Encounter</strong>: The sibling is there, having been transformed into a shadowy horror, a manifestation of their grief and desire for revenge turned into a dark entity. There is an opportunity for the DM to get creative here in how they want to end this, it should match whatever common theme is used in the campaign.  For example, upon being defeated the soul of the sibling rises and is confronted by the souls of their lost family who look at them with disappointment and grief as the siblings soul is dragged away to the Shadowfell by shadowy creatures.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>That’s it, with a bit of tweaking this is a simple adventure a DM could drop into almost any campaign.  Personally, I enjoy themed adventures that are a bit different and have a narrative undertone.  I hope you might find this useful as well.</p>

<p>Now get out there and run some great games.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="Encounters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore a dynamic Dungeons and Dragons dungeon inspired by player choices, where a warlock seeks retribution for their fallen kin.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/dungon-entrance_480x600.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/dungon-entrance_480x600.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Narrative Landscapes - More Engaging TTRPG Travel</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/07/23/painting-geography-with-narrative/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Narrative Landscapes - More Engaging TTRPG Travel" /><published>2023-07-23T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-23T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/07/23/painting-geography-with-narrative</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/07/23/painting-geography-with-narrative/"><![CDATA[<p>The art of travel in Tabletop Roleplaying Games remains a perennial favorite in community discussions. Despite my earlier posts on constructing <a href="/2021/07/13/perilous-journeys-in-5e-p1/">Perilous Journeys in D&amp;D 5e</a>, the conversation must go beyond mere obstacles and challenges. The true crux lies in the marriage of narrative and geography - a fusion that is underscored yet often lacks actionable guidance. So, how can we elevate the routine task of terrain description into a thrilling spark for player immersion? Let’s dive in.</p>

<p>Traditional narrative often falls into one of two traps: outlining the minutiae of geography or focusing heavily on terrain-oriented challenges. But both miss out on an essential element: potential adventure and side quests within the landscape. This bridge is exactly what we aim to build today.</p>
<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix p-3 mb-3">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/narrative-terrain_480x679.png" alt="A winding road through hills, headed towards mountains. Ruins and freshly cut logs by the roadside." height="679" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>
<h2 id="landscape-as-a-gateway-to-adventure">Landscape as a Gateway to Adventure</h2>

<p>When narrating geography, it’s not just about describing the environment. The landscape is an entity in itself, teeming with tales of bygone eras, potential adventures, and hidden secrets. Incorporating these elements into your narrative can make your players’ journey far more compelling.</p>

<p>Let’s say your adventurers are heading to Phandalin. Instead of describing it as a simple pathway towards the mountains, through increasingly steep hills, we can breathe life into this journey. Imagine instead: “You follow a narrow yet well-trodden road, winding its way towards distant, hulking mountains, snaking through gentle, tree-speckled hills. Although the roadway seems relatively young, deep-set ruts hint at heavy carts traversing this route with surprising frequency. Fortified rest stops pepper the roadside, silent sentinels in the wild, several bearing the brutal scars of past attacks.”</p>

<p>Similarly, as your adventurers approach the Sword Mountains, don’t limit the description to facts. Try this: “The landscape transforms dramatically as towering, jagged peaks capped with virgin snow thrust upwards from the lush, chaotic hills below. A testament to a turbulent history, abandoned fortresses dot the mountainsides, while evidence of beast lairs and old encampments sprawl across their ancient ruins.”</p>

<h2 id="implied-encounters-and-more">Implied Encounters and More</h2>

<p>Beyond the allure of detailed descriptions, these narratives hint at potential encounters that might lie ahead. They stoke curiosity, enticing players to delve deeper, exploring the whispers of hidden treasures or mysteries tucked away within the folds of the world.</p>

<p>The heavy usage of the roadway to Phandalin implies significant commerce, but why are these rest stops fortified, and who or what attacked them? Those abandoned fortresses in the Sword Mountains – who built them, and why were they deserted? What kinds of creatures might inhabit these mountains now? Builing off of this concept, there are any number of ways a thoughtful GM might be able to incorporate suggestive descriptions into their terrain.</p>

<p>Think about what a passing game trail that looks like a large creature barreled down it recently, was that creature chasing something or running from something?  What about thin trails of smoke suggesting small camps in the miles of wilderness surrounding the players?  Birds stirred up in the woods by something or absent altogether, a patch of landscape burned in the shape of a fan of flames or deep claw marks in a landing spot, fetishes hanging in the trees marking some territory or the remains of unfortunate travelers who might shared the parties fate?  These are all great ways to imply a story to be had in the area, build tension or suggest help, and give players more to think about between encounters.</p>

<p>By leaving these narrative hooks, you provide the players with a world that reacts and evolves around them. They may decide to investigate the fortified rest stops or seek out help from local tribes to explore those abandoned fortresses. Your players are no longer simply crossing a landscape – they’re interacting with it, making decisions based on the environment and context you’ve provided.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Geography in TTRPGs is not merely a backdrop or obstacle course but a world ripe with potential adventures. Shifting our narrative focus from straightforward descriptions to providing context and implied adventures allows players to experience the landscape in a much more immersive and dynamic way. The key lies in treating the geography as an integral part of your world’s history and its future – a character in its own right with secrets to reveal, battles to recount, and adventures to offer. Your landscapes are not just set pieces; they’re a canvas for countless stories waiting to unfold.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Enhance your TTRPGs with immersive, narrative-driven travel. Transform landscapes from mere backdrops to catalysts for adventure and player engagement.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/narrative-terrain_480x679.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/narrative-terrain_480x679.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Summon the Unusual - 3 New Spells for DnD 5e</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/28/arcane-servant-spells/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Summon the Unusual - 3 New Spells for DnD 5e" /><published>2023-06-28T09:40:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-28T09:40:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/28/arcane-servant-spells</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/28/arcane-servant-spells/"><![CDATA[<p>As a fan of magically animated minions, I’ve always felt somewhat limited by the options available in the 5th edition of Dungeons and Dragons. If you’re intrigued by the idea of a “pet” class in D&amp;D, your primary option is to become a Necromancer and use Animate Dead. However, the image of a group of shambling undead isn’t always what players envision. Given the rich narrative tradition of casters animating objects, constructs, or elements, it’s perplexing that these options aren’t more prevalent in the game.</p>

<p>To address this conundrum, I’ve incorporated three new spells into my games. They maintain balance with Animate Dead, offer compelling options for casters, and inject an element of arcane flavor into the gameplay. Allow me to share these additions with you.</p>

<blockquote class="stat-block">
  <h4 id="animated-weapon">Animated Weapon</h4>
  <p><em>3rd-level Transmutation</em></p>

  <hr />

  <ul>
    <li><strong>Casting Time:</strong> 1 minute</li>
    <li><strong>Attack/Save:</strong> None</li>
    <li><strong>Range:</strong> 10 ft</li>
    <li><strong>Components:</strong> V, S, M (A target one-handed melee weapon)</li>
    <li><strong>Duration:</strong>  24 hours</li>
  </ul>

  <hr />

  <p>This spell imbues a mundane, one-handed melee weapon with potent magical energy, bringing it to life as an animated weapon. The weapon’s statistics and abilities are based on the Flying Sword as described in the Monster Manual, with the following exceptions: The damage and damage type of the animated weapon are determined by the mundane weapon type on which the spell is cast. Additionally, the caster may add their main casting ability modifier to the damage, and the weapon attacks using the caster’s melee spell attack bonus.</p>

  <p>Once the spell is cast, the animated weapon becomes sentient and recognizes you as its master. It will dutifully follow your commands and fight on your behalf. As a bonus action on your turn, you can mentally command the weapon to move and attack a target within its reach. The weapon will continue attacking that target until it is defeated, it is given a new command, or your concentration on the spell ends. If the weapon’s hit points are reduced to 0, it is destroyed, and the spell ends.</p>

  <p>The animated weapon remains under your control for the duration of the spell, but it requires your concentration while being commanded. If your concentration is broken, the weapon falls to the ground and becomes an ordinary inanimate weapon until you regain concentration to command it once more.</p>

  <p>At Higher Levels. When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the damage increases by one weapon die for every two slot levels above 3rd.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="stat-block">
  <h4 id="clockwork-servant">Clockwork Servant</h4>
  <p><em>3rd-level Conjuration</em></p>

  <hr />

  <ul>
    <li><strong>Casting Time:</strong> 1 minute</li>
    <li><strong>Attack/Save:</strong> None</li>
    <li><strong>Range:</strong> 10 ft</li>
    <li><strong>Components:</strong> V, S, M (10 gp scrap metal and parts)</li>
    <li><strong>Duration:</strong>  24 hours</li>
  </ul>

  <hr />

  <p>This spell creates a loyal clockwork servant, imbuing a significant source of scrap metal. The servant takes on the form and aesthetics determined by the caster’s wishes, while inheriting the abilities and characteristics of a Modron. Consult with the game master for the specific statistics of the construct servant.</p>

  <p>On each of your turns, you can use a bonus action to mentally command any clockwork servant created by this spell, as long as it is within 60 feet of you. If you control multiple servants, you can command any or all of them simultaneously, issuing the same command to each one. You decide the construct’s actions and movement for its next turn, or you can give a general command, such as guarding a specific area. In the absence of specific commands, the construct defends itself against hostile creatures. Once a command is given, the servant continues to follow it until its task is complete.</p>

  <p>The construct servant remains under your control for 24 hours. After this duration, it degrades into component parts. To maintain control of a construct servant for an additional 24 hours, you must cast this spell on it again before the current 24-hour period ends. When you do so, you can reassert your control over up to four servants you have created with this spell, instead of creating new ones.</p>

  <p>If the spell expires, or when destroyed, a caster may recover 1d10 gp worth of material from the remnants of a servant.</p>

  <p><strong>At Higher Levels.</strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, you can create or reassert control over two additional construct servants for each slot level above 3rd.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="stat-block">
  <h4 id="elemental-servant">Elemental Servant</h4>
  <p><em>3rd-level Evocation</em></p>

  <hr />

  <ul>
    <li><strong>Casting Time:</strong> 1 minute</li>
    <li><strong>Attack/Save:</strong> None</li>
    <li><strong>Range:</strong> 10 ft</li>
    <li><strong>Components:</strong> V, S, M (source element of creature)</li>
    <li><strong>Duration:</strong>  24 hours</li>
  </ul>

  <hr />

  <p>This spell creates a loyal elemental servant, imbuing a significant source of earth, fire, air, or water within range with arcane animus and the semblance of life. The servant takes the form of a Mud, Steam, or Smoke Mephit, determined by the element used during the casting of the spell. Refer to the game master for the creature’s statistics.</p>

  <p>On each of your turns, you can use a bonus action to mentally command any servant created by this spell as long as it is within 60 feet of you. If you control multiple servants, you can command any or all of them simultaneously, issuing the same command to each one. You decide the creature’s actions and movement for its next turn, or you can give a general command, such as guarding a specific chamber or corridor. In the absence of specific commands, the creature defends itself against hostile creatures. Once a command is given, the servant continues to follow it until its task is complete.</p>

  <p>The servant remains under your control for 24 hours. After this duration, it no longer obeys your commands. To maintain control of a servant for an additional 24 hours, you must cast this spell on it again before the current 24-hour period ends. When you do so, you can reassert your control over up to four creatures you have animated with this spell, rather than creating new ones.</p>

  <p><strong>At Higher Levels.</strong> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, you can animate or reassert control over two additional creatures for each slot level above 3rd.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="integration-and-discovery">Integration and Discovery:</h2>
<p>To amplify the sense of adventure and discovery, I weave these spells into the fabric of the narrative instead of presenting them as standard spells accessible to all. I create opportunities for players to uncover these spells through their in-game actions. They might discover them as forgotten wisdom within a concealed library, earn them as accolades for gaining admission into a renowned wizard’s guild, or retrieve them from the ancient scrolls nestled in a formidable dragon’s treasure trove. By tying the procurement of these spells to the storyline, I instill an extra layer of intrigue and thrill, enriching my players’ journey. I think you can too.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>These spells open some fun possibilities for arcane spellcasters, providing players the opportunity to control flavorful arcane servants. With a sprinkle of creativity, you could even extend these spells to encompass additional schools of magic. Remember to find fun ways to weave these into your campaign, making them a rewarding part of the adventure. If concerns about power creep arise, you can always introduce a material component cost or other means to regulate the spell’s use within the world. Ultimately, I believe players seeking this type of interaction will find these spells tremendously enjoyable.</p>

<p>Now get out there and run some great games!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore new servant summoning spells for DnD 5e! This post introduces three innovative spells, adding depth and fun to your arcane gameplay.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/young_adult_wizard_scribing.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/young_adult_wizard_scribing.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Gritty Survival in 5e - Breathing life into Death Saves</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/19/revisiting-death-saves-in-5e/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gritty Survival in 5e - Breathing life into Death Saves" /><published>2023-06-19T14:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-19T14:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/19/revisiting-death-saves-in-5e</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/19/revisiting-death-saves-in-5e/"><![CDATA[<p>Ever found yourself scratching your head over the peculiarities of the Death Save system in Dungeons and Dragons (DnD) 5e? In particular, how the system seems disconnected from the gameplay and action. It can seem counter-intuitive when zero hit points result in the same outcome for any character, regardless of how they arrived there. The Death Save min-game is the same, whether you’ve taken a single point of damage, or sustained a catastrophic 150-foot fall. In this post, I aim to dissect the effects of this system on the game and propose a house rule that could shake things up to make the prospect of death an exciting part of the action again.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix p-3 mb-5">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/wounded_character_480x720.jpg" alt="A wounded warrior crawling on the ground with an arrow sticking out of their side." height="720" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<h2 id="death-saves-in-action">Death Saves in Action</h2>

<p>Under the standard 5e DnD rules, when you hit 0 HP you start rolling an unmodified D20 (in most cases) once you hit 0 HP, with a 10 or higher marking a success and a 9 or lower signifying a failure. The odds are slightly in favor of success (55%) than failure (45%) on each roll. After you accumulate three of either outcome, your fate is sealed. So you have a 60% chance of survival, with 18% of those possibly regaining consciousness at 1 HP. Most of these rolls resolve themselves within four turns, although Healing Word makes most of that irrelevant anyway.</p>

<p>While this system allows for players to quickly rejoin the action, it doesn’t necessarily add to the excitement of the encounter if reaching 0 HP doesn’t carry much risk. In fact, the urgency for other players to save you diminishes as you’re not under immediate threat. In fact, I would suggest that this was so devoid of tension that Healing Word was designed the way it was just so you didn’t have to interact much with the system. To me, this illustrates how rules can cascade across the system, reducing tension and lessening the importance of team interdependence.</p>

<h2 id="house-rule-positive-experiences-through-negative-hit-points">House Rule: Positive Experiences through Negative Hit Points</h2>

<p>I used a House Rule in my 3E days that I think could easily be adapted in 5E. This rule ties the risk of death more closely to the level of action, buts more managed uncertainty back into an encounter, and encourages collective responsibility for the group’s survival.</p>

<p>A character can drop negative HP up to their Constitution (CON) score plus level, before they succumb to death. When a character’s HP drop below 0 and they haven’t yet stabilized, they need to make a CON save. The difficulty class (DC) for this save is equal to their current negative hit point total. Failure results in the character’s demise, while a successful save inflicts 1 point of damage. Achieving success on two saves stabilizes the character at their present negative HP value.</p>

<p>Any healing received that doesn’t elevate the character to 0 HP or above, counts as a single successful save towards stabilization.</p>

<p>Characters with a negative HP value up to their CON modifier must remain prone and are unable to take bonus actions or reactions until their hit points return  above 0.</p>

<p><em>DMs may want to consider removing the Healing Word spell from the game or reducing it to just 1d4 of healing, otherwise this is needless complexity without changing things much.</em></p>

<h2 id="effect-on-play">Effect on Play</h2>

<p>Does this house rule make the game more “realistic?” Not necessarily. HP in DnD isn’t designed to mimic reality. Instead, it sets the tone of the game. Under this rule, stabilization could be achieved after a few successful rolls - relatively simple at -1 HP, but quite challenging at -15 HP.</p>

<p>This rule adds a sense of urgency and heightened risk to the game play. The deeper into the negatives you go, the harder it is for you to recover. Healing now has a significant effect, and the scale of the healing can make a significant difference.  Even Healing Word is helpful, but not as over powered as many lament.</p>

<p>The heightened stakes inspire more caution as characters become more wounded and make players more invested in their downed teammates’ outcomes. Ultimately, this gives players more reasons to interact, and damage becomes more than a countdown to zero HP.</p>

<p>In other words, downing a hero is back to being a significant event in combat, as it should be.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>While the 5e Death Save system serves its purpose, its disconnect from the action in an encounter and lack of urgency can leave some players wanting more. By revisiting an older house rule, I think we can add back some tension, interactivity, and adjust the tone of encounters so they feel like something is at stake again.</p>

<p>In the end, it’s about the feel of your game. Does the standard Death Save system work for your group, or could you benefit from tweaking the rules to spice things up? I’d love to hear your thoughts and experiences, so feel free to reach out to me on Twitter!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><category term="gritty survival" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the peculiarities of DnD's 5e Death Save system and discover a riveting house rule that adds urgency and deepens gameplay interaction]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/wounded_character_480x720.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/wounded_character_480x720.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Decoding D&amp;amp;D - The Enigma of Armor Class</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/16/abstract-nature-of-ac/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decoding D&amp;amp;D - The Enigma of Armor Class" /><published>2023-06-16T12:17:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-16T12:17:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/16/abstract-nature-of-ac</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/16/abstract-nature-of-ac/"><![CDATA[<p>Delving into the oft-debated mechanics of Dungeons and Dragons (D&amp;D), it’s hard to overlook the perennial discussion points: Armor Class (AC) and Hit Points (HP). While they may seem simple on the surface, these fundamental aspects of D&amp;D often engender misunderstandings and heated debates. Armor Class, though instinctively viewed as a gauge of whether a character is struck or not, is in fact a more abstract concept. Following my recent post <a href="/2023/06/02/what-are-hit-points-in-dnd/">What are HPs in D&amp;D anyway?</a>, it’s fitting that we now unpack the intricacies of AC and its symbiotic relationship with HP - the two crucial pillars that underpin the game’s combat system.</p>
<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix p-3 mb-5">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/the_duel_480x720.png" alt="Black and white art of two women dueling." height="720" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Rock, Paper, Greatsword!</figcaption>
    
</figure>
<h2 id="the-genesis-of-armor-class">The Genesis of Armor Class</h2>

<p>The genesis of AC in D&amp;D dates back to the game’s wargaming origins, where combat was typically a binary concept - either a unit was victorious or it was defeated. But as D&amp;D emerged, focusing on individual combat encounters instead of unit battles, a more intricate system was called for. To build and sustain tension for individual characters throughout an adventure, a ‘tug of war’ mechanic was introduced, wherein the game sought to quantify both a character’s resilience HP and the time needed to overcome them. Hence, Armor Class was born.</p>

<p>In Original D&amp;D (OD&amp;D), AC represented the challenge of landing a damaging hit on your character. However, it left the concept of a ‘hit’ undefined. Was it a sword deflecting off plate armor? A deft evasion? A streak of divine luck? The rulebook intentionally remained silent on these specifics, emphasizing AC’s inherent abstraction.</p>

<p>It’s important to appreciate that the architects of D&amp;D were well aware of the ‘swinginess’ of D20s. They understood that setting up a damage over time mechanic, regulated by the frequency of hits and the strength of attacks, was the most effective way to offset this inherent randomness. This allowed Adventures to be risky, but not random. An incredibly important element of TTRPG game design, if you wanted players to invest in their characters.</p>

<h2 id="armor-class-defining-its-abstraction">Armor Class: Defining its Abstraction</h2>

<p>As the D&amp;D editions evolved, the ambiguity of AC continued. Some players interpreted it as purely physical protection - the better the armor, the higher the AC. But armor could be bulky and restrictive. How would that account for the nimbleness of an unarmored monk? Or the ability of a rogue to evade attacks? Here’s where the abstraction comes into play.</p>

<p>AC is not just about physical armor. It encapsulates all the factors that might prevent a character from taking damage - natural agility, training, magical protection, divine favor, sheer luck, and yes, wearing a sturdy suit of armor. But, like HP, it’s not literally any of these things. It’s a mechanical tool that enables players to visualize their characters surviving in a dangerous world.</p>

<h2 id="the-dance-of-ac-and-hp">The Dance of AC and HP</h2>

<p>The relationship between AC and HP forms the basis of the D&amp;D Damage Over Time system. A character’s AC determines how likely they are to evade damage, while HP defines how much damage they can withstand before being defeated.</p>

<p>To illustrate, imagine a heavily armored knight (high AC, high HP) and a lightly armored rogue (lower AC, lower HP). The knight, with their superior armor, can absorb more hits before their HP depletes. In contrast, the rogue relies on their agility to avoid hits, mitigating the need for a large HP pool. Neither is invincible - the knight might face a foe with an accurate strike, and the rogue could encounter an enemy with an area attack that’s hard to dodge.</p>

<p>However, it’s vital to understand that AC isn’t a literal damage reduction. A higher AC doesn’t directly decrease the damage you take - but higher AC does mean you’ll take less damage over time. In this way, the single simple AC value serves the narrative role of damage reduction, as miss, or just toughing it out. Similarly, a high HP doesn’t mean you can shrug off a dragon’s fire breath - it represents your ability to avoid the worst of the attack, keep going despite the pain, or recover quickly.</p>

<h2 id="unshackling-the-abstraction">Unshackling the Abstraction</h2>

<p>It’s worth repeating that both AC and HP are mechanical tools for the game, not narrative shackles. They offer a game-friendly way to handle the complex, chaotic nature of combat without bogging down in ultra-realism that could hinder gameplay.</p>

<p>As the DM, it’s your job to help the mechanics flow into the narrative to best fit your campaign’s tone. You could describe the dodges and near misses for a rogue with high AC, or the punishing blows that a knight absorbs through heavy armor and sheer toughness. In other words, the mechanics tension and provides momentum to a scene without getting in the way of the narrative tone of the game.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion-embrace-the-abstract">Conclusion: Embrace the Abstract</h2>

<p>Attempting to pin down AC in literal terms is a pure madness. Much like HPs, AC is best understood as an abstraction. Representative of various factors contributing to your character’s survivability in combat. It’s not simply the quality of a character’s armor, nor their ability to dodge, but a mix of physical, skillful, and even supernatural factors. It’s all of it, or none of it depending on how it fits the tone of your game.</p>

<p>Rules play a pivotal role in defining the tone, pace, and action in a TTRPG. At some point, most D&amp;D fans question the abstract nature of AC and HP, wondering why armor doesn’t directly mitigate damage. While damage reduction systems can be enjoyable, D&amp;D offers two broad alternatives: reduce damage per hit or leverage AC to apply damage less frequently. Both approaches yield similar outcomes, but AC achieves this without adding further mathematical steps, underlining its design simplicity.</p>

<p>And so, dear reader, as with Hit Points, I encourage you to embrace the abstract nature of Armor Class. It’s a tool, a game mechanic designed to simulate the unpredictability and risk of combat in a fantasy world. It’s there help build a narrative through game play, because you don’t need a lesson in impact physics, you need a trilling duel in the streets of Neverwinter!  Use it as such, and weave it into your narrative in a way that enhances your game, not restricts it. Happy gaming!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="Analysis" /><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the abstraction of Armor Class in D&D, its roots in wargaming, and its dance with Hit Points.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/the_duel_480x720.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/the_duel_480x720.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Malevolent Monsters - Rage Husk</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/16/monster-rage-husk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Malevolent Monsters - Rage Husk" /><published>2023-06-16T11:45:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-16T11:45:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/16/monster-rage-husk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/16/monster-rage-husk/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome, intrepid Dungeon Masters, to the next thrilling addition to our bespoke bestiary: <strong>The Rage Husk</strong>. This terrifying creature is no standard zombie; it’s a psychic construct, the haunting aftermath of a <a href="/2023/05/24/monster-mind-reaver/">Mind Reaver</a>’s psychic assault. Incorporating elements of D&amp;D 4e’s Minion mechanics, Rage Husks serve as a swarm of formidable adversaries that, while dispatched with a single blow, offer a uniquely relentless and ruthless challenge. Join us as we delve into the grim lore of these dreadful entities and explore how they can elevate your campaign, introducing fresh layers of tension, suspense, and strategic complexity. Embrace the dread, harness the horror, and let your adventurers feel the chill of the Mind Reaver’s shadow with the introduction of the Rage Husk.</p>

<h2 id="rage-husks">Rage Husks</h2>
<p>In the labyrinthine depths of chaotic realms, there dwell malevolent entities known as a <a href="/2023/05/24/monster-mind-reaver/">Mind Reaver</a>. These beings, aberrations formed from failed attempts to create Mind Flayers, weave their own brand of dark, psychic terror. It’s in their destructive wake that the unfortunate victims are morphed into the monstrosities known as Rage Husks.</p>

<p>Robbed of their sanity and consciousness by the Mind Reavers, the victims are left with nothing but an echo of the pain and fury experienced in their final cognizant moments. This torment is reshaped into a fearsome determination to destroy, creating a formidable, mindless husk fueled by pure rage.</p>

<p>Rage Husks are often found scattered across the aftermath of a Mind Reaver attack, a chilling reminder of their terrifying power. Furthermore, within the treacherous lairs of these vile creatures, the Mind Reavers maintain a fragile control over the Rage Husks, utilizing them as part of their defensive strategies. As your group delves deeper into these chaotic territories, brace yourself for encounters with these tortured beings, their relentless pursuit a testament to the horrors of the Mind Reaver’s touch.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/monsters/RageHusk_407x610.png" alt="A raging and twisted humanoid running toward the viewer." height="610" width="407" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">A Rage Husk</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<blockquote class="stat-block wide">
  <h2 id="rage-husk">Rage Husk</h2>
  <p><em>Medium abomination, chaotic evil; (Minion)</em></p>

  <hr />

  <ul>
    <li><strong>Armor Class</strong> 11</li>
    <li><strong>Hit Points</strong> 19 (3d8 + 6)</li>
    <li><strong>Speed</strong> 30 ft.</li>
  </ul>

  <hr />

  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th style="text-align: center">STR</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">DEX</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">CON</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">INT</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">WIS</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">CHA</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: center">13 (+1)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">14 (+2)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">12 (+1)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">3 (-4)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">6 (-2)</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">5 (-3)</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>

  <hr />
  <ul>
    <li><strong>Saving Throws</strong> DEX +4</li>
    <li><strong>Damage Vulnerabilities</strong> Psychic</li>
    <li><strong>Condition Immunities</strong> Charmed, Frightened</li>
    <li><strong>Senses</strong> Passive perception 8</li>
    <li><strong>Languages</strong> –</li>
    <li><strong>Challenge</strong> 1/2 (100 XP)</li>
  </ul>

  <h3 id="abilities">Abilities</h3>
  <p><strong><em>Mindless Aggression.</em></strong> As a bonus action, the rage husk can move up to its speed toward a hostile creature that it can see.</p>

  <p><strong><em>Tackler.</em></strong> The rage husk has advantage on any shove or grapple action if it has moved 10 feet or more in a straight line toward the target that turn.</p>
  <h3 id="actions">Actions</h3>
  <p><strong><em>Multiattack.</em></strong> The rage husk makes two slam attacks.</p>

  <p><strong><em>Slam.</em></strong> Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 4 (1d6 + 1) bludgeoning damage.</p>

  <h3 id="reactions">Reactions</h3>
  <p><strong><em>Overwhelm.</em></strong>  The rage husk may make a single slam attack against a creature as soon as it successfully grapples them or knocks them prone.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="mastering-minions-a-page-from-dds-4e-playbook">Mastering Minions: A Page from D&amp;D’s 4e Playbook</h3>

<p>Calling all Dungeon Masters seeking to elevate their combat encounters! Let’s revisit a technique from D&amp;D’s 4th edition that’s making a modern comeback, including in <a href="https://shop.mcdmproductions.com/collections/flee-mortals-the-mcdm-monster-book" target="_blank">MCDM’s ‘Flee Mortals’</a> book: the mighty Minion rule. This simple rule is your key to creating scenes of epic, heroic battles: minions, despite behaving like standard monsters, fall with just one successful hit. But don’t discard the minion’s hit points just yet. These still matter for spells like Sleep, which operate based on HP.</p>

<p>Whether it’s a horde of minions, or adding spice to a boss battle, the Minion rule can turn a routine encounter into a memorable tale of heroic warfare. Harness this tool, and let’s take your game to the next level!</p>

<h2 id="using-rage-husks">Using Rage Husks</h2>
<p>Imagine unleashing a torrent of Rage Husks against your unsuspecting party, creating a frantic and intense combat scenario where waves of these formidable yet easily dispatchable enemies push the heroes to their limits. Even the mightiest of warriors can be overwhelmed by sheer numbers, testing not just their strength, but their endurance and tactical acumen as well. Rage Husks also serve as formidable minions when under the control of a powerful adversary like a Mind Reaver, adding a dangerous layer to an already challenging boss fight. But don’t limit yourself to what’s written here - let your imagination run wild! These psychic zombies could be the consequence of a cursed item, a magical effect gone wrong, or a myriad of other creative plot devices. So go ahead, unleash the Rage Husks and let the heroic chaos unfold!</p>

<h3 id="adventure-seeds">Adventure Seeds</h3>
<p>Here are some adventure seeds you can use to incorporate Rage Husks into your adventure.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Cursed Heirloom:</strong> An antique necklace recently acquired by a noble family is actually a cursed item that transforms its wearers into Rage Husks. Can the party find a way to reverse the curse before the entire family is affected?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Madness Below:</strong> A mining town reports strange occurrences in the depths of their mines – miners turning into Rage Husks. The party must delve into the depths and discover the cause before it’s too late.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Blood Moon Ritual:</strong> During every Blood Moon, a deranged wizard’s failed experiments result in the creation of Rage Husks. Can the party stop the wizard before the next moon rise?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Crumbling Stronghold:</strong> In an ancient fortress, the party finds a horde of Rage Husks, mindlessly guarding something. What secrets are they protecting and can the party uncover them?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Towering Silence:</strong> An entire city suddenly falls quiet, and an army of Rage Husks are the only residents. The party must uncover what turned the citizens and if there’s a way to restore them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Lost Expedition:</strong> An archaeological expedition in ancient ruins has disappeared. Their last message spoke of strange, rage-filled creatures. Can the party rescue the lost archaeologists and confront the Rage Husks?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Wailing Forest:</strong> A haunted forest has started birthing Rage Husks from its mists. The party must find the source of this curse and put an end to it.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Puppeteer’s Game:</strong> A Mind Reaver is using Rage Husks as pawns in its deadly game. Can the party navigate the treacherous lair, defeat the Rage Husks, and stop the Mind Reaver?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Abandoned Monastery:</strong> Monks of a secluded monastery have become Rage Husks after dabbling with forbidden magic. Can the party cleanse the monastery and break the cycle of transformation?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Plagued Harbor:</strong> A cursed artifact brought into a bustling port city is slowly transforming its inhabitants into Rage Husks. The party must identify the artifact and break its curse to save the city.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Now get out there and run some great games!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><category term="Monsters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Unearth the chilling world of Rage Husks in DnD! Discover lore, encounter tactics, and adventure seeds for these psychic zombies of the Underdark.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/monsters/RageHusk_407x610.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/monsters/RageHusk_407x610.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Pitch Perfect - Using a Pitch Deck for Your D&amp;amp;D Campaign</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/10/campaign-pitch-decks/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pitch Perfect - Using a Pitch Deck for Your D&amp;amp;D Campaign" /><published>2023-06-10T10:46:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-10T10:46:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/10/campaign-pitch-decks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/10/campaign-pitch-decks/"><![CDATA[<p>Launching a new Dungeons &amp; Dragons campaign is no small feat. It requires not only the arduous task of finding players, but also identifying those who are the perfect fit for your envisioned adventure. Even before delving into character backgrounds, safety tools, or other vital session zero elements, a Dungeon Master’s first hurdle is convincing potential players to invest their precious time and energy into the unfolding saga. This initial step bears striking similarity to pitching a fresh product or service. Just as entrepreneurs entice investors with the promise of innovation and value, DMs need to captivate potential players with a compelling campaign concept. Enter the Pitch Deck - a tool commonly used in the business world, but equally potent in setting the stage for a thrilling D&amp;D campaign.</p>

<p>Indeed, a Pitch Deck isn’t mandatory. You could create a written summary instead. The advantage of a deck, however, is its brevity and focus on essentials. Regardless of format, the aim stays the same. We’ll conclude with a template to help you craft your own pitch, be it a Deck or a Summary.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix p-3 mb-5">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/CharactersCelebratingAtTable_480x480.png" alt="A group of adventurers in a tavern with a leader giving an inspirational speech." height="480" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Run the game in your heart.</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h2 id="what-is-a-pitch-deck">What is a Pitch Deck?</h2>

<p>A pitch deck is a short presentation that shows off your unique game idea. It gives people a sneak peek into your game’s style, story, changes to rules, schedule, and other key parts that make your game special.</p>

<p>Although your D&amp;D game doesn’t need money from investors, a pitch deck is still very useful. It helps you get people excited to play and willing to spend their valuable time on your game.</p>

<h2 id="creating-a-dd-campaign-pitch-deck">Creating a D&amp;D Campaign Pitch Deck</h2>

<p>The contents of a pitch deck can vary based on firm a concept the DM has for the game they’re looking to run, but it often includes several key elements. First, it establishes the premise, tone, and style of the game, providing relevant examples. Second, it delves into how the party will interact with each other and their surrounding world. Third, it outlines how the game will engage with its mechanics. Finally, it sets certain baseline boundaries and expected norms within the group, laying the groundwork for future collaboration or safety tools.</p>

<h3 id="the-campaign-pitch-summary">The Campaign Pitch Summary</h3>

<p><strong>The essence of your pitch lies in just one slide - this is it!</strong> Captivating your audience involves inciting curiosity for more, so focus on broad strokes and highlights. Tease the plot, evoke the action, and convey the tone of the game. If the players you’re pitching to aren’t familiar with each other, share a few insights about your DMing style, the humor at the table, and the particular rules you’re implementing. Save the details for follow-up questions or Session Zero. Your primary goal is to pique the players’ interest and steer their thinking in the right direction from the start.</p>

<p>Here’s what I recommend:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Campaign Title and Tagline:</strong> Consider examples like “Rime of the Frostmaiden: A chilling struggle for survival in the heart of fantasy horror” or “Trouble on the Triboar Trail: Frontier justice meets rugged survival in the untamed Sword Mountains.”</li>
  <li><strong>Setting:</strong> Include a brief mention of the setting, landscape, travel logistics, or how players will interact with the world.</li>
  <li><strong>System:</strong> Outline the system, edition, any specific versions, and sources the game will use. Example: “5e D&amp;D, minor house rules apply. Core books, Xanathar’s, &amp; Tasha’s acceptable. No Unearthed Arcana, please.”</li>
  <li><strong>Inspiration:</strong> Reference a few films, books, or other media that capture the campaign’s intended ambiance. If relevant, consider including a film-like rating for the campaign.</li>
  <li><strong>Campaign Style:</strong> Indicate how Roleplaying, Lore, Action, and Combat will factor into the campaign. You might also want to mention the degree of consequence in the game. Adding a note about humor’s place can be helpful – e.g., “Significant lore and roleplay. Light humor. Minimize metagaming.” or “Intense lore and roleplaying, grim-dark setting, no phones at the table.”</li>
  <li><strong>Schedule &amp; Venue:</strong> Be upfront about your proposed schedule, as this can often be a hurdle for campaigns. Also, specify whether the game will be online, in-person, or a mix. This is akin to “the ask” in pitches - be explicit. E.g., “Online via Roll20, weekly for 3 hours, Saturdays 5pm EST. Please commit to regular attendance”, “In-person at my home, biweekly Sundays at 2pm, flexible attendance.”</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="additional-topics">Additional Topics</h3>

<p>The Campaign Pitch Summary is the essential part of your game pitch. Ideally, if your presentation includes more than one slide, the first one should captivate your players enough to prompt them to view the subsequent slides. The following are some additional slides that could provide players with more context. Out of these, I’d highly recommend “Game Boundaries &amp; Tools.” While many TTRPG players refer to these as Safety &amp; Consent, I believe the term “Boundaries” is more apt.</p>

<p><strong>Suggested Additional Slides or Topics:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Tools &amp; Resources:</strong> If your game is online or employs extensive tooling, this is the place to list those out. DnDBeyond, VTT, Text Chat, Voice Chat, and any other tools players will be using during the game. Differentiate between optional and mandatory tools. You might also consider mentioning your boundaries regarding other tools.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Table Styles:</strong> If you have specific expectations about game flow or table norms, outline them here. Whether you use an hourglass during play, ask players not to offer advice during others’ turns, or expect players to select their spells before their turn - these details belong on this slide.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Optional and House Rules:</strong> House Rules are quite common in D&amp;D, and even the core rules offer different variations a DM might adopt. Highlight these here, especially if a rule significantly impacts certain classes or players.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Baseline Boundaries:</strong> As touched on earlier, this would be my first choice for an additional slide after the summary. Boundaries are crucial in TTRPGs and can significantly affect the game’s enjoyment. While DMs should undoubtedly discuss player boundaries in session zero, it’s also essential to establish baseline expectations or non-negotiables ahead of that discussion. This sets a clear foundation and prevents any false sense of flexibility during session zero. For instance, I’m not fond of overly sexualized or evil play; it doesn’t mesh with my style. Your preferences and the nature of your game may differ. If you plan to run a particularly grim setting like Dark Sun, players should be aware of that before session zero. This slide is the place for such disclosures.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix p-3 mb-5">
    
        <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1kjaK9Q9p90P54E2ITZPf0DHGyaZZMHXYAg52Ar19zp4/edit?usp=sharing" target="_blank">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/ROTFM_PitchDeck.gif" alt="Animated GIF of the pitch deck I used in my Rime of the Frostmaiden Campaign." width="480" />
    
        </a>
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Example Pitch for my RotF Campaign</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h2 id="other-resources">Other Resources</h2>

<p>Creating a TTRPG Pitch Deck can be as elaborate or as straightforward as the DM prefers. Personally, I enjoy developing a deck adorned with images to add a bit of flair to the pitch. However, a text summary could be just as effective. Choose the format that suits you, your game, and the target players best.</p>

<p>Here are a few useful resources:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/assets/downloads/TTRPG_Pitch_Deck_Template.pptx"><strong>Pitch Deck Template</strong></a> I’ve designed this simple pitch deck template, complete with prompts for a one-page summary. It’s provided in PowerPoint format, but you can upload it to Google Drive or open it with LibreOffice.
    <ul>
      <li>For a real-world example, take a look at this <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1kjaK9Q9p90P54E2ITZPf0DHGyaZZMHXYAg52Ar19zp4/edit?usp=sharing" target="_blank">Rime of the Frostmaiden Pitch Deck</a> I used for my campaign.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://slyflourish.com/one_page_campaign_guide.html" target="_blank"><strong>Writing a One-Page Campaign Guide</strong></a> by Mike ‘Sly Flourish’ Shea offers another perspective. While I prefer using the pitch to pique interest and then this tool to provide more context prior to session zero, you could begin with this if you’ve already garnered sufficient interest.</li>
  <li><a href="https://youtu.be/MtH1SP1grxo" target="_blank"><strong>Pitching Your Campaign</strong></a> by Matt Colville is a fantastic video from his Running the Game series.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Getting player investment from the start can be a powerful tool for launching your campaign on the right foot. It not only helps identify players who are a good fit for your style of game,  but also directs their creative energies from the get-go. While session zero tends to get the limelight, we shouldn’t overlook engaging the right players even before we reach that point. Pitching your game in a fun and engaging way can help you navigate past common challenges by aligning with the right players from the beginning.</p>

<p>Now get out there and run some great games!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><category term="TTRPG" /><category term="DnD" /><category term="Player Recruitment" /><category term="Safety Tools" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Pitch your D&D campaign like a start-up. Use a pitch deck to attract the right players, align expectations and kickstart a successful game.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/CharactersCelebratingAtTable_480x480.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/CharactersCelebratingAtTable_480x480.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Decoding D&amp;amp;D - What the heck are Hit Points Anyway?</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/02/what-are-hit-points-in-dnd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decoding D&amp;amp;D - What the heck are Hit Points Anyway?" /><published>2023-06-02T08:51:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-02T08:51:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/02/what-are-hit-points-in-dnd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/06/02/what-are-hit-points-in-dnd/"><![CDATA[<p>The conversation around what Hit Points (HP) are and what they represent in Dungeons &amp; Dragons (D&amp;D) is a cyclical one. It’s a concept that periodically bubbles up in the tabletop role-playing game (TTRPG) community, like an ancient dragon in its cyclical slumber, and we seem to be in the midst of another awakening.</p>

<p>It’s no surprise that understanding HP often seems like trying to learn Draconic without a spell of Comprehend Languages. Table Top Roleplaying Games are narrative adventures, so we naturally want to weave a compelling story around every game element. And therein lies the enigma of Hit Points - no matter how you narrate them, you’re likely to walk into a wall of confusion and pile of contradictions.</p>

<div class="d-inline-flex flex-column float-end">
<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix shadow p-3 mb-5 bg-body-tertiary rounded">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/hitpoints/ODnD_p18_480.png" alt="Text on HP from the original DnD book." width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Original and B/X D&amp;D</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix shadow p-3 mb-5 bg-body-tertiary rounded">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/hitpoints/1stEditionDnD480.png" alt="Text on HP from AD&amp;D." width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">The AD&amp;D PHB</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix shadow p-3 mb-5 bg-body-tertiary rounded">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/hitpoints/2ndEditionDnD480.png" alt="Text on HP from 2nd Edition AD&amp;D." width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">The 2nd Edition AD&amp;D PHB</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix shadow p-3 mb-5 bg-body-tertiary rounded">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/hitpoints/5thEditionDnD480.png" alt="Text on HP from 5E D&amp;D." width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">The 5e PHB</figcaption>
    
</figure>
</div>

<h2 id="a-historical-perspective">A Historical Perspective</h2>

<p>Many D&amp;D elements, including HP, sprung from the hobby’s wargaming roots. In those days, units usually had a defensive score and an offensive score. The outcomes were binary: units either lived or died. But when these concepts morphed into the individual tactical combat that defined Original D&amp;D (OD&amp;D), there was a need for a way to track the progress towards defeat, thus giving birth to Armor Class (AC) and Hit Points (HP).</p>

<p>In OD&amp;D, AC denoted how challenging you were to hit, and HP showed how close you were to defeat. The game simply states, “Your hit points determine how hard your character is to kill.” And that’s it. That’s the HP origin story. They’re an arbitrary, abstract measurement of how difficult you are to kill and how far along the game is in achieving that.</p>

<h2 id="the-evolution-of-hp">The Evolution of HP</h2>

<p>Later D&amp;D editions got increasingly philosophical about HP. Advanced D&amp;D acknowledged physical punishment, but clarified that “a significant portion of hit points, especially at higher levels, stands for skill, luck, and/or magical factors.” It even said it would be “ridiculous” to assume characters could endure such physical punishment, further emphasizing that HP are not intended to be taken literally.</p>

<p>2nd Edition D&amp;D kept the abstract theme, defining damage as an abstract concept that allows characters to be heroic. It didn’t dwell on the semantics of HP. 3rd Edition, on the other hand, leaned into the mechanics and didn’t provide a narrative explanation for HP and damage at all. 4th Edition tried to have the best of both worlds, setting a base number of hit points representing “real” damage, while anything over was the old dance of skill, luck, and magic.</p>

<p>By the time 5th edition D&amp;D came around, we’re back in the abstract realm, with the game stating, “Hit Points represent a combination of physical and mental durability, the will to live, and luck.”</p>

<h2 id="hit-points-setting-the-stage-not-defining-the-genre">Hit Points: Setting the Stage, Not defining the Genre</h2>

<p>Hit Point mechanics are integral, but the presence of HP doesn’t force your game into a specific genre. That job is for the Dungeon Master, who tailors how this mechanic comes into play. For instance, early D&amp;D editions painted a grim, risky scene with low HP and tight damage thresholds, providing a sword-and-sorcery feel. In contrast, 5th Edition, with its generous HP pools and high-damage exploits, resonates with high-fantasy heroics.</p>

<p>Remember, it’s not the existence of HP that set these styles; it’s their application. As the DM, you have the freedom to adjust this tool to shape your campaign’s tone, from injecting grimdark elements into a 5th Edition game by reducing HP, to amping up the heroics in a 1st Edition game by increasing HP totals. At the end of the day, HP is a vital but flexible aspect of the D&amp;D universe.</p>

<h2 id="hit-points-tools-not-shackles">Hit Points: Tools, Not Shackles</h2>

<p>It’s crucial to remember that Hit Points are a mechanic, not a set of shackles for the DM. They have their boundaries and are not designed to simulate everything could befall a character. Every edition of D&amp;D underscores this, suggesting that the DM delineates these limits.</p>

<p>For instance, if a character decides to take a dip in a lava pool or plunge from a mile-high cliff, many DMs might opt not to roll damage, deeming these situations unsurvivable. In such cases, the official material often advises DMs to declare character death outright, instead of getting tangled in the mire of damage dice. <em>However, if these drastic scenarios occur frequently in your game, it might be worth reassessing your game design.</em></p>

<p>On the flip side, some DMs might channel a superhero vibe, letting characters brush off falls from great heights. That’s equally valid. As with any ruling in a tabletop RPG, maintaining an internally consistent world is the important part.</p>

<p>The bottom line? Understanding the tone of your game and setting appropriate limits is key when navigating the world of Hit Points. Keep this in mind as you weave your epic tales of adventure.</p>

<h2 id="living-with-the-hp-conundrum">Living with the HP Conundrum</h2>

<p>Trying to define Hit Points is like grappling with a Mind Flayer — it’s a sure path to madness. Make it too abstract, and you create a narrative disconnect. Make it too literal, and you grapple with the absurdities of surviving a lava bath or healing from the brink of death overnight.</p>

<p>In my humble opinion, D&amp;D intends for players to embrace the vagueness of Hit Points. They’re not ‘meat points’ or a measure of your plot armor, but more an abstraction of your character’s struggle to survive. Like most time travel plotlines, it’s nonsensical. So, just wave your hand, enjoy the game, and let the Hit Points fall where they may. Their purpose is to serve the adventure, the narrative, and ultimately, the fun. Because, in the end, who needs a physics lesson in the thermal dynamics of lava when you can have a daring escape from a volcano instead?</p>

<p>Now get out there and run some great games!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="Analysis" /><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This post unravels the history of D&D's Hit Points (HP), from wargaming roots to 5th Ed's abstract system. And it looks into what the heck hit points are supposed to be anyway.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/mandy-jurgens-female-plate_475x672.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/mandy-jurgens-female-plate_475x672.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">You Have the Power - Places of Power in D&amp;amp;D</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/31/places-of-power/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You Have the Power - Places of Power in D&amp;amp;D" /><published>2023-05-31T08:54:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-05-31T08:54:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/31/places-of-power</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/05/31/places-of-power/"><![CDATA[<p>The untamed forces of magic in Dungeons and Dragons have long held the power to both awe and terrify, a duality echoed in the narrative threads of fantasy literature. This house rule invites players to embrace this paradox, offering a high-stakes opportunity to amplify their spells beyond conventional limits. But, this isn’t a risk to be taken lightly; mastery comes with potential for both magnificent success and cataclysmic failure. This high-risk, high-reward dynamic is not universal, but rather tethered to Places of Power - locations within the game world steeped in raw, wild magical energy. Here, spellcasters can attempt to weave this abundant power into their own spells, pushing the boundaries of what they could usually achieve. However, the road to arcane supremacy is fraught with peril, and the volatile energies of these places can lead to unexpected and dangerous consequences.</p>

<p>As a Dungeon Master, this house rule offers a unique narrative tool to manage the use of these amplified abilities and build compelling encounters. Villains, drawn to the immense power offered by these locations, might set up their lairs in Places of Power, adding an extra layer of challenge and strategy to confrontations. Moreover, these magical nexuses can become focal points in your campaign, driving the narrative as players might actively seek these places out, eager to tap into their vast potential. This is not just a rule - it is a lore, a plot device, and a tantalizing challenge all rolled into one, offering new avenues for character development and world-building. Embark on this arcane journey, and let your game be infused with the volatile and awe-inspiring power of raw magic.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/PlaceOfPower._480x720.jpg" alt="A ruin teaming with magical energy." height="720" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<h2 id="places-of-power">Places of Power</h2>

<p>Places of Power are distinctive locations saturated with arcane or divine energies. A competent spellcaster can tap into these energies, enhancing their own spells and abilities. To utilize a Place of Power, a spellcaster must first identify a location that aligns with their specific magical or divine influence. Following discovery, the caster must engage in a period of study and attunement to effectively harness the location’s power. Place types may or may not make a difference in terms of access and attunement, as determined by the DM.</p>

<p>Here are the common types of Places of Power:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Leyline Nodes:</strong> Leyline Nodes serve as focal points where natural currents of arcane energy converge, forming reservoirs of magical energy. Wizards can utilize these nodes, but only if their school of magic aligns with the particular energy of the node.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Holy Sites:</strong> These locations bear a distinct significance to a specific god, religion, or holy ideal. Clerics can tap into these sites, provided their divine domain aligns with the site’s sacred affiliation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Primal Refuges:</strong> These are areas that brim with the untouched, primal energies of nature, drawing power directly from the Feywild. Druids can utilize these refuges, but their Circle must align with the refuge’s primal energy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Pure Essence:</strong> These locations have been previously inhabited by potent supernatural entities, and their residual essence remains infused within these places. Sorcerers can tap into these locations, but their bloodline must correspond to the essence of the entity that once inhabited the location.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="finding-and-attuning-to-a-place-of-power">Finding and Attuning to a Place of Power</h2>
<p>Places of power may be detected with the Detect Magic spell. Alternatively a combination of a study of the history of the place or careful examination may allow a History or Investigation check to realize a location is a place of power.</p>

<p>Once discovered, a spellcaster can take a short rest and attempt to attune to a Place of Power by making a check using their primary spellcasting ability. The DC for this check is set by the DM and typically ranges from 10 for common or well-known Places of Power, to 20 or more for extremely rare or unique locations. Importantly, attuning to a location does not count against the character’s maximum item attunement limit. However, this attunement isn’t permanent and may fade over time, necessitating reattunement after a significant period.</p>

<p>Remember, Places of Power should be treated as significant elements within your world, and their discovery and utilization should carry corresponding narrative weight.</p>

<h2 id="rarity--effects">Rarity &amp; Effects</h2>
<p>Places of Power in D&amp;D can enhance, modify or even provide entirely new abilities, offering a boost to spellcasters and creatures alike. DMs are encouraged to get creative with the effects of these power locations, making their campaigns even more engaging. Many wizards position their towers, creatures make lairs, and churches build their foundations upon these mystical spots, all seeking to harness their power.</p>

<p>Places of Power have a rarity system, akin to that of magic items, ranging from Common to Legendary. Here’s a brief overview of each category:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Common:</strong> These Places of Power are frequently encountered, and their effects, while beneficial, are relatively minor. Examples might include an area providing something akin to the Guidance spell or Song of Rest ability once per day. Roadside inns, small shrines, and minor monster lairs often occupy these sites.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Uncommon:</strong> Less common than their counterparts, these Places of Power provide slightly more potent effects or a broader range of minor effects. Typical examples might include Spell Weaving (see below), halving the time of spell scribing or alchemical production, providing an extra hit die of healing during a short rest once a day, or a small bonus to attack. Large shrines or small chapels, houses of healing, fortifications, libraries, and lairs often occupy these sites.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Rare:</strong> Rare Places of Power are challenging to find, but their beneficial effects are considerably more potent and impactful. Typical effects might include providing an increase to hit points, resistance to a type of damage, sustaining low-level spell effects, doubling healing, and more. Churches, organizational headquarters, strong castles, and powerful monster lairs often occupy these sites.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Very Rare:</strong> These Places of Power are seldom encountered. Their effects are significantly powerful, offering substantial benefits to those able to tap into them. These sites may provide regeneration, multiple resistances, spell resistance, control of regional weather, and more. Grand temples, state capitals, powerful citadels, and ancient dragon lairs often occupy these sites.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Legendary:</strong> The most elusive of all, Legendary Places of Power offer truly awe-inspiring and mind-bending abilities. They’re often tied to significant historical or world events and form the stuff of myths and legends. These sites provide total damage resistance or some damage immunities, combinations of spell-like abilities, the ability to alter terrain or control animals or beings in the region. Locations are almost always unique and heavily contested, leaving a legacy of woe.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>The possibilities are truly limitless, and Dungeon Masters are encouraged to get creative. Perhaps these locations house portals, serve as communion points for Warlocks and their patrons, or even provide coveted power sources for diligent Wizards. They could also imbue lair-dwelling monsters with abilities they might not typically possess. Use these Places of Power to enhance your game, provide players with intriguing new goals and mysteries, and above all, enjoy the journey. Gear up to elevate your gaming experience!</p>

<h3 id="spell-weaving-uncommon">Spell Weaving (Uncommon)</h3>

<p>When a spellcaster is within an attuned Place of Power, they may tap into its energy to enhance their spellcasting. As part of casting a spell, the caster can choose add one or more Metamagic-like effects. To do so, the caster must make a spellcasting ability check. The DC for this check is 10 + the level of the spell being cast + 2 for each Metamagic effect selected.</p>

<p>The available effects at a Place of Power typically include Distant Spell, Empower Spell, Extended Spell, and Subtle Spell, as per the descriptions provided in the Sorcerer class, but with references to Charisma replaced by the caster’s primary spellcasting ability.</p>

<p>If the character fails the check, the spell fails and the caster loses the spell slot. Additionally, if they fail the roll by 5 or more, they suffer one randomly rolled spell failure plus one additional failure effect for every additional 5 points they fail the Check by.</p>

<p>Roll a d6 to determine the type of failure:</p>

<p><strong>Spell Failure</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Mana Burn:</strong> The caster loses a spell slot of the spell’s level. If they have no more spell slots of that level, the player may choose to lose a spell slot of the next highest level, or two slots from the level below - it’s the player’s choice. If none are available, roll again.</li>
  <li><strong>Exhaustion:</strong> The caster gains a level of exhaustion as they’ve overtaxed their body.</li>
  <li><strong>Soul Shock:</strong> The caster has disadvantage on all checks with their primary casting ability until they complete a long rest. Rolling this effect again extends the duration by one additional long rest.</li>
  <li><strong>Sensory Overload:</strong> The caster is blinded, deafened, or loses the ability to speak (player’s choice) until the end of their next long rest. Rolling this effect again allows the player to select another effect or extends the duration of an existing effect by one additional long rest.</li>
  <li><strong>System Shock:</strong> The caster must succeed on a Constitution saving throw (DC 10 + spell level) or become stunned until the end of their next turn. Rolling this effect again means the condition lasts until the wizard makes a successful save, repeating this save at the end of each turn. If this effect is rolled a 3rd time, roll again instead.</li>
  <li><strong>Mana Feedback:</strong> The caster takes 1d8 force damage per level of the spell they attempted to cast.</li>
</ol>

<p>As always, adjust this system as necessary to fit your campaign and your players’ preferences.</p>

<h4 id="sorcerer-metamagic-in-a-place-of-power">Sorcerer Metamagic in a Place of Power</h4>

<p>When a sorcerer attuned to a Place of Power uses a Metamagic ability, they reduce the Sorcery Point cost by 1. If this adjustment would bring the cost below 1, there’s still a 50% chance they expend 1 Sorcery Point. Sorcerers can choose to use the standard Place of Power rules instead, particularly if they’re out of Sorcery Points or willing to embrace the risk.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="sample-places-of-power">Sample Places of Power</h2>
<p>The following examples offer a peek into what Places of Power might look like in your game. Remember, these descriptions aren’t exhaustive, and we urge all Dungeon Masters to inject their own creativity into these magical locales. Our goal is for these sites to spark your imagination, providing your players with thrilling incentives to delve deeper into the world. Also, don’t forget about the potential threats posed by creatures that might call these power-infused locales their home. Let’s dive in!</p>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="comforting-hearth">Comforting Hearth</h3>
  <h4 id="common-universal">Common, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>This welcoming place resonates with soothing energies, offering deep rest and restoration to those weary from their journeys.</em></p>

  <p>A character attuned to this site can recover an extra level of exhaustion after completing a Long Rest here, feeling their weariness melt away faster than usual. This effect can be used once per Long Rest. Additionally, any attuned character may roll with advantage to recover from a disease or poison while resting here.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="shrine-of-guided-grace">Shrine of Guided Grace</h3>
  <h4 id="common-holy-site">Common, Holy Site</h4>
  <p><em>This humble shrine is steeped in divine favor, bestowing a touch of guidance on those who pray here.</em></p>

  <p>An attuned character who spends time in prayer or contemplation at this holy site can receive a divine boon: a 1d4 bonus to a single skill roll for a specific task. This blessing must be invoked before the character’s next Long Rest or it dissipates, the divine favor waiting to be called upon another day.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="alchemists-reservoir">Alchemist’s Reservoir</h3>
  <h4 id="uncommon-universal">Uncommon, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>This enchanting site adorned with ancient, ornate distilleries, filled with swirling, shimmering vials of vibrant liquids, all bathed in the soft, multi-hued glow of arcane energy that pulses from the earth and air around it.</em></p>

  <p>Imbued with ancient alchemical energy, alchemists and herbalists attuned to this location can brew potions in half the time.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="the-echoing-library">The Echoing Library</h3>
  <h4 id="uncommon-leyline-node">Uncommon, Leyline Node</h4>
  <p><em>Echoes of arcane knowledge radiate from every shelf in this vast library, accelerating the study pace of those who delve into its treasures.</em></p>

  <p>Attuned spellcasters can prepare an additional spell of a level they can cast for each day they spend here, up to their proficiency bonus. This bonus lasts until the next long rest.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="the-vibrant-henge">The Vibrant Henge</h3>
  <h4 id="uncommon-universal-1">Uncommon, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>Constructed from ancient monoliths, these stones hum with ley line energy, amplifying the powers of those attuned to them.</em></p>

  <p>Arcane practitioners can draw on the raw power of this location to amplify their spells. Some Henges are aligned with a specific school of magic. When casting a spell within this school, practitioners can benefit from an advantageous Spell Weaving roll.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="haven-of-healing">Haven of Healing</h3>
  <h4 id="uncommon-holy-site-primal-refuge">Uncommon, Holy Site, Primal Refuge</h4>
  <p><em>Restorative energies suffuse this location, accelerating recovery and invigorating those who rest within.</em></p>

  <p>Those attuned to this sanctuary recover one level of exhaustion following a short rest. Furthermore, any spell or potion that restores Hit Points, when used within the haven, yields its maximum possible value. These benefits can each be claimed once per long rest.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="sanctuary-of-solitude">Sanctuary of Solitude</h3>
  <h4 id="uncommon-universal-2">Uncommon, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>Ancient wisdom lingers in this tranquil locale, inspiring profound insights for those who meditate here.</em></p>

  <p>Individuals attuned to this place can inscribe scrolls or copy spells into their spell book in half the usual time.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="celestial-observatory">Celestial Observatory</h3>
  <h4 id="rare-universal">Rare, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>This ancient observatory, filled with cryptic glyphs and celestial maps, resonates with whispers from the stars, enhancing the divination skills of those attuned to its energies.</em></p>

  <p>Attuned individuals within the Celestial Observatory gain a deep connection with the cosmos. They can channel this bond to cast the spell Message once per day. Attuned spellcasters in this location also gain the ability to use Spell Weaving, with divination spells providing an advantage to their Spell Weaving checks, enhancing their pursuit of knowledge and insights.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="feywild-glade">Feywild Glade</h3>
  <h4 id="rare-universal-1">Rare, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>Mystical energies from the Feywild permeate this location, empowering those who are attuned to it.</em></p>

  <p>Attuned characters may utilize the Spell Weaving ability here. When casting enchantment spells, they can apply Spell Weaving with an advantage.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="mana-oasis">Mana Oasis</h3>
  <h4 id="rare-universal-2">Rare, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>Overflowing with raw magical energy, this place replenishes the reserves of any attuned spellcaster resting here.</em></p>

  <p>Spellcasters attuned to this location can recover a number of spell slots after a short rest. They regain one spell slot of a level up to their proficiency bonus at the end of a short rest or an hour into a long rest. This benefit is limited to once per long rest.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="moonshadow-glenn">Moonshadow Glenn</h3>
  <h4 id="rare-primal-refuge">Rare, Primal Refuge</h4>
  <p><em>As a nexus of raw, wild power, this place resonates with the primal aspects of nature.</em></p>

  <p>Attuned characters can use their Wild Shape ability to transform into a beast with a Challenge Rating 1 higher than they normally could, once per long rest.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="stoneheart-bastion">Stoneheart Bastion</h3>
  <h4 id="rare-universal-3">Rare, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>Deep beneath the mountain’s roots, this subterranean bastion imbues those within with resilience, mirroring the earth’s unyielding strength.</em></p>

  <p>Any character or beast attuned to this place of power, or who has laired here for more than a full moon cycle, gains the fortitude of the earth itself. This manifests as resistance to non-magical bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage. The boon fades if they leave the site for more than a day or if their attunement is broken.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="primordial-nexus">Primordial Nexus</h3>
  <h4 id="very-rare-primal-refuge">Very Rare, Primal Refuge</h4>
  <p><em>A verdant haven echoing with the vibrant life force of nature, this place empowers attuned druids to embody a vast range of creatures inhabiting these lands.</em></p>

  <p>The Primordial Nexus allows attuned characters who can Wildshape to form deeper connections with creatures in the region. By performing a ritual with a trophy from a Monstrosity or Fey, the character can add that creature to their Wildshape options, as long as it falls within the normal Hit Dice and movement restrictions of their Wildshape ability.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="sanctuary-of-spirits">Sanctuary of Spirits</h3>
  <h4 id="very-rare-universal">Very Rare, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>The spirits of the departed are bound to this sacred refuge, allowing them to linger beyond their natural existence.</em></p>

  <p>When an attuned spellcaster casts Animate Dead on beings that met their end within this sanctuary, it doesn’t count towards their control limit. Instead, they can control a number of undead equal to their primary casting ability score. These undead are bound to the sanctuary and cannot leave its confines; the caster loses control if they lose their attunement.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="d-flex flex-column rule simple-rule">
  <h3 id="echoing-cavern-of-the-berzerker">Echoing Cavern of The Berzerker</h3>
  <h4 id="very-rare-universal-1">Very Rare, Universal</h4>
  <p><em>Legend speaks of a place where reality and illusion refuse to merge; this echoing cavern bolsters mental fortitude and instils clarity amidst deceptive influences.</em></p>

  <p>Characters or beasts that are attuned to this place, or have made it their lair for more than a lunar cycle, become extremely difficult to mislead. They gain advantage on saving throws against illusion spells and mind control effects. Furthermore, those capable of raging can maintain their rage for an additional round without taking damage or attacking an opponent, their resolve empowered by the steadfast spirit of the cavern.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Dive into D&D's magic with our guide on Places of Power. Explore how to find, attune, and harness these unique locations to enhance your game.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/PlaceOfPower._480x720.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/PlaceOfPower._480x720.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>