<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-24T15:40:28+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Optional Rule</title><subtitle>Optional Rule is a blog for DMs and Players alike of DnD 5e and any tabletop  roleplaying game. It offers rules, insight, analysis, and resources that help people run games and enhance their play.</subtitle><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><entry><title type="html">The DnD 2024 Launch and the Future of Hasbro</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/24/hasbro-q3-2024/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The DnD 2024 Launch and the Future of Hasbro" /><published>2024-10-24T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-24T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/24/hasbro-q3-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/24/hasbro-q3-2024/"><![CDATA[<p>The financial health of Hasbro frequently sparks intense discussion among Dungeons &amp; Dragons fans. While speculation often trends toward the alarmist, the underlying concern is understandable. Fans have invested heavily in this hobby - not just financially, but with their time, creativity, and emotional energy. They want to understand the stability of the company behind their beloved game, whether the focus is on product quality over brand exploitation, and how corporate decisions might impact the future of their hobby. <a href="https://investor.hasbro.com/news-releases/news-release-details/hasbro-reports-third-quarter-2024-financial-results" target="_blank">Hasbro’s Q3 earnings report</a> offers us a chance to move beyond speculation and examine actual data.</p>

<p>This analysis covers Hasbro’s financial position from July through September 2024, as reported to their investors. The timing is particularly significant as it encompasses the launch of the D&amp;D 2024 Player’s Handbook and should include pre-order data.</p>

<p>For transparency: while this analysis was generated using AI, it’s worth noting that I work professionally in AI-driven analytics. This isn’t simply a matter of prompting and pasting - it’s a careful examination of the data through an informed lens.</p>

<p>Looking at the broader picture, Hasbro appears stable but faces challenges. While carrying considerable debt, their aggressive inventory reduction has resulted in impressive margins (the percentage of revenue they retain as profit). Despite these high margins, debt reduction will likely remain a long-term process. However, their healthy cash reserves and continued dividend payments suggest stability and maintain investor confidence.</p>

<p><strong>Key observations:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Baldur’s Gate 3’s impact on last year’s numbers is stark. With that revenue stream now diminished, there’s clear pressure to find new ways to monetize the D&amp;D franchise.</li>
  <li>The D&amp;D 2024 launch appears to have underperformed. If the Player’s Handbook hasn’t significantly moved the needle, it’s unlikely the DMG and MM will fare better. This suggests the 5e brand may be in decline.</li>
  <li>Their strategic focus on digital gaming is evident, though the success of their VTT initiative remains uncertain. If they’re considering AI as a major strategy (though this isn’t clear from the report), that’s potentially problematic. In a world where AI can effectively run games, the value of traditional gaming brands and systems could be significantly diminished.</li>
</ul>

<p>Now, let’s examine the detailed analysis of the Q3 report.  Note, <em>I’ve added some commentary in italics to the report below.</em></p>

<h2 id="hasbro-q3-2024-report-summary">Hasbro Q3 2024 Report Summary</h2>

<p><strong>Major Findings:</strong></p>
<ol>
  <li>Overall revenue declined 15% year-over-year (9% excluding eOne divestiture) - <em>This is fairly dramatic to me, the eOne divestiture is a big deal but that they’re 9% down even after excluding it is significant.</em></li>
  <li>Operating profit was $302 million with a margin of 23.6% - <em>Comparing this to the WotC margins below, it’s clear that MtG is floating the company right now.</em></li>
  <li>Company is maintaining its full-year EBITDA guidance of $975M-$1.025B - <em>This is a big range, but it’s a good sign that they’re not revising their expectations for the year.</em></li>
  <li>Company continues to pay quarterly dividends ($0.70 per share) - <em>This is a good sign, it shows that they’re still committed to rewarding shareholders even as they work to transition the business.</em></li>
  <li>Inventory levels are down 39% versus prior year - <em>This is a good sign, it shows that they’re managing their inventory more effectively and can maintain their margins</em></li>
  <li>Digital gaming business saw success with Monopoly Go! ($30M revenue in Q3) - <em>This should be seen as good but I believe this is the origin of a strategic mistake.  I believe they saw the development of the VTT to be the same as Monoboloy Go and I think they’ve bit off more than they can chew with the VTT.</em></li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Financial Position Overall:</strong>
The company is in a period of strategic transition but maintaining stability. While revenues are down, they’ve improved their operational efficiency and maintain strong margins. Their cash position is healthy ($696.1M) and they’ve added short-term investments ($489.3M). The reduction in inventory levels (39% down) suggests better operational management. The maintenance of dividend payments indicates confidence in their cash flow position. However, they do carry significant debt ($3.96B total between current and long-term), which they’ve listed debt reduction as a priority. The company appears financially stable but in need of revenue growth to improve their position.</p>

<p><strong>Wizards of the Coast Indicators:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Revenue decreased 5% in Q3 2024 vs Q3 2023 - <em>Appears to be from lost BG3 revenue. I was hoping to see a softer decline with the release of the 2024 PHB.</em></li>
  <li>Operating margin of 44.9% (down 3.1 points) - <em>Down yes, but 45% is insanely good.</em></li>
  <li>MAGIC: THE GATHERING revenue increased 3%</li>
  <li>Digital gaming affected by tough comparison to Baldur’s Gate 3 launch in Q3 2023</li>
  <li>Year-to-date performance is strong: - <em>All of this incidates the changes at the end of 2023 had a strong positive impact on the business. Hate them if you like but business is unforgiving and they did what they needed to do IMO.</em>
    <ul>
      <li>Revenue up 7% for first nine months</li>
      <li>Operating profit increased 30%</li>
      <li>Operating margin of 47.0%</li>
      <li>Tabletop revenue increased 3%</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Dungeons &amp; Dragons Product Line:</strong>
The report doesn’t break out specific D&amp;D performance metrics, but there are some relevant indicators:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Listed as one of their “Franchise Brands” alongside MAGIC: THE GATHERING - <em>I take this as an affirmation of support for DnD but I don’t know how to take the term “Franchise Brands” as Core Brand is really the gold standard.</em></li>
  <li>Digital gaming revenue decline was specifically attributed to comparing against Baldur’s Gate 3’s launch in Q3 2023, suggesting this was a significant revenue driver</li>
  <li>D&amp;D is included in “Hasbro Total Gaming” category which saw: - <em>The take away here is they had a significant decline at the end of last year that is turing around.</em>
    <ul>
      <li>6% decline in Q3 2024 vs Q3 2023</li>
      <li>3% growth year-to-date</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Strategy indicators:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Company appears to be focusing on digital transformation</li>
  <li>Pursuing licensing opportunities</li>
  <li>Focus on product innovation</li>
  <li>D&amp;D appears to be integrated into their broader digital gaming strategy</li>
  <li>No specific new D&amp;D initiatives were announced in this report</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="misc" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hasbro's Q3 2024 report offers a detailed look at their financial performance and strategic direction and teases the future of the DnD brand.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/dnd_record_keeping_1200x600.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/dnd_record_keeping_1200x600.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Movement in Theater of the Mind for DnD 5e</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/20/theater-of-the-mind-movement-in-5e/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Movement in Theater of the Mind for DnD 5e" /><published>2024-10-20T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-20T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/20/theater-of-the-mind-movement-in-5e</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/20/theater-of-the-mind-movement-in-5e/"><![CDATA[<p>As a Dungeon Master, I’ve always been drawn to the flexibility and imagination-sparking nature of Theater of the Mind (TotM) gameplay. However, at least in grid based systems like D&amp;D 5e, it can be a challenge to account for various elements of the game designed for tactical combat. Additionally, it can be tempting to simply ignore movement when using TotM and miss out on the exciting and dynamic nature of swashbuckling adventures. Today, I want to share a system I’ve developed that keeps TotM combat dynamic and tactical while avoiding the need to track every 5-foot square.</p>

<p>While this system is primarily designed with D&amp;D 5e in mind, its core principles can be easily adapted to any TTRPG. In fact, I think it would work particularly well in games like ShadowDark, which already emphasizes streamlined gameplay. The fundamental concept - declaring your intention and then rolling for the outcome - is universally applicable across various game systems. This flexibility allows you to bring more dynamic movement to your TotM sessions, regardless of the specific ruleset you’re using.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/pitch_battle_ai_art_480x856.webp" alt="A pitch battle with warriors charging back and forth. AI generated art." height="856" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<h2 id="the-core-principle-intention-over-precision">The Core Principle: Intention Over Precision</h2>

<p>The heart of this system is focusing on what characters are trying to achieve with their movement, rather than precisely where they are at any given moment. Here’s how it works:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Describe that the character is trying to achieve and select the appropriate maneuver.</li>
  <li>If two opponents want the same thing (like engaging in melee), let it happen without a roll.</li>
  <li>If opponents want different things, (like staying in cover or avoiding engagement) resolve it with an opposed skill check.</li>
</ol>

<p>This approach keeps the action flowing and puts the emphasis on the narrative rather than the mechanics.</p>

<h2 id="simplified-movement-ranges">Simplified Movement Ranges</h2>

<p>Instead of tracking exact distances, we use two primary ranges:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Move Range</strong>: The character can reach the target in a single move action.</li>
  <li><strong>Extended Range</strong>: The character is beyond a single move away  If nessisary define how many moves it would take to reach a target.</li>
</ul>

<p>This simplification allows for quick decision-making and keeps the focus on the action.</p>

<h2 id="key-maneuvers">Key Maneuvers</h2>

<p>To add tactical depth to combat, I’ve introduced several maneuvers that players can attempt:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Engage</strong>: Move into melee range with an opponent or multiple opponents (up to their proficiency bonus).</li>
  <li><strong>Close</strong>: Reduce the distance between you and a target so you may attempt an Engage or other maneuver next turn.  (Useful in chase scenes.)</li>
  <li><strong>Avoid</strong>: Stay out of an opponent’s melee reach.</li>
  <li><strong>Flee</strong>: Use a full action to move significantly away from combat. Because they are using a full action, the character gains advantage on any checks to avoid engagement.</li>
  <li><strong>Line Up A Shot</strong>: Attempt to negate the cover bonus of an opponent for a clear ranged attack.</li>
  <li><strong>Use Cover</strong>: Utilize an obstacle for protection.</li>
  <li><strong>Intercept</strong>: Use a reaction to move and potentially make an attack of opportunity.</li>
</ol>

<p>These maneuvers give players clear options for positioning without needing a grid.</p>

<h2 id="resolving-maneuvers">Resolving Maneuvers</h2>

<p>When a player attempts a maneuver, here’s how we resolve it:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The player describes their intended movement.</li>
  <li>If an opponent wants the same thing, let it happen.  If they want different things, the player rolls the chosen skill check and the opponent rolls their skill check.</li>
  <li>Resolve the maneuver, ties to to the ‘defender’, the winning roll is the one that gets to do what they want.</li>
</ol>

<p>The most common skills used are Athletics, Acrobatics, and Deception, but I encourage players to think creatively about how other skills might apply.</p>

<p>Some examples:</p>

<p>The player characters are Ahmed the Fighter, Lora the Rogue, and Kaelin the Cleric.  They are engaged in combat with a group of 3 goblin archers and 2 goblin warriors.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ahmed wants to Engage with one of the Goblin Archers.  All the archers want to Avoid engagement.  Ahmed rolls Athletics vs the all the archer’s Acrobatics.  If Ahmed beats any of the Gobin Archers roll, he can engage them. Any Goblin Archer that wins successfully avoids engagement.</li>
  <li>Lora wants to Use Cover against the ranged attacks while shooting at a Goblin Fighter.  It just happens.  On the turn for a Goblin Archer, they try to Line up a Shot on Lora and roll Deception vs her Acrobatics.  If the Archer beats her roll, they get to shoot without Lora’s cover bonus.</li>
  <li>A Goblin Warrior tries to engage Ahmed but Kaelin uses her reaction to Intercept them.  Kaelin rolls Athletics vs the Goblin Warrior’s Athletics.  If Kaelin beats the Goblin Warrior’s roll, she can make an opporunity attack. (Kalin indends to shove the Goblin Warrior and attempt to knock them prone.)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="special-considerations">Special Considerations</h2>

<p>To add even more depth and account for various D&amp;D rules, I’ve incorporated a few special considerations:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Flanking</strong>: If you’re using flanking rules, any character attacking a target already engaged by another character gains advantage on their attack roll.</li>
  <li><strong>Within 5 feet</strong>: Some character or monster ability uses the ‘within 5 feet’ qualfier. In this case any character that is engaged with someone is within 5 feet of them.  Moving to within 5 feet of an ally is automatic in most cases.</li>
  <li><strong>Multiple Opponents</strong>: A character can attempt to use multi-attack on different opponents within range.</li>
  <li><strong>Dodge Action</strong>: Grants advantage on all maneuver rolls and reactions to avoid engagement.</li>
  <li><strong>Sentinel Feat</strong>: Allows the Intercept maneuver as a free action, once per round.</li>
  <li><strong>Reach Weapons</strong>: Grant advantage on maneuvers to engage or intercept.</li>
  <li><strong>Limited/Enhanced Movement</strong>: Some characters have limited movement or enhanced movement.  In most cases this should grant disadvantage/advantage on applicable maneuvers. This could include but not be limited to bonus action movement, being limited to half movmenet due to gettiing up from prone,haste, or other effects that grant extra movement.</li>
  <li><strong>Opportunity Attack</strong>: If a character is engaged or with an opponent and attempts to move away, the opponent can make an opportunity attack as normal.</li>
  <li><strong>Force Movement</strong>: This is not typically handled in these rules and proceed as normal.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="keeping-it-fun-and-flexible">Keeping It Fun and Flexible</h2>

<p>Remember, the goal of this system is to enhance the fun and tactical elements of combat without getting bogged down in rules. These rules can likely be twisted and work best when everyone enages them in good faith.  If a situation is unclear or some particular use of a maneuver does not make sense, the DM should make a ruling and keep things moving.  As a DM, I always prioritize the following:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Narrative Flow</strong>: Use the system to enhance the story, not hinder it.</li>
  <li><strong>Player Agency</strong>: Give players meaningful choices about their positioning and actions.</li>
  <li><strong>Quick Resolution</strong>: Keep the action moving by making quick judgments rather than consulting tables.</li>
  <li><strong>Fairness</strong>: Be consistent in your rulings, but be willing to adapt if something isn’t working.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping Up</h2>

<p>This system has brought new life to my TotM combat sessions, allowing for dynamic and engaging fights without the need for miniatures or a battle map. It’s flexible enough to work with various game systems and can be easily tweaked to fit your group’s style.</p>

<p>Remember, the key is to keep things moving and fun. Don’t be afraid to make quick decisions and adjust on the fly. Your players will appreciate the added depth to combat, and you’ll enjoy the freedom of not having to track every little movement.</p>

<p>Give this system a try in your next TotM session and let me know how it goes. Happy gaming, everyone!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="rpg" /><category term="resources" /><category term="DnD" /><category term="Theater of the Mind" /><category term="Combat" /><category term="House Rules" /><category term="Movement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover a dynamic system for handling movement in Theater of the Mind gameplay, designed primarily for D&D 5e but adaptable to any TTRPG. This approach emphasizes narrative flow and player agency while maintaining tactical depth.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/pitch_battle_ai_art_800x418.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/pitch_battle_ai_art_800x418.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/13/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-10-13T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-13T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/13/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/13/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>This week in the world of tabletop roleplaying games (TTRPGs) news you may have missed! We have stories about new resources that assist Game Masters (GMs) to significant announcements that bridge digital and tabletop realms, and other stories about how the TTRPG ecosystem continues to grow. Here’s a closer look at some of the most captivating stories from October 6 to October 13, 2024, that you may not have seen in your feeds.</p>

<h3 id="free-rpg-resources---flextale-infinite-adventures-volume-1-western-realm-of-aquilae">Free RPG Resources - FlexTale Infinite Adventures Volume 1: Western Realm of Aquilae</h3>
<p><em>October 8, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>; #TTRPG</p>

<p>Announced a free resource titled “FlexTale Infinite Adventures Volume 1: Western Realm of Aquilae” that provides an array of Points of Interest (POIs) tailored for easy integration into various fantasy TTRPGs. This comprehensive resource is designed to assist GMs in creating dynamic sessions without extensive preparation, making it an ideal asset for both new and experienced GMs.</p>

<p>Readers keen on enhancing their campaigns can access this invaluable resource at <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/10/free-rpg-resources-flextale-infinite.html" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>.</p>

<h3 id="worlds-beyond-number-makes-big-changes-after-its-next-arc">‘Worlds Beyond Number’ Makes Big Changes After Its Next Arc</h3>
<p><em>October 8, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net" target="_blank">Bell of Lost Souls</a>; #TTRPG</p>

<p>This popular podcast is transitioning to a space-themed campaign after wrapping up its current arc, marking a significant narrative shift. This evolution showcases the adaptability of TTRPG narratives to maintain freshness and engagement, underscoring the fluidity inherent in the genre.</p>

<p>For insights into the podcast’s new direction, check out <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/10/worlds-beyond-number-makes-big-changes-after-its-next-arc.html" target="_blank">Bell of Lost Souls</a>.</p>

<h3 id="dd-character-builder-level-up-release">D&amp;D Character Builder: Level Up Release</h3>
<p><em>October 11, 2024</em>, <a href="https://blog.roll20.net" target="_blank">Roll20 Blog</a>; #DungeonsAndDragons</p>

<p>Roll20 introduced an upgraded D&amp;D Character Builder featuring an automated level-up and a refined user interface, enhancing the character management experience for players. This upgrade aims to streamline gameplay and ease the learning curve for newcomers, reflecting the community’s feedback for more inclusive tools as they engage with D&amp;D 5E.</p>

<p>Learn more about this significant enhancement at <a href="https://blog.roll20.net/posts/dd-character-builder-level-up-release/" target="_blank">Roll20 Blog</a>.</p>

<h3 id="new-premium-edition-for-candela-obscura-from-beadle--grimms-and-critical-roles-darrington-press">New Premium Edition for Candela Obscura from Beadle &amp; Grimm’s and Critical Role’s Darrington Press</h3>
<p><em>October 11, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.rascal.news" target="_blank">Rascal News</a>; #TTRPG</p>

<p>Beadle &amp; Grimm announced “Horrors of the Fairelands,” a limited release for their game, Candela Obscura, enriched with immersive elements and beautifully crafted handouts to enhance the GM experience. This product highlights the growing trend for premium quality accessories in TTRPGs, aiming to elevate gameplay immensely.</p>

<p>Pre-orders are now available; take a look at this exciting offering at <a href="https://www.rascal.news/new-premium-edition-for-candela-obscura-from-beadle-grimms-and-critical-roles-darrington-press-2/" target="_blank">Rascal News</a>.</p>

<h3 id="baldurs-gate-3-characters-become-official-dungeons--dragons-minis">BALDUR’S GATE 3 Characters Become Official DUNGEONS &amp; DRAGONS Minis</h3>
<p><em>October 11, 2024</em>, <a href="https://nerdist.com" target="_blank">Nerdist</a>; #DungeonsAndDragons</p>

<p>WizKids is debuts a new line of official D&amp;D miniatures featuring beloved characters from Baldur’s Gate 3. This exciting initiative caters to fans and enhances the convergence of digital and tabletop experiences, exemplifying how video games profoundly influence the tabletop RPG community.</p>

<p>For detailed views on the release, visit <a href="https://nerdist.com/article/baldurs-gate-3-official-dungeons-dragons-minis/" target="_blank">Nerdist</a>.</p>

<p>In summary, there’s a lot happening in the TTRPG world, showcasing valuable resources and developments that continue to enrich our beloved hobby. Stay tuned for more updates as this dynamic community keeps evolving and growing!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><category term="TTRPG" /><category term="RPG Resources" /><category term="Podcasts" /><category term="DungeonsAndDragons" /><category term="CandelaObscura" /><category term="BaldursGate3" /><category term="EverQuest" /><category term="MMORPG" /><category term="GameMasters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Catch up on the latest TTRPG news from October 6 to October 12, 2024, including new resources, product announcements, and key updates in the world of tabletop gaming.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/06/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-10-06T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-06T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/06/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/06/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>As we dive into the latest happenings in the world of tabletop roleplaying games (TTRPGs), excitement fills the air! From classic titles making a digital debut to significant changes in design leadership, this month has been packed with news that every TTRPG enthusiast should know about. Let’s explore the key stories that are shaping our beloved hobby.</p>

<h4 id="a-shift-in-design-richard-august-leaves-steamforged-games">A Shift in Design: Richard August Leaves Steamforged Games</h4>
<p><em>October 4, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168865/steamforged-games-lead-ttrpg-designer-richard-august-leaves-the-company/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>; #TTRPG #SteamforgedGames</p>

<p>In a surprising move, Richard August, the lead designer at Steamforged Games, has announced his departure from the company. Known for his contributions to popular titles such as the “Dark Souls” RPG and “RuneScape Kingdoms,” August’s exit raises questions about the future direction of the studio and its upcoming projects.</p>

<p>August’s departure may signal a shift in design philosophy and project management at Steamforged, which has experienced a meteoric rise in the TTRPG landscape. His influence has been pivotal in establishing the company’s reputation for high-quality adaptations of video game franchises into tabletop formats. The TTRPG community should follow this development closely, as it could impact the future of beloved games. <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168865/steamforged-games-lead-ttrpg-designer-richard-august-leaves-the-company/" target="_blank">Dive deeper into the implications of this change here</a>.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="magic-awaits-sneak-peek-at-the-upcoming-55e-dungeon-masters-guide">Magic Awaits: Sneak Peek at the Upcoming 5.5E Dungeon Master’s Guide</h4>
<p><em>October 1, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/10/dont-worry-the-new-5-5e-dungeon-masters-guide-is-still-full-of-magic-items-preview-details.html" target="_blank">Bell of Lost Souls</a>; #D&amp;D #DungeonMastersGuide #5.5E</p>

<p>A preview of the forthcoming 5.5E Dungeon Master’s Guide has excited the community, revealing that it will retain a wealth of magical items that fans have come to love. This assurance that classic elements will remain intact is crucial for long-time players who enjoy the depth and variety magic items bring to their campaigns.</p>

<p>The enduring popularity of D&amp;D relies heavily on its ability to evolve while respecting its roots, making this update an essential read for DMs looking to enrich their game experience. <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/10/dont-worry-the-new-5-5e-dungeon-masters-guide-is-still-full-of-magic-items-preview-details.html" target="_blank">Explore what’s in store for the next iteration of the guide here</a>.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="empowering-players-the-bastion-system-in-dd-55e">Empowering Players: The Bastion System in D&amp;D 5.5E</h4>
<p><em>October 2, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/10/dd-5-5e-the-bastion-system-previews-players-make-your-mark-on-the-world.html" target="_blank">Bell of Lost Souls</a>; #D&amp;D #5.5E #BastionSystem</p>

<p>The introduction of the Bastion System in D&amp;D 5.5E aims to give players greater agency in world-building and storytelling. This system encourages collaboration between players and DMs, fostering a dynamic narrative environment where player choices significantly impact the game world.</p>

<p>This development is particularly significant as it aligns with a broader trend in tabletop RPGs toward increased player involvement in narrative creation. By empowering players to shape their stories, D&amp;D continues to innovate while deepening engagement within its community. <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/10/dd-5-5e-the-bastion-system-previews-players-make-your-mark-on-the-world.html" target="_blank">Read more about how this new system could transform gameplay here</a>.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="unleash-the-horror-new-bundle-of-holding-featuring-dread-thingonomicon">Unleash the Horror: New Bundle of Holding Featuring Dread Thingonomicon</h4>
<p><em>October 2, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/10/bundle-of-holding-dread-thingonomicon.html" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>; #TTRPG #BundleOfHolding</p>

<p>The latest Bundle of Holding features the Dread Thingonomicon, a collection of horror-themed TTRPG content that promises to thrill fans of the genre. This bundle not only provides new material but also highlights the growing niche of horror in tabletop gaming, appealing to those who enjoy darker narratives.</p>

<p>Bundles like this are important as they often introduce players to lesser-known titles and provide affordable access to a wealth of content. They also foster community through shared experiences in themed gameplay. If you’re a fan of horror RPGs, don’t miss out on this exciting opportunity to explore new adventures <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/10/bundle-of-holding-dread-thingonomicon.html" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>In conclusion, the TTRPG landscape continues to evolve with exciting developments, from classic games finding new life on digital platforms to significant shifts in company leadership and product offerings. Staying informed about these changes not only enriches our gaming experience but also connects us as a community navigating the dynamic world of tabletop roleplaying.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><category term="DnD" /><category term="Steamforged" /><category term="WOTC" /><category term="DungeonMastersGuide" /><category term="BundleOfHolding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Description of the article]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Greyhawk - The Original D&amp;amp;D Setting Returns</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/02/a-return-to-greyhawk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Greyhawk - The Original D&amp;amp;D Setting Returns" /><published>2024-10-02T08:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-02T08:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/02/a-return-to-greyhawk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/02/a-return-to-greyhawk/"><![CDATA[<p>When you’re leafing through the pages of the upcoming <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xWNT9N3cE2U&amp;t=1s" target="_blank">Dungeon Master’s Guide</a>, set to hit shelves this November as part of D&amp;D 2024. The familiar scent of fresh ink and new possibilities filling the air, you might notice something different. The default setting isn’t the Forgotten Realms in the latest edition. Instead, you’re reading about a world called Greyhawk. For some of you, this name might spark a nostalgic gleam in your eye. For others, it might be a curious first encounter. So what is with the new default setting for DnD 2024? Lets take a journey to the <a href="https://greyhawkonline.com/" target="_blank">World of Greyhawk</a>, D&amp;D’s original campaign setting, and find out what we’re in for.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/greyhawksupplament_480x754.webp" alt="Cover image of the original Greyhawk Supplement." height="754" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">The original Greyhawk Supplement</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h3 id="greyhawk-the-og-of-dd-worlds">Greyhawk: The OG of D&amp;D Worlds</h3>

<p>First things first - what exactly is Greyhawk? Well, imagine if Gary Gygax, one of the founding fathers of D&amp;D, decided to create an entire world. Oh wait, he did! That’s Greyhawk in a nutshell. This high fantasy setting centers on the continent of Oerth (yes, that’s Earth with an ‘O’, because why not?), with most of the action taking place in a region called the Flanaess.</p>

<p>Now, I know what some of you are thinking. “But I’ve been playing in the Forgotten Realms for years! Why the change?” Well, my friends, sometimes to move forward, we need to take a step back. And in this case, we’re stepping back to the very roots of D&amp;D.</p>

<h3 id="a-brief-history-of-greyhawk">A Brief History of Greyhawk</h3>

<p>Before we dive deeper into what makes Greyhawk tick, let’s take a quick jaunt through its history. Trust me, it’ll help you appreciate just how momentous this return really is.</p>

<p>Greyhawk’s journey began in the early 1970s as Gary Gygax’s personal campaign setting. But it didn’t say his for long - it quickly became a collaborative effort, with many of D&amp;D’s original creators leaving their mark on this burgeoning world.</p>

<p>Take, for instance, David Arneson’s Castle Blackmoor. This mega-dungeon, one of the earliest and most iconic in D&amp;D history, found its home in the north of Greyhawk. Its influence? Monumental. From the sprawling levels of Undermountain in the Forgotten Realms to the demon-infested halls of video games like Diablo, Blackmoor’s DNA is everywhere.</p>

<p>Many of D&amp;D’s most iconic NPCs - names like Bigby and Robilar - started as characters in Gary’s original play group. It was a world built not just by designers, but by players, their adventures weaving the very fabric of the setting. This to me always solidified the idea that collaborative world-building was fundamental to the D&amp;D experience. Shared setting development was part of the bones of the game from the start.</p>

<p>It wasn’t until 1980 that fans like myself got our first real taste of this rich world with the release of the <a href="https://archive.org/details/tsr09025worldofgreyhawkfolio" target="_blank">World of Greyhawk folio</a>. For a pre-teen me, it was like discovering that all those disconnected adventures actually existed in a fully-realized world. I gave me that feeling of a deep, living world that captivated me in the fictional settings I loved so much.</p>

<p>The 1983 “Gold Box” set expanded the world even further. Throughout the 80s and early 90s, Greyhawk thrived, with countless adventures, sourcebooks, and articles fleshing out its rich tapestry of cultures and conflicts.</p>

<p>The late 90s and early 2000s saw Greyhawk take a bit of a backseat, but it never truly went away. The “Living Greyhawk” organized play campaign kept the flame alive, allowing players to continue shaping the world’s ongoing narrative. If I recall correctly, this was the origin of what would eventually become the DnD Adventurers League we know today.</p>

<p>And now, after years of teasing references in various 5e products, Greyhawk is poised to reclaim its place at the heart of D&amp;D with the upcoming 2024 edition. It’s a homecoming decades in the making, and for many of us old-timers, it feels like reuniting with an old friend - a friend who’s been shaped by countless hands and imaginations over the years.</p>

<div class="clearfix text-center">
<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 img-fluid">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/greyhawkmap_1024x585.webp" alt="Overland map of Oerth." height="585" width="1024" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Updated map of Oerth from the 2024 DMG.</figcaption>
    
</figure>
</div>

<h3 id="a-tapestry-of-cultures-and-conflict">A Tapestry of Cultures and Conflict</h3>

<p>The core region of Greyhawk was the region of Flanaess. Originally steeped in a strong Eurasian flavor (a product of its time), Greyhawk has since evolved, expanding its cultural horizons beyond its initial borders. Yet, it still carries the DNA of the literary giants that inspired the very foundations of D&amp;D. You can feel the gritty urban landscapes of Fritz Leiber’s Lankhmar, the moral ambiguity of Michael Moorcock’s Eternal Champion saga, the primal energy of Robert E. Howard’s Hyborian Age, and the dying earth vibes of Jack Vance’s work.</p>

<p>At the heart of human civilization are the Oeridians, who once ran the show with their Great Kingdom of Aerdy. Imagine walking the haunted streets of Rauxes, the former capital, now a chilling reminder of how far the mighty can fall. Or picture yourself in the courts of Furyondy, where noble knights plan their next move against the evil forces of Iuz to the north.</p>

<p>But the Oeridians aren’t the only players in this game. To the west, you’ve got the Baklunish cultures in states like Ekbir and Zeif. Think minarets piercing the sky, bazaars bustling with strange wares, and magical traditions that would make your average Oeridian wizard’s pointy hat spin.</p>

<p>And let’s not forget the Suel. These folks have a bit of a checkered past, what with the Scarlet Brotherhood lurking in the shadows. Imagine a secret society of working in the shadows to infiltrate ever aspect of society, with plans spanning the continent. Paranoid yet? You should be.</p>

<p>Then there are the Flan, the original humans of these lands. Their great civilizations might have faded, but their legacy lives on in places like Tenh and among the nomadic Rovers of the Barrens. These are the folks who can tell you what the Flanaess was like before it was cool.</p>

<h3 id="welcome-to-the-city-of-adventure">Welcome to the City of Adventure</h3>

<p>At the heart of all this stands the Free City of Greyhawk itself. A melting pot of cultures where an Oeridian merchant might be haggling with a Baklunish mage over a Flan artifact, all while a Suel thief picks both their pockets. It’s a city of adventure, intrigue, and more shady deals than you can shake a wand of fireballs at. At the time, it was obvious to me that the City of Greyhawk was the city of Lankhmar from Fritz Leiber’s Fafhrd and the Gray Mouser stories, so I was immediatly hooked.</p>

<p>But humans aren’t the only ones stirring the pot. The Ulek States show us that dwarves, elves, and gnomes have long established cutures of their own. They’re right in the thick of it, forging alliances and shaping the political landscape alongside their human neighbors. This carried much of the tension between cultures that setup a dangerous world in the original days of DnD, which I think ahs softened over time. It will be interesting to see what tension DMs setup in their own versions of Greyhawk.</p>

<h3 id="why-greyhawk-why-now">Why Greyhawk? Why Now?</h3>

<p>So, why is Wizards of the Coast bringing Greyhawk back into the spotlight? Well, for one, it’s a return to roots for the 50th anniversary of D&amp;D. Greyhawk is where many of D&amp;D’s iconic elements were born. Ever cast Mordenkainen’s Magnificent Mansion or Bigby’s Hand? You can thank Greyhawk for those. Ever delved into the Tomb of Horrors or faced the horrors of the Temple of Elemental Evil? Greyhawk, baby.</p>

<p>But it’s more than just nostalgia. Greyhawk offers a grittier, more grounded take on high fantasy than the Forgotten Realms. It’s a world where political intrigue is as deadly as any dragon’s breath, where the line between hero and villain is often blurred, and where every victory feels hard-earned. For me, it’s the template for one of my favorite 2e settings, Birthright. At least, this is the original vision of Greyhawk.  I think it’s fair to say that WotC has a more portable vision in mind, a Greyhawk that can adapt to any group, any world, and any story. I have to confess, if this is the case, it makes me a little sad.  A setting should have a point of view, a flavor that makes it unique.  I adore the Forgotten Realms, and I love the homebrew that has sprung from it, but Greyhawk deserves more than a simple “generic fantasy” approach.</p>

<p>WotC has been teasing us with Greyhawk references throughout the 5e era. But now, with part of the recent Vecna: Eve of Ruin module set on Oerth, it seems they’re finally ready to pull back the curtain.  I sincerly hope they do it justice when the setting returns to the 2024 Dungeon Master’s Guide in November.</p>

<h3 id="what-this-means-for-you">What This Means for You</h3>

<p>Whether you’re a grizzled veteran eager to return to familiar lands or a wide-eyed newcomer ready to explore this classic setting for the first time, Greyhawk’s return as the default D&amp;D setting is big news. But what does it really mean for your gaming table?</p>

<p>First off, if you’re hoping to recreate the gritty feel of original Greyhawk, you might find yourself wrestling with the D&amp;D 2024 system. Let’s face it, D&amp;D hasn’t been truly gritty for a long time, and the 2024 edition seems to be dialing up the power level yet another notch. This presents an interesting challenge for DMs: how do you maintain Greyhawk’s classic tone when your players are wielding more power than ever?</p>

<p>On the flip side, the new Bastion system introduced in the 2024 DMG could be a perfect fit for Greyhawk’s political landscape. Players might find themselves quickly rising to become lords of their own realms. Having a rich, detailed setting like Greyhawk to ground these newfound fiefdoms could be incredibly satisfying - provided your players buy into the world’s deep background and complex politics.</p>

<p>It’ll be fascinating to see WotC’s modern take on this classic setting. How will they balance nostalgia with the need to appeal to new players? How dedicated will they be to fully supporting Greyhawk beyond its initial reintroduction? And perhaps most intriguingly, how will the new Greyhawk interact with the evolving Open Gaming License (OGL)? These are questions that could shape not just how we play in Greyhawk, but how we engage with D&amp;D as a whole in the coming years.</p>

<p>For DMs, this means a wealth of opportunities. You’ll have access to a rich, detailed world with decades of lore to draw from. At the same time, you’ll face the challenge of adapting this classic setting to modern game mechanics and player expectations. It’s a chance to blend the best of old-school D&amp;D with the innovations of recent years.</p>

<p>For players, Greyhawk offers a world ripe for exploration and conquest. Whether you’re delving into the depths of Castle Greyhawk, navigating the political intrigues of the Free City, or carving out your own baronies with the Bastion system, there’s no shortage of adventures waiting for you.</p>

<p>Ultimately, the return of Greyhawk is more than just a nostalgic throwback. It’s an opportunity to bridge the gap between D&amp;D’s roots and its future, to explore how a classic setting can evolve to meet the needs of modern players while still retaining its unique charm. Whether this experiment succeeds will depend not just on WotC’s execution, but on how we as a community embrace and shape this new incarnation of a beloved world.</p>

<p>So, are you ready to make your mark on the Flanaess? To walk the streets of the Free City, to face the horrors lurking in Castle Greyhawk, to shape the fate of empires? Greyhawk is calling, adventurers. And this time, it’s calling from the very core of D&amp;D itself. The question is: how will you answer?</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="rpg resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore Greyhawk's return as D&D's default setting in 2024. Discover its rich history, unique features, and what it means for players and DMs alike.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/greyhawkmap_1024x585.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/greyhawkmap_1024x585.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/29/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-09-29T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-29T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/29/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/29/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>As we dive into the latest developments in the tabletop RPG landscape, there’s a wealth of exciting news that every TTRPG fan should be aware of. From significant releases in the Dungeons &amp; Dragons universe to the resurgence of classic games, this week has proven to be pivotal for both new and seasoned players. Here’s a detailed look at the most relevant stories from September 22, 2024, to September 29, 2024.</p>

<h3 id="drunkards-druggies--delinquents-titmouse-the-studio-behind-vox-machina-launches-a-new-ttrpg">Drunkards, Druggies, &amp; Delinquents: Titmouse, the Studio Behind Vox Machina, Launches a New TTRPG</h3>
<p><em>September 24, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168668/drunkards-druggies-delinquents-titmouse-the-the-legend-of-vox-machina-studio-launch-a-ttrpg/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>; #TTRPG #LegendofVoxMachina #NewRelease</p>

<p>Titmouse, the animation studio renowned for “The Legend of Vox Machina,” has launched a new tabletop RPG titled “Drunkards, Druggies, &amp; Delinquents.” This game promises to deliver a unique blend of humor and adventure, reflecting the studio’s creative ethos.</p>

<p>This introduction showcases the crossover potential between animation and tabletop gaming, appealing to fans of both mediums. For those interested in exploring this new game, more information can be found in the article at <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168668/drunkards-druggies-delinquents-titmouse-the-the-legend-of-vox-machina-studio-launch-a-ttrpg/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>.</p>

<h3 id="wotc-inflates-sales-numbers-for-players-handbook">WOTC Inflates Sales Numbers for Player’s Handbook</h3>
<p><em>September 23, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tabletopgamingnews.com/wotc-inflates-sales-numbers-for-players-handbook-real-figures-might-be-shockingly-low/" target="_blank">Tabletop Gaming News</a>; #D&amp;D #Sales #PlayersHandbook</p>

<p>Recent reports suggest that Wizards of the Coast may have exaggerated sales figures for the new Player’s Handbook, with real physical sales potentially falling short of expectations. This news raises concerns about the marketing strategies employed by WOTC and the overall health of tabletop RPG sales in an increasingly digital marketplace.</p>

<p>Understanding these dynamics is crucial for fans and retailers alike, as it could impact future releases and the types of products that get prioritized. For a deeper dive into the implications of these sales figures, check out the full article on <a href="https://www.tabletopgamingnews.com/wotc-inflates-sales-numbers-for-players-handbook-real-figures-might-be-shockingly-low/" target="_blank">Tabletop Gaming News</a>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>This week has seen a vibrant mix of new releases, classic revivals, and significant industry shifts that will shape the future of tabletop RPGs. Whether you’re a long-time player or new to the scene, there’s plenty to explore and engage with in the world of TTRPGs. Stay tuned for more updates as the community continues to evolve!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><category term="DnD" /><category term="Kickstarter" /><category term="WOTC" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Catch up on the latest TTRPG news, including new releases, classic revivals, and industry developments from September 22-29, 2024.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/22/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-09-22T21:31:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-22T21:31:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/22/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/22/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back, TTRPG enthusiasts! This week has been buzzing with exciting developments in the world of tabletop roleplaying games. Whether you’re a Dungeon Master looking for new material or a player eager to dive into fresh adventures, we’ve got you covered. Let’s dive into the latest trends and news from the TTRPG community.</p>

<p><strong>Lets dive into the latest News you may have missed last week!</strong></p>

<h4 id="backerkit---gaslight-victorian-fantasy-revised-and-expanded-for-5e">Backerkit - Gaslight Victorian Fantasy Revised and Expanded for 5E</h4>
<p><strong>September 15, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>, <em>Tags: 5E, Victorian Fantasy, Backerkit</em></p>

<p>The much-loved Gaslight Victorian Fantasy setting for 5th Edition is getting a significant upgrade. The revised and expanded edition promises new mechanics and adventures, breathing fresh life into this unique genre. Victorian fantasy fans and 5E players alike will find something to love in this new release.</p>

<p><strong>Why Read More:</strong> Dive into the details of what new content and mechanics are being introduced and get ready to back this project on Backerkit. <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/backerkit-gaslight-victorian-fantasy.html" target="_blank">Read more here</a>.</p>

<h4 id="44-year-old-ttrpg-rolemaster-finally-launches-on-roll20">44-year-old TTRPG “Rolemaster” Finally Launches on Roll20</h4>
<p><strong>September 16, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>; <em>Tags: Rolemaster, Roll20, Classic TTRPG</em></p>

<p>Rolemaster, the iconic TTRPG known for its detailed mechanics and depth, has finally made its debut on Roll20. This launch allows a new generation of players to experience the intricate gameplay of Rolemaster online, making it more accessible than ever before.</p>

<p><strong>Why Read More:</strong> Learn about the features and enhancements that come with the Roll20 adaptation and see how you can integrate this classic into your online gaming sessions. <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168554/44-year-old-ttrpg-rolemaster-finally-launches-on-roll20/" target="_blank">Read more here</a>.</p>

<h4 id="the-other-osr-sanction">The Other OSR: Sanction</h4>
<p><strong>September 16, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://rlyehreviews.blogspot.com/" target="_blank">R’lyeh Reviews</a>; <em>Tags: OSR, Sanction, TTRPG</em></p>

<p>This article explores the latest offerings in the OSR (Old School Revival) scene, focusing on a new game titled “Sanction,” which is designed to engage players with classic gameplay mechanics while introducing fresh narratives and challenges.</p>

<p><strong>Why You Should Read More:</strong> For fans of the OSR movement, “Sanction” offers a blend of nostalgia and innovation. <a href="https://rlyehreviews.blogspot.com/2024/09/the-other-osr-sanction.html" target="_blank">Read the full article</a>.</p>

<h4 id="2024-dungeons--dragons-players-handbook-now-available-fresh-upgrades-and-enhancements-await">2024 Dungeons &amp; Dragons Player’s Handbook Now Available: Fresh Upgrades and Enhancements Await!</h4>
<p><strong>September 17, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.geeksaresexy.net/" target="_blank">Geeks Are Sexy</a>; <em>Tags: D&amp;D, Player’s Handbook, New Edition</em></p>

<p>The new edition of the Dungeons &amp; Dragons Player’s Handbook is now available, packed with significant upgrades, enhancements, and new content aimed at enriching the gameplay experience. This release is set to redefine the core of D&amp;D gameplay with fresh rules and expanded lore.</p>

<p><strong>Why Read More:</strong> Discover the new features and content that will enhance your D&amp;D sessions and find out where you can get your hands on the latest edition. <a href="https://www.geeksaresexy.net/2024/09/17/2024-dungeons-dragons-players-handbook-now-available-fresh-upgrades-and-enhancements-await/" target="_blank">Read more here</a>.</p>

<h4 id="dd-2024-players-handbook-debuts-with-mixed-success">D&amp;D 2024 Players Handbook Debuts with Mixed Success</h4>
<p><strong>September 18, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>; #DungeonsAndDragons #PlayersHandbook #CommunityFeedback</p>

<p>Following the release of the 2024 Player’s Handbook, mixed reactions have surfaced within the community. While many appreciate the updates, others express concerns about certain changes that may alter the balance of gameplay. This analysis highlights the ongoing dialogue between developers and players, underscoring the importance of community input in the evolution of such a beloved game.</p>

<p>For a closer examination of the feedback and the implications for the D&amp;D community, read the full analysis <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168589/dd-2024-players-handbook-debuts-with-mixed-success/" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h4 id="state-of-play-kobold-press-issues-the-no-ai-pledge">State of Play: Kobold Press Issues the No AI Pledge</h4>
<p><strong>September 19, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://koboldpress.com/" target="_blank">Kobold Press</a>; <em>Tags: Kobold Press, No AI, TTRPG</em></p>

<p>Kobold Press has officially pledged to not utilize AI in their game design processes, emphasizing their commitment to human creativity and the importance of original content in the tabletop gaming community.</p>

<p><strong>Why You Should Read More:</strong> This pledge highlights a significant stance in the industry, reinforcing the value of human creativity in game design. <a href="https://koboldpress.com/state-of-play-kobold-press-issues-the-no-ai-pledge/" target="_blank">Read the full article</a>.</p>

<p>See my artifcle on my thoughts on <a href="/2024/09/20/ethical-ai-in-ttrpgs/">Ethical use of AI in TTRPGs</a>.</p>

<h4 id="trench-crusade-kickstarter-release-date--campaign-details">Trench Crusade Kickstarter Release Date &amp; Campaign Details</h4>
<p><strong>September 19, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.destructoid.com" target="_blank">Destructoid</a>; #Kickstarter #TrenchCrusade #TTRPG</p>

<p>The upcoming Kickstarter for Trench Crusade has been announced, building excitement for a new TTRPG that promises to blend tactical gameplay with rich storytelling. This campaign will offer unique rewards and stretch goals, aiming to capture the interest of both veteran gamers and newcomers alike. The project reflects a growing trend of crowdfunding in the RPG space, allowing creators to directly engage with their audience.</p>

<p>For details on the campaign specifics and how to participate, check out the full article <a href="https://www.destructoid.com/trench-crusade-kickstarter-release-date-campaign-details/?utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=trench-crusade-kickstarter-release-date-campaign-details" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>This week’s TTRPG news highlights the dynamic and evolving nature of our beloved hobby. From new editions and settings to significant industry pledges, there’s plenty to be excited about. Stay tuned to Optionalrule.com for more updates, and don’t forget to check out the detailed articles linked above to stay ahead of the game. Happy adventuring!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><category term="5E" /><category term="Victorian Fantasy" /><category term="Backerkit" /><category term="Rolemaster" /><category term="Roll20" /><category term="D&amp;D" /><category term="Player&apos;s Handbook" /><category term="Kobold Press" /><category term="AI" /><category term="Game Design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly TTRPG news roundup: Victorian Fantasy, Rolemaster, D&D, Kobold Press, AI, Game Design]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Embracing AI in TTRPGs - Enhancing, Not Replacing, Creativity</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/20/ethical-ai-in-ttrpgs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embracing AI in TTRPGs - Enhancing, Not Replacing, Creativity" /><published>2024-09-20T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-20T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/20/ethical-ai-in-ttrpgs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/20/ethical-ai-in-ttrpgs/"><![CDATA[<p>The TTRPG community has been abuzz with discussions about AI, and understandably so. The mere mention of artificial intelligence in our beloved hobby often sparks heated debates and anxiety. There’s a palpable fear that AI might replace the human creativity that forms the very essence of tabletop roleplaying games. In these discussions, we’ve sometimes been too quick to judge, too harsh in our criticisms, and perhaps a bit too reactionary. Without doubt, there’s Fear, Uncertainty, and Doubt (FUD) surrounding AI, but there are also great possibilities when used thoughtfully. As with many topics in our community, we need to approach the AI conversation with more open-mindedness and less cruelty towards those with differing views. After all, the spirit of TTRPGs is one of collaboration and imagination – qualities we should bring to these important discussions as well.</p>

<p>Recently, Hasbro’s CEO mentioned exploring ways to <a href="https://www.enworld.org/threads/hasbro-ceo-chris-cocks-talks-ai-usage-in-d-d-updated.706638/" target="_blank">incorporate AI into D&amp;D</a>, which predictably caused a significant backlash. Many assumed this meant replacing creative teams with AI-generated content. However, it’s worth noting that this wasn’t explicitly stated, and there are numerous potential applications of AI that could enhance, rather than replace, the TTRPG experience.</p>

<p>While I share the community’s concerns about AI-generated books, adventures, or artwork, I believe we’re overlooking some genuinely beneficial uses of AI that could improve our gaming experiences. Let’s explore some of these possibilities:</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/ttrpg_players_and_robot_480x600.webp" alt="People playing dungeons and dragons with a robot looking on." height="600" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<h3 id="1-a-dndbeyond-search-that-actually-works">1. A DnDBeyond Search that Actually Works!</h3>

<p>Imagine a D&amp;D Beyond with a truly functional search feature powered by AI. A Perplexity-like AI could revolutionize how we access and utilize the vast amount of information in the digital toolset. This would save DMs and players countless hours of frustration trying to locate specific rules, spells, or creature stats.  Extend this to your library of PDFs, GM Notes, and Campaign Logs and now you’ve got a truly useful personal assistant. <em>“Show me examples of area effect zones in grid based combat from the DMG.”</em></p>

<h3 id="2-lore-summarization">2. Lore Summarization</h3>

<p>One of the most exciting potential applications of AI in TTRPGs is summarizing published content. An AI chatbot that could provide concise summaries of lore from various settings like the Forgotten Realms, Dark Sun, or Eberron would be invaluable. This tool could help DMs quickly refresh their memory or give players a brief overview of a setting without spoiling key plot points. <em>“Summarize the history of the city of Waterdeep from the Dungeon Master’s Guide.”</em>, <em>“Give me a list of the named wizards from the city of Thay.”</em></p>

<h3 id="3-advanced-random-tables">3. Advanced Random Tables</h3>

<p>We already use random tables for various aspects of our games. AI could take this concept further, generating more complex and contextually appropriate random elements on the fly. This could include NPC personalities, location details, or even plot hooks that align with the current game state. Better yet, if you have access to your campaign notes you can do things like ask it to related a random encounter to a specific NPC or location. <em>“Generate a random encounter along the Triboar trail that involves bandits and smugglers and add a complication to the encounter based on the notes for the mountain gnome enclave.”</em></p>

<h3 id="4-game-management-assistant">4. Game Management Assistant</h3>

<p>AI could be a game-changer for the administrative side of running a TTRPG campaign. Imagine an AI assistant that helps with:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Scheduling games and managing player availability</li>
  <li>Keeping track of session logs and important plot points</li>
  <li>Organizing campaign notes and player character information</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="5-vtt-scene-preparation-and-management">5. VTT Scene Preparation and Management</h3>

<p>Virtual Tabletop (VTT) platforms have opened up new possibilities for online play, but they’ve also increased the workload for DMs. An AI assistant could help streamline VTT preparation and management by:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Suggesting appropriate maps and tokens based on the planned encounter</li>
  <li>Automating lighting and fog of war settings</li>
  <li>Handling initiative tracking and turn management</li>
</ul>

<p>This kind of AI integration could significantly reduce the time DMs spend wrestling with VTT logistics, allowing them to focus more on storytelling and player engagement.</p>

<h3 id="6-managing-characters-and-game-content">6. Managing Characters and Game Content</h3>

<p>At their core, TTRPGs are essentially analog databases. We constantly reference character abilities, skills, equipment, and various other game elements. This often involves tedious record-keeping and calculations that, while necessary, aren’t particularly enjoyable. AI opens up exciting new possibilities to streamline these processes and make our game data more accessible and useful.</p>

<p><strong>Character Sheet Management</strong></p>

<p>Imagine an AI assistant that can instantly provide you with any information from your character sheet, summarize it, transform it into a different format. Need to know your current load and carrying capacity? Just ask. Want a quick summary of all flammable items in your inventory? Need a version of your character with abilities after you’ve been polymorphed into a purple octopus? The AI can compile that for you in seconds.</p>

<p><strong>Equipment Details On-Demand</strong></p>

<p>Ever wondered exactly what’s in your component pouch or what that obscure magic item does? An AI could provide detailed breakdowns of equipment contents and magical properties on command. For example:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“List all the components in my component pouch.”</li>
  <li>“What are the exact effects of the Ring of Spell Storing I just found?”</li>
  <li>“Calculate how many days of rations I can carry at my current strength.”</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Group Information Aggregation</strong></p>

<p>DMs often need to compile information about the entire party quickly. An AI assistant could be invaluable for this:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“Create a table with all characters’ ability modifiers, initiative bonuses, and passive perception scores.”</li>
  <li>“List all party members’ languages and their tool proficiencies.”</li>
  <li>“Summarize the party’s current inventory of healing potions and scrolls.”</li>
  <li>“I have 4 days of downtime and 300gp, what could I craft in that time?”</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Rules and Mechanics Clarification</strong></p>

<p>When disputes or questions about rules arise, an AI could quickly provide relevant information from the rulebooks, saving time spent leafing through pages or searching PDFs.</p>

<p><strong>Campaign Note Organization</strong></p>

<p>For DMs, keeping track of campaign notes, NPCs, and plot threads can be challenging. An AI assistant could help organize and recall this information effortlessly, allowing DMs to focus more on storytelling and less on bookkeeping.</p>

<ul>
  <li>“I need to know what plot threads I left open in the city of Thornwick.”</li>
  <li>“Give me a list of funny quotes from the campaign.”</li>
  <li>“Randomly remove 3 items from from the inventory of every character.”</li>
  <li>“I need to know what my party is currently carrying. Give me a compiled list of everything.”</li>
  <li>“What was the last mention of an NPC named Kaelin in the campaign notes?”</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>While it’s crucial to remain vigilant about preserving the human creativity at the heart of TTRPGs, we shouldn’t dismiss AI entirely. By focusing on applications that enhance rather than replace human input, we can leverage AI to make our games more accessible, efficient, and enjoyable.</p>

<p>The key is to view AI as a tool that empowers DMs and players, not as a replacement for the imagination and storytelling that make our hobby unique. As we continue to explore the potential of AI in TTRPGs, let’s keep an open mind about how it can be used to elevate our gaming experiences while preserving the essence of what makes tabletop roleplaying special.</p>

<p>By leveraging AI for data management tasks, we can focus more on the creative and interactive aspects of the game. The tedious record-keeping becomes just a prompt away from being useful, allowing players and DMs to immerse themselves more fully in the storytelling and roleplaying experience.</p>

<p>It’s important to note that while AI can greatly enhance our ability to manage and access game information, it doesn’t replace the need for human decision-making and creativity. The AI serves as a powerful tool to support and streamline the game, allowing us to spend more time on the aspects of TTRPGs that we truly enjoy.</p>

<p>What are your thoughts on AI in TTRPGs? Are there other applications you think could be beneficial? Hit me on on X and let me know!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="rpg resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore positive AI applications in TTRPGs. Discover how AI can enhance gameplay, streamline admin tasks, and support creativity without replacing human input.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/ttrpg_players_and_robot_1200x600.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/ttrpg_players_and_robot_1200x600.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/15/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-09-15T20:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-15T20:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/15/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/15/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back to Insight Check! This is my experiment in a weekly roundup of TTRPG news and trends you may have missed. From nostalgic franchises making their tabletop debut to beloved indie darlings expanding their realms, we’ve got a little magic for every gaming group. This week’s roundup covers everything from a transformative bundle that’s more than meets the eye to Root’s woodland creatures delving into dungeons, community highlights from Tabletop Scotland, and even a liminal deal that bridges our world and the next. So, grab your character sheets and settle into your comfiest chair (I’ve got my trusty tankard of coffee right here) as we explore the latest happenings in the TTRPG world. Whether you’re a dungeon master looking for new tools or a player seeking your next great campaign, I promise there’s something here to spark your imagination and fuel your next adventure.</p>

<p>Ready to roll? Let’s dive into stories for the week of September 15th 2024!</p>

<h3 id="humble-bundle---transformers-rpg">Humble Bundle - Transformers RPG</h3>
<p><em>September 8, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/humble-bundle-transformers-rpg.html" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>, #HumbleBundle #Transformers #RPG #Deals</p>

<p>A new Humble Bundle featuring a Transformers RPG has been launched, providing fans with a unique gaming experience. This bundle offers a range of materials and resources that can help you dive deep into the world of Transformers, making it a must-have for fans of the franchise. If you’re a Transformers fan or just looking for a new RPG to explore, this bundle offers excellent value. Check out the <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/humble-bundle-transformers-rpg.html" target="_blank">full article here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="root-the-roleplaying-game--ruins-and-expeditions-adds-dungeons-and-delves-and-monsters">‘Root: The Roleplaying Game’ – “Ruins and Expeditions” Adds Dungeons and Delves and Monsters</h3>
<p><em>September 9, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/09/root-the-roleplaying-game-ruins-and-expeditions-adds-dungeons-and-delves-and-monsters.html" target="_blank">Bell of Lost Souls</a>, #RootRPG #Expansion #Dungeons #Monsters</p>

<p>The latest expansion for ‘Root: The Roleplaying Game’ introduces new adventures, including dungeons, delves, and monsters, expanding the gameplay for fans. This addition brings a fresh layer of excitement and complexity to an already beloved game. If you’re a fan of Root, this expansion is a game-changer. Discover more about the new features <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/09/root-the-roleplaying-game-ruins-and-expeditions-adds-dungeons-and-delves-and-monsters.html" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="audio-exp-podcast-253--the-tabletop-scotland-download">Audio EXP Podcast: #253 – The Tabletop Scotland download</h3>
<p><em>September 10, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168503/audio-exp-podcast-253-the-tabletop-scotland-download/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>, #Podcast #TabletopScotland #Community</p>

<p>The latest episode of the Audio EXP Podcast discusses recent developments in the tabletop gaming community, including highlights from Tabletop Scotland. This episode is packed with insights and updates that are sure to interest any TTRPG fan. Stay updated with the latest community news and events by listening to this episode. Find out more <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168503/audio-exp-podcast-253-the-tabletop-scotland-download/" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="voting-open-for-the-rpg-publisher-spotlight-october-2024">Voting open for the RPG Publisher Spotlight October 2024</h3>
<p><em>September 11, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168249/voting-open-for-the-rpg-publisher-spotlight-october-2024/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>, #RPGPublisher #Voting #Community</p>

<p>Voting has opened for the RPG Publisher Spotlight, allowing fans to recognize their favorite publishers in the industry. This is a fantastic opportunity to support the creators who bring your favorite games to life. Show your support for your favorite RPG publishers by participating in the voting. Learn how you can cast your vote <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168249/voting-open-for-the-rpg-publisher-spotlight-october-2024/" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="kickstarter---warlock-knight-dfrpg">Kickstarter - Warlock Knight (DFRPG)</h3>
<p><em>September 12, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/kickstarter-warlock-knight-dfrpg.html" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>, #Kickstarter #WarlockKnight #DFRPG</p>

<p>A new Kickstarter campaign for ‘Warlock Knight’ has launched, aiming to bring fresh content and adventures to the DFRPG community. This campaign promises to add exciting new elements to the game, making it a worthwhile investment for fans. Support the Kickstarter and be among the first to experience the new content. Check out the campaign details <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/kickstarter-warlock-knight-dfrpg.html" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="bundle-of-holding---liminal-modiphius">Bundle of Holding - Liminal (Modiphius)</h3>
<p><em>September 13, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/bundle-of-holding-liminal-modiphius.html" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>, #BundleOfHolding #Liminal #Modiphius #Deals</p>

<p>A new Bundle of Holding featuring the Liminal RPG from Modiphius is available, providing great deals for players looking to explore new settings. This bundle offers a rich and immersive experience at a fraction of the cost. Don’t miss out on this fantastic deal. Learn more about what’s included in the bundle <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/bundle-of-holding-liminal-modiphius.html" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>This week has been a whirlwind of exciting news and developments in the TTRPG world. Whether you’re a fan of Transformers, Root, or looking to support new projects on Kickstarter, there’s something for everyone. Stay tuned to OptionalRules.com for more updates and insights into the ever-evolving world of tabletop roleplaying games.</p>

<p>Happy gaming!</p>

<p>I hope this roundup helps you stay informed and inspired for your next gaming session. Don’t forget to check out the links for more detailed information and consider supporting the creators who make our favorite games possible. Until next time, roll those dice and embark on new adventures!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[TTRPG News and Trends you may have missed for the week ending of September 15th 2024.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/09/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-09-09T20:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-09T20:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/09/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/09/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the first Insight Check! A small experiment I’m trying out to see if there is any interest in a weekly news and trends series. In this first weekly round-up, we’ve got everything from digital tools leveling up (and changing their character name) to video game developers crossing the planes into our tabletop realm. We’ll explore how D&amp;D is rolling natural 20s in helping folks with autism, and we’ll peek behind the DM screen at a horror game that’s sure to give your Charisma score a fright.</p>

<p>So, pull up a chair, order your favorite fantasy brew, and let’s embark on this quest together. Who knows? You might just gain advantage on your next roll at the gaming table. Ready your dice, and let’s dive in!</p>

<h3 id="study-playing-dungeons--dragons-helps-autistic-players-in-social-interactions">Study: Playing Dungeons &amp; Dragons helps autistic players in social interactions</h3>
<p><strong>September 4, 2024</strong>, Ars Technica; #D&amp;D #Autism<br />
A recent study reveals that playing D&amp;D significantly aids autistic players in developing social skills. The study provides empirical evidence that the game’s mechanics and narrative-driven engagement help players navigate social cues and build friendships. This aligns with a growing trend within the RPG community to promote inclusivity and accessibility, echoing historical movements towards making gaming environments more welcoming for diverse players. The therapeutic potential of RPGs is becoming more recognized, demonstrating a shift in how games are perceived beyond mere entertainment.<br />
<a href="https://arstechnica.com/science/2024/09/study-playing-dungeons-dragons-helps-autistic-players-in-social-interactions/" target="_blank">Read more</a></p>

<h3 id="splinter-cell-and-far-cry-2-developer-launches-new-ttrpg--mythmaster-rpg-now-in-beta">‘Splinter Cell’ and ‘Far Cry 2’ Developer Launches New TTRPG – ‘Mythmaster RPG’ Now In Beta</h3>
<p><strong>September 5, 2024</strong>, Bell of Lost Souls; #TTRPG #Mythmaster RPG<br />
In an exciting development for tabletop gaming, the developers behind popular video games like ‘Splinter Cell’ and ‘Far Cry 2’ have launched ‘Mythmaster RPG,’ now in beta testing. This move signifies a growing trend of crossover between video games and tabletop RPGs, where established brands are exploring new formats to engage with fans. The historical connection between video games and tabletop RPGs has been long-standing, with many mechanics and storytelling techniques crossing over. The influx of video game developers into the TTRPG space could lead to innovative gameplay experiences and attract a broader audience to tabletop gaming.<br />
<a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/09/splinter-cell-and-far-cry-2-developer-launches-new-ttrpg-mythmaster-rpg-now-in-beta.html" target="_blank">Read more</a></p>

<h3 id="sleepy-hollow-kids-in-the-attic-fund-folk-horror-ttrpg">Sleepy Hollow: Kids in the Attic fund folk horror TTRPG</h3>
<p><strong>September 5, 2024</strong>, Geek Native; #TTRPG #Sleepy Hollow<br />
The successful funding of a folk horror tabletop RPG set in the ‘Sleepy Hollow’ universe speaks to the nostalgia-driven themes that continue to captivate gamers. This project taps into the rich history of folklore and horror in RPGs, which has been a staple since the inception of the genre. As tabletop RPGs increasingly explore unique and culturally rich settings, the ‘Sleepy Hollow’ game exemplifies how historical narratives can be reimagined through interactive storytelling. This trend highlights a revival of interest in genre-specific games, blending traditional folklore with modern gaming mechanics.<br />
<a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168259/sleepy-hollow-kids-in-the-attic-fund-folk-horror-ttrpg/" target="_blank">Read more</a></p>

<h3 id="hedron-worldbuilding-platform-raises-51000-and-changes-name">Hedron: Worldbuilding platform raises $51,000 (and changes name)</h3>
<p><strong>September 6, 2024</strong>, Geek Native; #TTRPG #Worldbuilding<br />
The worldbuilding platform ‘Hedron’ has successfully raised $51,000 and announced a name change, reflecting the evolving needs of tabletop RPG creators. This funding success illustrates the increasing reliance on crowdfunding within the tabletop community, a trend that has reshaped how games are developed and marketed. Historically, many RPGs began as grassroots initiatives, and this model continues to empower creators by providing direct access to funding and community support. Hedron’s evolution signifies a commitment to enhancing the creative process for RPG developers, ensuring a diverse range of games and settings for players.<br />
<a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168313/hedron-worldbuilding-platform-raises-51000-and-changes-name/" target="_blank">Read more</a></p>

<h3 id="cyberpunk-2077-the-board-game-smashes-crowdfunding-goals-with-over-3-million-raised-and-counting">‘Cyberpunk 2077: The Board Game’ Smashes Crowdfunding Goals With Over $3 Million Raised, And Counting</h3>
<p><strong>September 6, 2024</strong>, Bell of Lost Souls; #Cyberpunk 2077 #Board Game<br />
The crowdfunding campaign for ‘Cyberpunk 2077: The Board Game’ has exceeded expectations by raising over $3 million. This monumental success underscores the enduring popularity of the Cyberpunk franchise and its transition into the board game realm. Historically, adaptations from video games to tabletop formats have seen varied success, but the massive backing for this project indicates a robust interest in hybrid gaming experiences. This trend reflects a broader movement within the industry to capitalize on popular IPs and engage fans in new and interactive ways, merging the excitement of video gaming with traditional tabletop experiences.<br />
<a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/09/cyberpunk-2077-the-board-game-smashes-crowdfunding-goals-with-over-3-million-raised-and-counting.html" target="_blank">Read more</a></p>

<h3 id="new-release---humans-humans-1st-edition-for-monsters-monsters">New Release - Humans! Humans! 1st Edition (For Monsters! Monsters!)</h3>
<p><strong>September 7, 2024</strong>, Tenkar’s Tavern; #TTRPG #Humans! Humans!<br />
The release of ‘Humans! Humans!’, designed as a companion for ‘Monsters! Monsters!’, expands the narrative options available to tabletop RPG enthusiasts. This new release is part of a growing trend towards creating interconnected games that enhance player experience by allowing different perspectives and gameplay styles. Historically, the RPG genre has thrived on the expansion of lore and mechanics, with numerous games branching off from established titles. The introduction of this new edition signifies the ongoing evolution of RPG systems, promoting diversity in storytelling and gameplay experiences for all types of players.<br />
<a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/new-release-humans-humans-1st-edition.html" target="_blank">Read more</a></p>

<p>That’s it for the past week, ping me on twitter if you found anything interesting!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Latest TTRPG News and Trends for the week of September 7th 2024.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>