<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-26T17:18:28+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Optional Rule</title><subtitle>Optional Rule is a blog for DMs and Players alike of DnD 5e and any tabletop  roleplaying game. It offers rules, insight, analysis, and resources that help people run games and enhance their play.</subtitle><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Human Side of D&amp;amp;D History</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/11/26/the-human-side-of-dnd-history/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Human Side of D&amp;amp;D History" /><published>2024-11-26T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-26T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/11/26/the-human-side-of-dnd-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/11/26/the-human-side-of-dnd-history/"><![CDATA[<p>I came across something today that made me reflect deeply on how we, as a community, engage with the people who shaped our hobby. Tim Cain (creator of Fallout and lead at Troika) posted a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kYg6uz1Gqf4" target="_blank">heartfelt video</a> about his team’s work on Temple of Elemental Evil (2003) being omitted from “D&amp;D: Art and Arcana” - the comprehensive art history book from 2018. This got me thinking about how we remember our hobby’s creators, particularly in light of the recent online debates about Gary Gygax’s legacy and his critisism in the recent D&amp;D publications.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/CorpseKing_Gygax_Tweet_screenshot_480x504.webp" alt="A barbarian holding a legal document." height="504" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">The tweet that started the latest round of online debates.</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>What struck me wasn’t just the omission itself, but how Tim spoke about it. He talked about his team physically cutting up his personal original ToEE module to share with artists because they couldn’t get official copies. He spoke about how they transformed Zuggtmoy’s appearance so dramatically that it became canon. These weren’t just professional grievances - they were personal investments of passion and creativity that somehow got lost in the historical record.</p>

<p>This resonated strongly with me, particularly given our ongoing discussions about Gary Gygax’s legacy. I think we’ve lost something important in how we talk about these creators. Gary has become something of an internet token, deployed either as a shield or a target depending on the argument being made. But those of us who remember the pre-internet days know a different Gary - someone who was essentially every D&amp;D fan’s pen pal, who you’d actually meet at GenCon, who would run games for fans and engage in real conversations.</p>

<p>I’ve been following the recent YouTube discussions on this topic, and the contrast is telling. Dan “Professor DM” of the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Esf22_cFQ4o" target="_blank">DungeonCraft</a> channel approaches Gary as a complex human being, acknowledging both his contributions and his humanity. Meanwhile, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ATwHT-3YLzk" target="_blank">Bob World Builder’s Video</a> take was uncharacterisiticall un-kind and dismissive.  His commenary feels more like a response to a meme, conflating Gary with current cultural battles that have nothing to do with his actual work or person. Combined with Bob’s departure from X to Bluesky, it’s clear there is a lot going on there beyond the topic, which makes feel like deflected anger.</p>

<p>Tim Cain’s video serves as a powerful reminder that there are real people behind everything we love about this hobby. His team’s work on ToEE might not have achieved the commercial success they hoped for, but it represented real innovation - they were the first to implement 3E rules in a computer game, the only ones to bring Greyhawk to digital life, and they created artistic interpretations that became canon.</p>

<p>The community’s selective empathy is something we should examine. We’ll passionately defend creators against AI or corporate overreach, but then turn around and reduce past creators to caricatures when it suits our current cultural arguments. Whether it’s Gary Gygax, Tim Cain’s team, or any of the countless others who’ve contributed to this hobby, they deserve to be remembered as real people who did real work.</p>

<p>None of these oversights or mischaracterizations are tragedies in the grand scheme of things. But they matter to the people who poured their creativity and passion into building this hobby we all love. When we reduce them to mere symbols in our cultural debates, we lose something valuable - the human story of how D&amp;D became what it is today.</p>

<p>I hope we can find ways to discuss the history and future of D&amp;D that honor the humanity of everyone involved - even (perhaps especially) when we’re being critical. After all, isn’t the human element what makes this hobby special in the first place?</p>

<p>What are your thoughts on this? How do you think we can better preserve and discuss the human side of D&amp;D’s history?</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="rpg resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A reflection on how the D&D community remembers its creators, sparked by Tim Cain's ToEE story and the ongoing discussions about Gary Gygax's legacy.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/CorpseKing_Gygax_Tweet_screenshot_896x229.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/CorpseKing_Gygax_Tweet_screenshot_896x229.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Exception Based Design in D&amp;amp;D - When Rules Enable Rule Lawyers</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/11/24/exception-based-dnd-design/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exception Based Design in D&amp;amp;D - When Rules Enable Rule Lawyers" /><published>2024-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/11/24/exception-based-dnd-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/11/24/exception-based-dnd-design/"><![CDATA[<p>With the slow rollout of the 2024 edition of Duneon &amp; Dragons 5e, there’s been considerable discussion about the game’s underlying design philosophy and how it shapes player behavior at the table. While every edition has had its share of rules lawyers, the current design trajectory might actually be encouraging more rules-focused play - and not always in ways that enhance the experience.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/unfrozen_barbarian_lawyer_480x856.webp" alt="A barbarian holding a legal document." height="856" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Unfrozen Barbarian Lawyer.</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<blockquote>

  <p><em>“If it pleases the court, your honor, I choose to rage, throw our rogue as an inprovised weapon with elemental damage, and have them return to my hand.”</em></p>

</blockquote>

<h2 id="the-exception-that-proves-the-rule">The Exception That Proves the Rule</h2>

<p>Since its inception, D&amp;D 5e operates on what I call an “exception-based” design philosophy. Rather than providing broad, flexible guidelines that empower creative play, the system builds character capabilities through stacks of specific exceptions to basic rules. Your fighter doesn’t just “fight well” - they have Action Surge, Second Wind, and various fighting styles that each modify base rules in particular ways. So they’re not just fighting better than everyone else, they’re operating under a complete different set of rules than anyone else. A unique set of exceptions just for them.</p>

<p>This might seem like a minor distinction, but it fundamentally shapes how players engage with the game:</p>

<ol>
  <li>It trains players to think in terms of “what special rules apply here?” rather than “what makes sense in this situation?”</li>
  <li>It creates an implicit promise that if something isn’t explicitly permitted by a rule exception, it might not be allowed</li>
  <li>It rewards system mastery through finding and combining favorable exceptions</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-complexity-stack-of-5e-2024">The Complexity Stack of 5e 2024</h2>

<p>The 5e 2024 revision appears to be doubling down on the exception-based design philosophy the edition started with in 2014. With more class features, more specific interactions, and more granular rules, we’re seeing what might be the most complex stack of exceptions yet in 5e’s history.</p>

<p>This isn’t inherently bad - some players genuinely enjoy engaging with complex rule systems. However, it creates some challenging dynamics and can sometimes put a game at odds with itself when situations arise where a rules exception runs counter to the DMs attempt to run a cohesive game.  I want to be clear here that, were this to happen, it’s not the fault of the DM or a player.  DMs are trying to create smooth fast fun, and players want to naturally use the abilities that make their character unique.  It’s just a natural part of the game. But they do sometimes conflict in the best of cases, and can sometimes incentivize arguments over rules interpretations in the worse cases.</p>

<h3 id="the-incentive-problem">The Incentive Problem</h3>

<p>When your character’s capabilities are defined primarily through rules exceptions, you’re incentivized to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Search for more exceptions</li>
  <li>Find ways to combine exceptions favorably</li>
  <li>Argue for beneficial interpretations of exception interactions</li>
</ul>

<p>This naturally leads to more rules discussions, more time spent debating edge cases, and potentially more friction at the table.</p>

<h3 id="the-new-rule-0-problem">The New Rule 0 Problem</h3>

<p>In almost every previous edition of D&amp;D, there was a Rule 0. This was the catch-all rule that allowed the DM to make decisions about how to handle situations that didn’t fit neatly into the rules as written. It was a narrative safety net that allowed the DM to weave a story that fit the theme of the adventure, even if it wasn’t spelled out in the rules.</p>

<p>In 5e 2024, it seems that Rule 0 has been replaced by a well intentioned and good sounding version “Rule 0 of D&amp;D is simple: Have fun. It’s fine if everyone agrees to change the rules as long as doing so means the game is more fun for everyone.” and this works fine for many groups. However, for games with rules lawyers problems, it fuels the fire of delays and arguments over rules interpretations. First, fun is subjective so it jumps right past the idea of a conhesive experience and the DMs role in managing that to a sort of palementary process. Second, it abandon’s the idea of making quick rulings to keep the game moving and directly sets the expectation of stopping everything for a debate whenever someone wants to. Third, it firmly enforces the idea that D&amp;D is a game or rules, not rulings, and that things run like a computer program, not like a story unless the entire groups stops and debates every single thing. Last, it flips traditional games on it’s head and establishes for the DM to be overruled by the players, which is a powerful and dangerous idea.</p>

<p>This is powerful because player input should be one of the most important things driving the game. However, it’s also dangerous because pushing this too far in a direction the DM isn’t interested is going to cause them to burn out and games to collapse. It can incentivize some very bad player behavior where they treat DMs like a low functioning gaming console they yell at whenever the game doesn’t go the way they want.</p>

<h2 id="finding-balance-at-your-table">Finding Balance at Your Table</h2>

<p>Despite these design considerations, it’s crucial to remember that system design influences but doesn’t determine player behavior. I’ve seen groups play highly tactical games using narrative systems, and groups play narrative-focused games using crunchy systems.</p>

<p>The key is understanding these design influences so we can actively choose how to engage with them:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Be Up Front</strong>: Everyone in the group should be up front about their play styles, what their deal breakers are, and what they expect from each other at the table. This is NOT just a DM responsibility, it’s the responsibility of everyone at the table to both communicate and listen to each other and to abide by any agreements made.</li>
  <li><strong>Embrace The DM’s Role</strong>: The DM should be supported by everyone at the table. This means they will everyone will do their flat best to be mindful that the DM is doing their best to run the game smoothly and that we’re all in this together.</li>
  <li><strong>Focus on Fun for Everyone</strong>: If a rules discussion is slowing down play, help everyone make a quick decision and move on. Anyone can offer a quick suggestin or alternative to keep things moving.The DM should be empowered to make these decisions and everyone should be mindful that the game is more important than any one ability or ruling.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="moving-forward">Moving Forward</h2>

<p>The 2024 edition of D&amp;D 5e is a good game, just as its predecessors have been. Understanding its design philosophy helps us engage with it more intentionally and adapt it to our preferred play styles. People can lose sight of this when commenting in this way and assuming I’m saying the game is bad. It’s not, but design does effect how we play and how we interact with each other at the table. It’s important to be aware of these things so we can make choices about how we play that enhance the experience for everyone.</p>

<p>Remember that every game system has its strengths and weaknesses. The goal isn’t to find a perfect system, but to understand how to work with the system you’re using to create the best experience for your group.</p>

<h3 id="tips-for-dms">Tips for DMs</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Set aside time between sessions to review any “rulings over rules” you made during the last session</li>
  <li>Be confident in making rulings that prioritize game flow over perfect rule accuracy, and don’t feel shy about asking players to help you keep the game moving</li>
  <li>Consider house rules that simplify exception chains that commonly cause confusion and write them down</li>
  <li>Unless something is going to wreck the game for everyone, let it slide and say yes. Remember you can revisit the decision in between sessions.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="tips-for-players">Tips for Players</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Focus on understanding your character’s capabilities thoroughly, not just on the letter of the ability but the spirit of the rules</li>
  <li>Consider the greater flow of the game, the style you’ve all agreed on, and what the DM is trying to do at the table</li>
  <li>Save complex rules discussions for between sessions and trust the DM to make the call when needed. However, don’t just forget about it until the next session. Actively discuss things between sessions and don’t just leave it until the next situation.</li>
  <li>Remember that D&amp;D is collaborative, not competitive.  Also keep in mind that once something is decided, accept it and move on.</li>
</ol>

<p>By understanding these design elements, we can better navigate their influence and focus on what truly matters: creating memorable stories and having fun with friends around the table.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="rpg resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore how D&D 5e's exception-based design affects table dynamics and player behavior, with tips for better game flow and group harmony]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/unfrozen_barbarian_lawyer_480x856.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/unfrozen_barbarian_lawyer_480x856.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">War and Warfare in TTRPGs - How to Bring Epic Conflicts to Life</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/11/22/warfare-in-ttrpgs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="War and Warfare in TTRPGs - How to Bring Epic Conflicts to Life" /><published>2024-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/11/22/warfare-in-ttrpgs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/11/22/warfare-in-ttrpgs/"><![CDATA[<p>War. It’s the drumbeat of countless fantasy epics, a crucible that forges heroes and shapes kingdoms. From the sweeping battles of <em>The Lord of the Rings</em> to Conan’s gritty skirmishes, war has always been central to the fantasy genre. Even modern fantasy leans heavily on the backdrop of conflict, often zooming in on the personal stories of individuals caught in its tide.</p>

<p>In TTRPGs like <em>Dungeons &amp; Dragons</em>, war seems like an obvious theme to explore. But translating epic wartime narratives into compelling, player-driven experiences can be tricky. After all, TTRPGs are fundamentally about personal choices and agency, while war is a massive, impersonal machine that often renders individual actions insignificant. Balancing these conflicting dynamics is no small task.</p>

<p>But fear not, brave DM. With a bit of forethought and creativity, you can craft war narratives that feel personal, impactful, and, most importantly, fun for your players. Let’s dive into how to make it work.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/pitch_battle_ai_art_480x856.webp" alt="A pitch battle with warriors charging back and forth. AI generated art." height="856" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<h2 id="understanding-war-in-ttrpg-contexts">Understanding War in TTRPG Contexts</h2>

<p>War has always loomed large in fantasy storytelling. It’s a canvas for epic struggles, where the stakes are high and the lines between good and evil often blur. But in TTRPGs, there’s a fundamental challenge: war is too big for a small group of adventurers to control. This conflict between the scope of war and the personal focus of roleplaying games can leave DMs scratching their heads.</p>

<p>It’s worth remembering that TTRPGs have their roots in wargaming. But early players quickly moved away from commanding armies to telling personal stories of adventurers with unique goals. While the DNA of war remains in TTRPGs, the focus has shifted. That’s our design challenge: to honor the grandeur of war while keeping the game personal.</p>

<h2 id="common-pitfalls-in-war-scenarios">Common Pitfalls in War Scenarios</h2>

<p>Many of the problems with integrating war stories into adventures stem from a mislaignment of how DMs align the grand scale of war with the personal focus of TTRPGs.  Recognizing these mistakes can help you avoid common pitfalls in adventures that include these stories.</p>

<h3 id="treating-pcs-like-armies">Treating PCs Like Armies</h3>

<p>One mistake DMs often make is treating the party as a tactical unit capable of single-handedly winning battles. Sure, a group of adventurers can decimate a squad or even a company of soldiers, but if your players can rout entire armies, why does your world even have armies? Why not just let champions duke it out gladiator-style to decide wars? It’s a question that can undermine your setting’s internal logic.</p>

<p>Moreover, overpowering the players can lead to a lack of tension. If every challenge is easily overcome, the stakes diminish, and the epic feel of the war narrative can be lost. It’s essential to maintain a balance where players feel impactful yet not omnipotent.</p>

<h3 id="overemphasizing-grand-strategy">Overemphasizing Grand Strategy</h3>

<p>Another common pitfall is focusing too much on the big picture. Grand strategy might be thrilling in historical simulations, but most players didn’t roll up a bard to debate supply lines. If the game veers too far into abstract logistics, it risks alienating the players.</p>

<p>While some players might enjoy a strategic layer, it should enhance, not overshadow, the core roleplaying experience. Remember, the heart of TTRPGs lies in character interaction and storytelling, not in simulating military command.</p>

<h3 id="forgetting-player-agency">Forgetting Player Agency</h3>

<p>War narratives can also strip players of agency. Orders from above and the chaos of battle can make it feel like their choices don’t matter. Without a sense of personal impact, the game loses what makes TTRPGs unique.</p>

<p>Players thrive when they can make meaningful decisions that affect the outcome of events. Even in the midst of a vast war, ensure there are moments where their choices have clear and immediate consequences.</p>

<h3 id="neglecting-emotional-stakes">Neglecting Emotional Stakes</h3>

<p>War isn’t just about armies clashing; it’s about people. Ignoring the personal and emotional aspects of war can lead to a flat narrative. Without connections to NPCs or investment in the conflict’s outcome, players might not feel compelled by the war’s progression. This can be a difficult balance, DMs neither way to overplay or underplay emotional stakes.  DM should also never tell players how their characters feel about the war. That’s their player’s job and a well designed adventure will allow different characters to have different reactions to the same events.</p>

<h2 id="designing-war-narratives-for-ttrpgs">Designing War Narratives for TTRPGs</h2>

<p>To avoid these pitfalls, focus on scenarios where the players can influence the tide of war without overshadowing it entirely. Here are several types of scenarios that work beautifully:</p>

<h3 id="the-fulcrum">The Fulcrum</h3>

<p>In these scenarios, the battle hinges on a specific event the players can directly affect. Imagine a key bridge that must be captured, a city gate that needs to be opened, or an enemy war engine that must be destroyed. Success or failure has consequences that ripple across the battlefield.</p>

<p>When running a Fulcrum scenario, make sure the stakes are clear and the mission is urgent. Time pressures are particularly effective here. In one campaign I ran, the players infiltrated a necropolis beneath a besieged city to destroy a magic artifact empowering the enemy. They had to work against the clock, knowing that if they failed, the main assault would be a slaughter. The timer added tension, and their success felt earned.</p>

<h3 id="the-stop-loss">The Stop Loss</h3>

<p>Sometimes, it’s not about winning; it’s about surviving. Stop Loss scenarios focus on retreating, evacuating allies, or delaying the enemy. These stories emphasize the cost of war and force players to make tough choices about who or what to save.</p>

<p>One of my favorite examples comes from a <em>Star Wars</em> campaign. The players evacuated Yavin base moments before the Death Star’s attack, only to face an Imperial facility blocking the civilian fleet’s escape route. They had to infiltrate and sabotage the base, knowing every moment they delayed cost lives. It was tense, emotional, and quintessentially <em>Star Wars</em>.</p>

<h3 id="the-hidden-blade">The Hidden Blade</h3>

<p>In covert operations, the players act as a scalpel rather than a hammer. They might assassinate an enemy general, steal intelligence, or sabotage supplies. These scenarios let the party operate behind enemy lines, where their actions can shift the tide of war in subtle but meaningful ways.</p>

<p>The key here is balance. Make sure the players’ contributions feel significant without making them overshadow the broader war effort. A successful mission might turn the odds slightly in their side’s favor, but it shouldn’t feel like they single-handedly won the day.</p>

<h3 id="the-home-front">The Home Front</h3>

<p>War affects more than just soldiers on the battlefield. The Home Front scenario focuses on the impacts of war on society and the player’s personal lives. Players might defend their hometown from enemy incursion, deal with espionage, or manage wartime resources. This approach personalizes the conflict and can make the stakes feel incredibly real.</p>

<p>In a campaign I ran, the players returned to their village to find it occupied by enemy forces. They had to rally the townsfolk, plan guerrilla attacks, and navigate the moral complexities of rebellion. The emotional investment was high because they were fighting for their own homes and loved ones.</p>

<h3 id="the-diplomatic-mission">The Diplomatic Mission</h3>

<p>Not all wars are fought with swords and spells. Sometimes, the most crucial battles occur in the courts and councils. Assigning players to a Diplomatic Mission to prevent a war, forge alliances, or negotiate peace can lead to rich roleplaying opportunities. It challenges players to use their wits and charisma rather than their combat prowess.</p>

<h2 id="enhancing-engagement-in-war-scenarios">Enhancing Engagement in War Scenarios</h2>

<p>Once you’ve chosen a scenario type, you can deepen player engagement with these techniques:</p>

<h3 id="time-pressure">Time Pressure</h3>

<p>A ticking clock adds urgency and forces tough decisions. Whether it’s a literal countdown to an enemy’s attack or a metaphorical race against dwindling resources, time constraints heighten tension. Use time pressure to keep the pace brisk and the stakes high.</p>

<h3 id="npc-connections">NPC Connections</h3>

<p>Allies and civilians can ground the stakes in personal relationships, making losses feel real. Introduce NPCs that players care about—comrades, mentors, family members. Their fates can serve as emotional anchors, motivating players to act and adding weight to their decisions.</p>

<h3 id="variable-outcomes">Variable Outcomes</h3>

<p>Avoid binary success/failure. Instead, design scenarios with degrees of success that influence the larger narrative. Perhaps the players achieve their primary goal but at a significant cost, or they succeed partially, leading to unforeseen consequences. This complexity reflects the unpredictable nature of war.</p>

<h3 id="leveraging-player-backstories">Leveraging Player Backstories</h3>

<p>Integrate the players’ personal histories into the war narrative. If a character’s hometown is under threat or their family is involved in the conflict, their investment in the outcome increases dramatically. Personal stakes can drive engagement and foster deeper roleplaying.</p>

<h3 id="moral-dilemmas">Moral Dilemmas</h3>

<p>War is rife with ethical gray areas. Present the players with choices that test their morals: sacrifice a few to save many, uphold their code of honor or achieve victory at any cost, follow orders or do what they believe is right. These dilemmas add depth and can lead to memorable roleplaying moments.</p>

<h3 id="dynamic-battlefields">Dynamic Battlefields</h3>

<p>Make the environment an active participant in the scenario. Battles can take place in hazardous terrains like burning forests, crumbling castles, or magical storms. Environmental hazards force players to adapt their strategies and keep encounters fresh and exciting.</p>

<h3 id="incorporate-mass-combat-mechanics">Incorporate Mass Combat Mechanics</h3>

<p>If you want to represent larger battles without bogging down gameplay, consider using streamlined mass combat rules. Systems like “Unearthed Arcana: When Armies Clash” for D&amp;D or other third-party supplements can help simulate large-scale conflicts while keeping the focus on the players’ actions. They key is still to keep the focus on the players’ actions without turning them into military units. The fun you can add to a game by using mass combat rules are the uncertinty of the outcome and the chaos of battle. If you base outcomes on actions and rolls, even the DM can be surprised. I find this fairly fun, but it’s not for everyone. Again this can be a fun addition to a campaign, but don’t lose sight that the game is about the players’ actions and choices.</p>

<h3 id="utilize-propaganda-and-information-warfare">Utilize Propaganda and Information Warfare</h3>

<p>Introduce elements of misinformation, propaganda, and espionage. Players might need to expose enemy lies, protect their own secrets, or influence public opinion. This adds a layer of psychological warfare that can be engaging and thought-provoking.</p>

<h2 id="fitting-war-into-the-fantasy-framework">Fitting War into the Fantasy Framework</h2>

<p>Fantasy worlds offer unique opportunities for wartime storytelling. Magic, legendary weapons, and fantastical creatures can all add flavor. But balance is key. If the players wield too much power, it undermines the setting. At the same time, war provides a chance to explore morally complex choices. Who are the heroes and villains, really? What does victory cost?</p>

<h3 id="magical-warfare">Magical Warfare</h3>

<p>Consider how magic impacts warfare. Siege engines might be replaced with spellcasters, teleportation circles could be used for troop movements, and magical communication can alter strategies. Integrate these elements thoughtfully to enhance the setting without unbalancing the game.</p>

<h3 id="legendary-creatures-and-constructs">Legendary Creatures and Constructs</h3>

<p>Incorporate dragons, golems, or other mythical beasts as instruments of war. Perhaps the enemy has tamed a dragon, or your side has constructed warforged soldiers. These can serve as significant challenges or allies and add epic scale to encounters.</p>

<h3 id="artifacts-and-ancient-weapons">Artifacts and Ancient Weapons</h3>

<p>Introduce powerful artifacts that both sides seek to control. The quest to find or protect these items can drive the narrative and give players a clear objective that impacts the war’s outcome.</p>

<h3 id="cultural-and-racial-dynamics">Cultural and Racial Dynamics</h3>

<p>Use the diverse cultures and races in your world to enrich the war narrative. Different factions might have unique fighting styles, philosophies, and motivations. Exploring these differences can add depth and complexity to the conflict.</p>

<h3 id="the-aftermath">The Aftermath</h3>

<p>Don’t forget to address the consequences of war. How does the conflict change the political landscape, the environment, and the people? Exploring the aftermath can lead to new adventures and character development opportunities.</p>

<h2 id="embracing-the-moral-complexity-of-war">Embracing the Moral Complexity of War</h2>

<p>War is rarely black and white and it’s much more complex than anyone appreciates.  Here I want to pause and encourage everyone to be thoughtful about how they encorporate war into their campaigns. I am not going to say there is one right or wrong way to do it, but as a real world topic, people can have very strong feelings about how it’s portrayed. DMs would do well to consider the players at the table and how they might feel about the topic, particularly if they have personal experiences with war. As a veteran, this if often a problem for me as I don’t appreciate when people simplify the complexities of war. That’s a personal thing, but I think it’s important to be thoughtful about how war is portrayed in our games becuase other people will have other feelings and experiences.</p>

<p>As strongly as I can say this, I recommend you do not use personal politics as a driver for your war scenarios. It’s a good way to offend people and likely an insult to whatever cause you think you’re championing. By all means, make commentary in youir game, but I recommend you keep it at a high level and not focus on the minutiae of whatever real world events are currently in vogue to have a political position on.</p>

<p>That sayd, embrace its moral complexities of war at a high levelcan lead to a richer narrative:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Questionable Orders</strong>: Present players with commands that conflict with their morals. Do they follow orders or their conscience?</li>
  <li><strong>Sympathetic Enemies</strong>: Humanize the opposing side. Perhaps the enemy soldiers are conscripts or fighting for a cause they believe is just.</li>
  <li><strong>The Cost of Victory</strong>: Highlight the sacrifices required to win. Victory might come at the expense of innocent lives or personal losses.</li>
  <li><strong>Rebuilding and Healing</strong>: After the battle, focus on the efforts to rebuild and the lingering traumas. This can lead to profound character moments and future plot hooks.</li>
</ul>

<p>The trick to working with moral complexity in game design is to stick to asking questions and not making statements. This is not only good practice, but it puts the emphasis where it should be, the characters points of view, not the DM’s.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>War in TTRPGs is a challenge worth taking on. By designing scenarios that focus on player agency, balancing power dynamics, and embracing the unique possibilities of fantasy settings, you can craft wartime stories that resonate with your group. The next time your campaign calls for epic conflict, don’t shy away. Lean in and let the battle unfold.</p>

<p>Remember, the best war stories aren’t just about the battles won or lost but about the people who fought them and the choices they made. By keeping the focus on your players and their characters, you can ensure that your wartime campaign is both epic and deeply personal.</p>

<p>War is calling, adventurers. The question is: how will your table answer?</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="rpg resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Dive into how to effectively run war scenarios in TTRPGs like D&D, balancing epic battles with personal player agency.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/pitch_battle_ai_art_800x418.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/pitch_battle_ai_art_800x418.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The DnD 2024 Launch and the Future of Hasbro</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/24/hasbro-q3-2024/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The DnD 2024 Launch and the Future of Hasbro" /><published>2024-10-24T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-24T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/24/hasbro-q3-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/24/hasbro-q3-2024/"><![CDATA[<p>The financial health of Hasbro frequently sparks intense discussion among Dungeons &amp; Dragons fans. While speculation often trends toward the alarmist, the underlying concern is understandable. Fans have invested heavily in this hobby - not just financially, but with their time, creativity, and emotional energy. They want to understand the stability of the company behind their beloved game, whether the focus is on product quality over brand exploitation, and how corporate decisions might impact the future of their hobby. <a href="https://investor.hasbro.com/news-releases/news-release-details/hasbro-reports-third-quarter-2024-financial-results" target="_blank">Hasbro’s Q3 earnings report</a> offers us a chance to move beyond speculation and examine actual data.</p>

<p>This analysis covers Hasbro’s financial position from July through September 2024, as reported to their investors. The timing is particularly significant as it encompasses the launch of the D&amp;D 2024 Player’s Handbook and should include pre-order data.</p>

<p>For transparency: while this analysis was generated using AI, it’s worth noting that I work professionally in AI-driven analytics. This isn’t simply a matter of prompting and pasting - it’s a careful examination of the data through an informed lens.</p>

<p>Looking at the broader picture, Hasbro appears stable but faces challenges. While carrying considerable debt, their aggressive inventory reduction has resulted in impressive margins (the percentage of revenue they retain as profit). Despite these high margins, debt reduction will likely remain a long-term process. However, their healthy cash reserves and continued dividend payments suggest stability and maintain investor confidence.</p>

<p><strong>Key observations:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Baldur’s Gate 3’s impact on last year’s numbers is stark. With that revenue stream now diminished, there’s clear pressure to find new ways to monetize the D&amp;D franchise.</li>
  <li>The D&amp;D 2024 launch appears to have underperformed. If the Player’s Handbook hasn’t significantly moved the needle, it’s unlikely the DMG and MM will fare better. This suggests the 5e brand may be in decline.</li>
  <li>Their strategic focus on digital gaming is evident, though the success of their VTT initiative remains uncertain. If they’re considering AI as a major strategy (though this isn’t clear from the report), that’s potentially problematic. In a world where AI can effectively run games, the value of traditional gaming brands and systems could be significantly diminished.</li>
</ul>

<p>Now, let’s examine the detailed analysis of the Q3 report.  Note, <em>I’ve added some commentary in italics to the report below.</em></p>

<h2 id="hasbro-q3-2024-report-summary">Hasbro Q3 2024 Report Summary</h2>

<p><strong>Major Findings:</strong></p>
<ol>
  <li>Overall revenue declined 15% year-over-year (9% excluding eOne divestiture) - <em>This is fairly dramatic to me, the eOne divestiture is a big deal but that they’re 9% down even after excluding it is significant.</em></li>
  <li>Operating profit was $302 million with a margin of 23.6% - <em>Comparing this to the WotC margins below, it’s clear that MtG is floating the company right now.</em></li>
  <li>Company is maintaining its full-year EBITDA guidance of $975M-$1.025B - <em>This is a big range, but it’s a good sign that they’re not revising their expectations for the year.</em></li>
  <li>Company continues to pay quarterly dividends ($0.70 per share) - <em>This is a good sign, it shows that they’re still committed to rewarding shareholders even as they work to transition the business.</em></li>
  <li>Inventory levels are down 39% versus prior year - <em>This is a good sign, it shows that they’re managing their inventory more effectively and can maintain their margins</em></li>
  <li>Digital gaming business saw success with Monopoly Go! ($30M revenue in Q3) - <em>This should be seen as good but I believe this is the origin of a strategic mistake.  I believe they saw the development of the VTT to be the same as Monoboloy Go and I think they’ve bit off more than they can chew with the VTT.</em></li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Financial Position Overall:</strong>
The company is in a period of strategic transition but maintaining stability. While revenues are down, they’ve improved their operational efficiency and maintain strong margins. Their cash position is healthy ($696.1M) and they’ve added short-term investments ($489.3M). The reduction in inventory levels (39% down) suggests better operational management. The maintenance of dividend payments indicates confidence in their cash flow position. However, they do carry significant debt ($3.96B total between current and long-term), which they’ve listed debt reduction as a priority. The company appears financially stable but in need of revenue growth to improve their position.</p>

<p><strong>Wizards of the Coast Indicators:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Revenue decreased 5% in Q3 2024 vs Q3 2023 - <em>Appears to be from lost BG3 revenue. I was hoping to see a softer decline with the release of the 2024 PHB.</em></li>
  <li>Operating margin of 44.9% (down 3.1 points) - <em>Down yes, but 45% is insanely good.</em></li>
  <li>MAGIC: THE GATHERING revenue increased 3%</li>
  <li>Digital gaming affected by tough comparison to Baldur’s Gate 3 launch in Q3 2023</li>
  <li>Year-to-date performance is strong: - <em>All of this incidates the changes at the end of 2023 had a strong positive impact on the business. Hate them if you like but business is unforgiving and they did what they needed to do IMO.</em>
    <ul>
      <li>Revenue up 7% for first nine months</li>
      <li>Operating profit increased 30%</li>
      <li>Operating margin of 47.0%</li>
      <li>Tabletop revenue increased 3%</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Dungeons &amp; Dragons Product Line:</strong>
The report doesn’t break out specific D&amp;D performance metrics, but there are some relevant indicators:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Listed as one of their “Franchise Brands” alongside MAGIC: THE GATHERING - <em>I take this as an affirmation of support for DnD but I don’t know how to take the term “Franchise Brands” as Core Brand is really the gold standard.</em></li>
  <li>Digital gaming revenue decline was specifically attributed to comparing against Baldur’s Gate 3’s launch in Q3 2023, suggesting this was a significant revenue driver</li>
  <li>D&amp;D is included in “Hasbro Total Gaming” category which saw: - <em>The take away here is they had a significant decline at the end of last year that is turing around.</em>
    <ul>
      <li>6% decline in Q3 2024 vs Q3 2023</li>
      <li>3% growth year-to-date</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Strategy indicators:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Company appears to be focusing on digital transformation</li>
  <li>Pursuing licensing opportunities</li>
  <li>Focus on product innovation</li>
  <li>D&amp;D appears to be integrated into their broader digital gaming strategy</li>
  <li>No specific new D&amp;D initiatives were announced in this report</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="misc" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hasbro's Q3 2024 report offers a detailed look at their financial performance and strategic direction and teases the future of the DnD brand.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/dnd_record_keeping_1200x600.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/dnd_record_keeping_1200x600.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Movement in Theater of the Mind for DnD 5e</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/20/theater-of-the-mind-movement-in-5e/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Movement in Theater of the Mind for DnD 5e" /><published>2024-10-20T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-20T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/20/theater-of-the-mind-movement-in-5e</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/20/theater-of-the-mind-movement-in-5e/"><![CDATA[<p>As a Dungeon Master, I’ve always been drawn to the flexibility and imagination-sparking nature of Theater of the Mind (TotM) gameplay. However, at least in grid based systems like D&amp;D 5e, it can be a challenge to account for various elements of the game designed for tactical combat. Additionally, it can be tempting to simply ignore movement when using TotM and miss out on the exciting and dynamic nature of swashbuckling adventures. Today, I want to share a system I’ve developed that keeps TotM combat dynamic and tactical while avoiding the need to track every 5-foot square.</p>

<p>While this system is primarily designed with D&amp;D 5e in mind, its core principles can be easily adapted to any TTRPG. In fact, I think it would work particularly well in games like ShadowDark, which already emphasizes streamlined gameplay. The fundamental concept - declaring your intention and then rolling for the outcome - is universally applicable across various game systems. This flexibility allows you to bring more dynamic movement to your TotM sessions, regardless of the specific ruleset you’re using.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/pitch_battle_ai_art_480x856.webp" alt="A pitch battle with warriors charging back and forth. AI generated art." height="856" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<h2 id="the-core-principle-intention-over-precision">The Core Principle: Intention Over Precision</h2>

<p>The heart of this system is focusing on what characters are trying to achieve with their movement, rather than precisely where they are at any given moment. Here’s how it works:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Describe that the character is trying to achieve and select the appropriate maneuver.</li>
  <li>If two opponents want the same thing (like engaging in melee), let it happen without a roll.</li>
  <li>If opponents want different things, (like staying in cover or avoiding engagement) resolve it with an opposed skill check.</li>
</ol>

<p>This approach keeps the action flowing and puts the emphasis on the narrative rather than the mechanics.</p>

<h2 id="simplified-movement-ranges">Simplified Movement Ranges</h2>

<p>Instead of tracking exact distances, we use two primary ranges:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Move Range</strong>: The character can reach the target in a single move action.</li>
  <li><strong>Extended Range</strong>: The character is beyond a single move away  If nessisary define how many moves it would take to reach a target.</li>
</ul>

<p>This simplification allows for quick decision-making and keeps the focus on the action.</p>

<h2 id="key-maneuvers">Key Maneuvers</h2>

<p>To add tactical depth to combat, I’ve introduced several maneuvers that players can attempt:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Engage</strong>: Move into melee range with an opponent or multiple opponents (up to their proficiency bonus).</li>
  <li><strong>Close</strong>: Reduce the distance between you and a target so you may attempt an Engage or other maneuver next turn.  (Useful in chase scenes.)</li>
  <li><strong>Avoid</strong>: Stay out of an opponent’s melee reach.</li>
  <li><strong>Flee</strong>: Use a full action to move significantly away from combat. Because they are using a full action, the character gains advantage on any checks to avoid engagement.</li>
  <li><strong>Line Up A Shot</strong>: Attempt to negate the cover bonus of an opponent for a clear ranged attack.</li>
  <li><strong>Use Cover</strong>: Utilize an obstacle for protection.</li>
  <li><strong>Intercept</strong>: Use a reaction to move and potentially make an attack of opportunity.</li>
</ol>

<p>These maneuvers give players clear options for positioning without needing a grid.</p>

<h2 id="resolving-maneuvers">Resolving Maneuvers</h2>

<p>When a player attempts a maneuver, here’s how we resolve it:</p>

<ol>
  <li>The player describes their intended movement.</li>
  <li>If an opponent wants the same thing, let it happen.  If they want different things, the player rolls the chosen skill check and the opponent rolls their skill check.</li>
  <li>Resolve the maneuver, ties to to the ‘defender’, the winning roll is the one that gets to do what they want.</li>
</ol>

<p>The most common skills used are Athletics, Acrobatics, and Deception, but I encourage players to think creatively about how other skills might apply.</p>

<p>Some examples:</p>

<p>The player characters are Ahmed the Fighter, Lora the Rogue, and Kaelin the Cleric.  They are engaged in combat with a group of 3 goblin archers and 2 goblin warriors.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Ahmed wants to Engage with one of the Goblin Archers.  All the archers want to Avoid engagement.  Ahmed rolls Athletics vs the all the archer’s Acrobatics.  If Ahmed beats any of the Gobin Archers roll, he can engage them. Any Goblin Archer that wins successfully avoids engagement.</li>
  <li>Lora wants to Use Cover against the ranged attacks while shooting at a Goblin Fighter.  It just happens.  On the turn for a Goblin Archer, they try to Line up a Shot on Lora and roll Deception vs her Acrobatics.  If the Archer beats her roll, they get to shoot without Lora’s cover bonus.</li>
  <li>A Goblin Warrior tries to engage Ahmed but Kaelin uses her reaction to Intercept them.  Kaelin rolls Athletics vs the Goblin Warrior’s Athletics.  If Kaelin beats the Goblin Warrior’s roll, she can make an opporunity attack. (Kalin indends to shove the Goblin Warrior and attempt to knock them prone.)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="special-considerations">Special Considerations</h2>

<p>To add even more depth and account for various D&amp;D rules, I’ve incorporated a few special considerations:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Flanking</strong>: If you’re using flanking rules, any character attacking a target already engaged by another character gains advantage on their attack roll.</li>
  <li><strong>Within 5 feet</strong>: Some character or monster ability uses the ‘within 5 feet’ qualfier. In this case any character that is engaged with someone is within 5 feet of them.  Moving to within 5 feet of an ally is automatic in most cases.</li>
  <li><strong>Multiple Opponents</strong>: A character can attempt to use multi-attack on different opponents within range.</li>
  <li><strong>Dodge Action</strong>: Grants advantage on all maneuver rolls and reactions to avoid engagement.</li>
  <li><strong>Sentinel Feat</strong>: Allows the Intercept maneuver as a free action, once per round.</li>
  <li><strong>Reach Weapons</strong>: Grant advantage on maneuvers to engage or intercept.</li>
  <li><strong>Limited/Enhanced Movement</strong>: Some characters have limited movement or enhanced movement.  In most cases this should grant disadvantage/advantage on applicable maneuvers. This could include but not be limited to bonus action movement, being limited to half movmenet due to gettiing up from prone,haste, or other effects that grant extra movement.</li>
  <li><strong>Opportunity Attack</strong>: If a character is engaged or with an opponent and attempts to move away, the opponent can make an opportunity attack as normal.</li>
  <li><strong>Force Movement</strong>: This is not typically handled in these rules and proceed as normal.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="keeping-it-fun-and-flexible">Keeping It Fun and Flexible</h2>

<p>Remember, the goal of this system is to enhance the fun and tactical elements of combat without getting bogged down in rules. These rules can likely be twisted and work best when everyone enages them in good faith.  If a situation is unclear or some particular use of a maneuver does not make sense, the DM should make a ruling and keep things moving.  As a DM, I always prioritize the following:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Narrative Flow</strong>: Use the system to enhance the story, not hinder it.</li>
  <li><strong>Player Agency</strong>: Give players meaningful choices about their positioning and actions.</li>
  <li><strong>Quick Resolution</strong>: Keep the action moving by making quick judgments rather than consulting tables.</li>
  <li><strong>Fairness</strong>: Be consistent in your rulings, but be willing to adapt if something isn’t working.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping Up</h2>

<p>This system has brought new life to my TotM combat sessions, allowing for dynamic and engaging fights without the need for miniatures or a battle map. It’s flexible enough to work with various game systems and can be easily tweaked to fit your group’s style.</p>

<p>Remember, the key is to keep things moving and fun. Don’t be afraid to make quick decisions and adjust on the fly. Your players will appreciate the added depth to combat, and you’ll enjoy the freedom of not having to track every little movement.</p>

<p>Give this system a try in your next TotM session and let me know how it goes. Happy gaming, everyone!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="rpg" /><category term="resources" /><category term="DnD" /><category term="Theater of the Mind" /><category term="Combat" /><category term="House Rules" /><category term="Movement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover a dynamic system for handling movement in Theater of the Mind gameplay, designed primarily for D&D 5e but adaptable to any TTRPG. This approach emphasizes narrative flow and player agency while maintaining tactical depth.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/pitch_battle_ai_art_800x418.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/pitch_battle_ai_art_800x418.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/13/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-10-13T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-13T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/13/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/13/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>This week in the world of tabletop roleplaying games (TTRPGs) news you may have missed! We have stories about new resources that assist Game Masters (GMs) to significant announcements that bridge digital and tabletop realms, and other stories about how the TTRPG ecosystem continues to grow. Here’s a closer look at some of the most captivating stories from October 6 to October 13, 2024, that you may not have seen in your feeds.</p>

<h3 id="free-rpg-resources---flextale-infinite-adventures-volume-1-western-realm-of-aquilae">Free RPG Resources - FlexTale Infinite Adventures Volume 1: Western Realm of Aquilae</h3>
<p><em>October 8, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>; #TTRPG</p>

<p>Announced a free resource titled “FlexTale Infinite Adventures Volume 1: Western Realm of Aquilae” that provides an array of Points of Interest (POIs) tailored for easy integration into various fantasy TTRPGs. This comprehensive resource is designed to assist GMs in creating dynamic sessions without extensive preparation, making it an ideal asset for both new and experienced GMs.</p>

<p>Readers keen on enhancing their campaigns can access this invaluable resource at <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/10/free-rpg-resources-flextale-infinite.html" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>.</p>

<h3 id="worlds-beyond-number-makes-big-changes-after-its-next-arc">‘Worlds Beyond Number’ Makes Big Changes After Its Next Arc</h3>
<p><em>October 8, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net" target="_blank">Bell of Lost Souls</a>; #TTRPG</p>

<p>This popular podcast is transitioning to a space-themed campaign after wrapping up its current arc, marking a significant narrative shift. This evolution showcases the adaptability of TTRPG narratives to maintain freshness and engagement, underscoring the fluidity inherent in the genre.</p>

<p>For insights into the podcast’s new direction, check out <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/10/worlds-beyond-number-makes-big-changes-after-its-next-arc.html" target="_blank">Bell of Lost Souls</a>.</p>

<h3 id="dd-character-builder-level-up-release">D&amp;D Character Builder: Level Up Release</h3>
<p><em>October 11, 2024</em>, <a href="https://blog.roll20.net" target="_blank">Roll20 Blog</a>; #DungeonsAndDragons</p>

<p>Roll20 introduced an upgraded D&amp;D Character Builder featuring an automated level-up and a refined user interface, enhancing the character management experience for players. This upgrade aims to streamline gameplay and ease the learning curve for newcomers, reflecting the community’s feedback for more inclusive tools as they engage with D&amp;D 5E.</p>

<p>Learn more about this significant enhancement at <a href="https://blog.roll20.net/posts/dd-character-builder-level-up-release/" target="_blank">Roll20 Blog</a>.</p>

<h3 id="new-premium-edition-for-candela-obscura-from-beadle--grimms-and-critical-roles-darrington-press">New Premium Edition for Candela Obscura from Beadle &amp; Grimm’s and Critical Role’s Darrington Press</h3>
<p><em>October 11, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.rascal.news" target="_blank">Rascal News</a>; #TTRPG</p>

<p>Beadle &amp; Grimm announced “Horrors of the Fairelands,” a limited release for their game, Candela Obscura, enriched with immersive elements and beautifully crafted handouts to enhance the GM experience. This product highlights the growing trend for premium quality accessories in TTRPGs, aiming to elevate gameplay immensely.</p>

<p>Pre-orders are now available; take a look at this exciting offering at <a href="https://www.rascal.news/new-premium-edition-for-candela-obscura-from-beadle-grimms-and-critical-roles-darrington-press-2/" target="_blank">Rascal News</a>.</p>

<h3 id="baldurs-gate-3-characters-become-official-dungeons--dragons-minis">BALDUR’S GATE 3 Characters Become Official DUNGEONS &amp; DRAGONS Minis</h3>
<p><em>October 11, 2024</em>, <a href="https://nerdist.com" target="_blank">Nerdist</a>; #DungeonsAndDragons</p>

<p>WizKids is debuts a new line of official D&amp;D miniatures featuring beloved characters from Baldur’s Gate 3. This exciting initiative caters to fans and enhances the convergence of digital and tabletop experiences, exemplifying how video games profoundly influence the tabletop RPG community.</p>

<p>For detailed views on the release, visit <a href="https://nerdist.com/article/baldurs-gate-3-official-dungeons-dragons-minis/" target="_blank">Nerdist</a>.</p>

<p>In summary, there’s a lot happening in the TTRPG world, showcasing valuable resources and developments that continue to enrich our beloved hobby. Stay tuned for more updates as this dynamic community keeps evolving and growing!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><category term="TTRPG" /><category term="RPG Resources" /><category term="Podcasts" /><category term="DungeonsAndDragons" /><category term="CandelaObscura" /><category term="BaldursGate3" /><category term="EverQuest" /><category term="MMORPG" /><category term="GameMasters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Catch up on the latest TTRPG news from October 6 to October 12, 2024, including new resources, product announcements, and key updates in the world of tabletop gaming.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/06/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-10-06T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-06T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/06/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/06/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>As we dive into the latest happenings in the world of tabletop roleplaying games (TTRPGs), excitement fills the air! From classic titles making a digital debut to significant changes in design leadership, this month has been packed with news that every TTRPG enthusiast should know about. Let’s explore the key stories that are shaping our beloved hobby.</p>

<h4 id="a-shift-in-design-richard-august-leaves-steamforged-games">A Shift in Design: Richard August Leaves Steamforged Games</h4>
<p><em>October 4, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168865/steamforged-games-lead-ttrpg-designer-richard-august-leaves-the-company/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>; #TTRPG #SteamforgedGames</p>

<p>In a surprising move, Richard August, the lead designer at Steamforged Games, has announced his departure from the company. Known for his contributions to popular titles such as the “Dark Souls” RPG and “RuneScape Kingdoms,” August’s exit raises questions about the future direction of the studio and its upcoming projects.</p>

<p>August’s departure may signal a shift in design philosophy and project management at Steamforged, which has experienced a meteoric rise in the TTRPG landscape. His influence has been pivotal in establishing the company’s reputation for high-quality adaptations of video game franchises into tabletop formats. The TTRPG community should follow this development closely, as it could impact the future of beloved games. <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168865/steamforged-games-lead-ttrpg-designer-richard-august-leaves-the-company/" target="_blank">Dive deeper into the implications of this change here</a>.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="magic-awaits-sneak-peek-at-the-upcoming-55e-dungeon-masters-guide">Magic Awaits: Sneak Peek at the Upcoming 5.5E Dungeon Master’s Guide</h4>
<p><em>October 1, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/10/dont-worry-the-new-5-5e-dungeon-masters-guide-is-still-full-of-magic-items-preview-details.html" target="_blank">Bell of Lost Souls</a>; #D&amp;D #DungeonMastersGuide #5.5E</p>

<p>A preview of the forthcoming 5.5E Dungeon Master’s Guide has excited the community, revealing that it will retain a wealth of magical items that fans have come to love. This assurance that classic elements will remain intact is crucial for long-time players who enjoy the depth and variety magic items bring to their campaigns.</p>

<p>The enduring popularity of D&amp;D relies heavily on its ability to evolve while respecting its roots, making this update an essential read for DMs looking to enrich their game experience. <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/10/dont-worry-the-new-5-5e-dungeon-masters-guide-is-still-full-of-magic-items-preview-details.html" target="_blank">Explore what’s in store for the next iteration of the guide here</a>.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="empowering-players-the-bastion-system-in-dd-55e">Empowering Players: The Bastion System in D&amp;D 5.5E</h4>
<p><em>October 2, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/10/dd-5-5e-the-bastion-system-previews-players-make-your-mark-on-the-world.html" target="_blank">Bell of Lost Souls</a>; #D&amp;D #5.5E #BastionSystem</p>

<p>The introduction of the Bastion System in D&amp;D 5.5E aims to give players greater agency in world-building and storytelling. This system encourages collaboration between players and DMs, fostering a dynamic narrative environment where player choices significantly impact the game world.</p>

<p>This development is particularly significant as it aligns with a broader trend in tabletop RPGs toward increased player involvement in narrative creation. By empowering players to shape their stories, D&amp;D continues to innovate while deepening engagement within its community. <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/10/dd-5-5e-the-bastion-system-previews-players-make-your-mark-on-the-world.html" target="_blank">Read more about how this new system could transform gameplay here</a>.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="unleash-the-horror-new-bundle-of-holding-featuring-dread-thingonomicon">Unleash the Horror: New Bundle of Holding Featuring Dread Thingonomicon</h4>
<p><em>October 2, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/10/bundle-of-holding-dread-thingonomicon.html" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>; #TTRPG #BundleOfHolding</p>

<p>The latest Bundle of Holding features the Dread Thingonomicon, a collection of horror-themed TTRPG content that promises to thrill fans of the genre. This bundle not only provides new material but also highlights the growing niche of horror in tabletop gaming, appealing to those who enjoy darker narratives.</p>

<p>Bundles like this are important as they often introduce players to lesser-known titles and provide affordable access to a wealth of content. They also foster community through shared experiences in themed gameplay. If you’re a fan of horror RPGs, don’t miss out on this exciting opportunity to explore new adventures <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/10/bundle-of-holding-dread-thingonomicon.html" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<hr />

<p>In conclusion, the TTRPG landscape continues to evolve with exciting developments, from classic games finding new life on digital platforms to significant shifts in company leadership and product offerings. Staying informed about these changes not only enriches our gaming experience but also connects us as a community navigating the dynamic world of tabletop roleplaying.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><category term="DnD" /><category term="Steamforged" /><category term="WOTC" /><category term="DungeonMastersGuide" /><category term="BundleOfHolding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Description of the article]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Greyhawk - The Original D&amp;amp;D Setting Returns</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/02/a-return-to-greyhawk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Greyhawk - The Original D&amp;amp;D Setting Returns" /><published>2024-10-02T08:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-02T08:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/02/a-return-to-greyhawk</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/10/02/a-return-to-greyhawk/"><![CDATA[<p>When you’re leafing through the pages of the upcoming <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xWNT9N3cE2U&amp;t=1s" target="_blank">Dungeon Master’s Guide</a>, set to hit shelves this November as part of D&amp;D 2024. The familiar scent of fresh ink and new possibilities filling the air, you might notice something different. The default setting isn’t the Forgotten Realms in the latest edition. Instead, you’re reading about a world called Greyhawk. For some of you, this name might spark a nostalgic gleam in your eye. For others, it might be a curious first encounter. So what is with the new default setting for DnD 2024? Lets take a journey to the <a href="https://greyhawkonline.com/" target="_blank">World of Greyhawk</a>, D&amp;D’s original campaign setting, and find out what we’re in for.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/greyhawksupplament_480x754.webp" alt="Cover image of the original Greyhawk Supplement." height="754" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">The original Greyhawk Supplement</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h3 id="greyhawk-the-og-of-dd-worlds">Greyhawk: The OG of D&amp;D Worlds</h3>

<p>First things first - what exactly is Greyhawk? Well, imagine if Gary Gygax, one of the founding fathers of D&amp;D, decided to create an entire world. Oh wait, he did! That’s Greyhawk in a nutshell. This high fantasy setting centers on the continent of Oerth (yes, that’s Earth with an ‘O’, because why not?), with most of the action taking place in a region called the Flanaess.</p>

<p>Now, I know what some of you are thinking. “But I’ve been playing in the Forgotten Realms for years! Why the change?” Well, my friends, sometimes to move forward, we need to take a step back. And in this case, we’re stepping back to the very roots of D&amp;D.</p>

<h3 id="a-brief-history-of-greyhawk">A Brief History of Greyhawk</h3>

<p>Before we dive deeper into what makes Greyhawk tick, let’s take a quick jaunt through its history. Trust me, it’ll help you appreciate just how momentous this return really is.</p>

<p>Greyhawk’s journey began in the early 1970s as Gary Gygax’s personal campaign setting. But it didn’t say his for long - it quickly became a collaborative effort, with many of D&amp;D’s original creators leaving their mark on this burgeoning world.</p>

<p>Take, for instance, David Arneson’s Castle Blackmoor. This mega-dungeon, one of the earliest and most iconic in D&amp;D history, found its home in the north of Greyhawk. Its influence? Monumental. From the sprawling levels of Undermountain in the Forgotten Realms to the demon-infested halls of video games like Diablo, Blackmoor’s DNA is everywhere.</p>

<p>Many of D&amp;D’s most iconic NPCs - names like Bigby and Robilar - started as characters in Gary’s original play group. It was a world built not just by designers, but by players, their adventures weaving the very fabric of the setting. This to me always solidified the idea that collaborative world-building was fundamental to the D&amp;D experience. Shared setting development was part of the bones of the game from the start.</p>

<p>It wasn’t until 1980 that fans like myself got our first real taste of this rich world with the release of the <a href="https://archive.org/details/tsr09025worldofgreyhawkfolio" target="_blank">World of Greyhawk folio</a>. For a pre-teen me, it was like discovering that all those disconnected adventures actually existed in a fully-realized world. I gave me that feeling of a deep, living world that captivated me in the fictional settings I loved so much.</p>

<p>The 1983 “Gold Box” set expanded the world even further. Throughout the 80s and early 90s, Greyhawk thrived, with countless adventures, sourcebooks, and articles fleshing out its rich tapestry of cultures and conflicts.</p>

<p>The late 90s and early 2000s saw Greyhawk take a bit of a backseat, but it never truly went away. The “Living Greyhawk” organized play campaign kept the flame alive, allowing players to continue shaping the world’s ongoing narrative. If I recall correctly, this was the origin of what would eventually become the DnD Adventurers League we know today.</p>

<p>And now, after years of teasing references in various 5e products, Greyhawk is poised to reclaim its place at the heart of D&amp;D with the upcoming 2024 edition. It’s a homecoming decades in the making, and for many of us old-timers, it feels like reuniting with an old friend - a friend who’s been shaped by countless hands and imaginations over the years.</p>

<div class="clearfix text-center">
<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 img-fluid">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/greyhawkmap_1024x585.webp" alt="Overland map of Oerth." height="585" width="1024" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Updated map of Oerth from the 2024 DMG.</figcaption>
    
</figure>
</div>

<h3 id="a-tapestry-of-cultures-and-conflict">A Tapestry of Cultures and Conflict</h3>

<p>The core region of Greyhawk was the region of Flanaess. Originally steeped in a strong Eurasian flavor (a product of its time), Greyhawk has since evolved, expanding its cultural horizons beyond its initial borders. Yet, it still carries the DNA of the literary giants that inspired the very foundations of D&amp;D. You can feel the gritty urban landscapes of Fritz Leiber’s Lankhmar, the moral ambiguity of Michael Moorcock’s Eternal Champion saga, the primal energy of Robert E. Howard’s Hyborian Age, and the dying earth vibes of Jack Vance’s work.</p>

<p>At the heart of human civilization are the Oeridians, who once ran the show with their Great Kingdom of Aerdy. Imagine walking the haunted streets of Rauxes, the former capital, now a chilling reminder of how far the mighty can fall. Or picture yourself in the courts of Furyondy, where noble knights plan their next move against the evil forces of Iuz to the north.</p>

<p>But the Oeridians aren’t the only players in this game. To the west, you’ve got the Baklunish cultures in states like Ekbir and Zeif. Think minarets piercing the sky, bazaars bustling with strange wares, and magical traditions that would make your average Oeridian wizard’s pointy hat spin.</p>

<p>And let’s not forget the Suel. These folks have a bit of a checkered past, what with the Scarlet Brotherhood lurking in the shadows. Imagine a secret society of working in the shadows to infiltrate ever aspect of society, with plans spanning the continent. Paranoid yet? You should be.</p>

<p>Then there are the Flan, the original humans of these lands. Their great civilizations might have faded, but their legacy lives on in places like Tenh and among the nomadic Rovers of the Barrens. These are the folks who can tell you what the Flanaess was like before it was cool.</p>

<h3 id="welcome-to-the-city-of-adventure">Welcome to the City of Adventure</h3>

<p>At the heart of all this stands the Free City of Greyhawk itself. A melting pot of cultures where an Oeridian merchant might be haggling with a Baklunish mage over a Flan artifact, all while a Suel thief picks both their pockets. It’s a city of adventure, intrigue, and more shady deals than you can shake a wand of fireballs at. At the time, it was obvious to me that the City of Greyhawk was the city of Lankhmar from Fritz Leiber’s Fafhrd and the Gray Mouser stories, so I was immediatly hooked.</p>

<p>But humans aren’t the only ones stirring the pot. The Ulek States show us that dwarves, elves, and gnomes have long established cutures of their own. They’re right in the thick of it, forging alliances and shaping the political landscape alongside their human neighbors. This carried much of the tension between cultures that setup a dangerous world in the original days of DnD, which I think ahs softened over time. It will be interesting to see what tension DMs setup in their own versions of Greyhawk.</p>

<h3 id="why-greyhawk-why-now">Why Greyhawk? Why Now?</h3>

<p>So, why is Wizards of the Coast bringing Greyhawk back into the spotlight? Well, for one, it’s a return to roots for the 50th anniversary of D&amp;D. Greyhawk is where many of D&amp;D’s iconic elements were born. Ever cast Mordenkainen’s Magnificent Mansion or Bigby’s Hand? You can thank Greyhawk for those. Ever delved into the Tomb of Horrors or faced the horrors of the Temple of Elemental Evil? Greyhawk, baby.</p>

<p>But it’s more than just nostalgia. Greyhawk offers a grittier, more grounded take on high fantasy than the Forgotten Realms. It’s a world where political intrigue is as deadly as any dragon’s breath, where the line between hero and villain is often blurred, and where every victory feels hard-earned. For me, it’s the template for one of my favorite 2e settings, Birthright. At least, this is the original vision of Greyhawk.  I think it’s fair to say that WotC has a more portable vision in mind, a Greyhawk that can adapt to any group, any world, and any story. I have to confess, if this is the case, it makes me a little sad.  A setting should have a point of view, a flavor that makes it unique.  I adore the Forgotten Realms, and I love the homebrew that has sprung from it, but Greyhawk deserves more than a simple “generic fantasy” approach.</p>

<p>WotC has been teasing us with Greyhawk references throughout the 5e era. But now, with part of the recent Vecna: Eve of Ruin module set on Oerth, it seems they’re finally ready to pull back the curtain.  I sincerly hope they do it justice when the setting returns to the 2024 Dungeon Master’s Guide in November.</p>

<h3 id="what-this-means-for-you">What This Means for You</h3>

<p>Whether you’re a grizzled veteran eager to return to familiar lands or a wide-eyed newcomer ready to explore this classic setting for the first time, Greyhawk’s return as the default D&amp;D setting is big news. But what does it really mean for your gaming table?</p>

<p>First off, if you’re hoping to recreate the gritty feel of original Greyhawk, you might find yourself wrestling with the D&amp;D 2024 system. Let’s face it, D&amp;D hasn’t been truly gritty for a long time, and the 2024 edition seems to be dialing up the power level yet another notch. This presents an interesting challenge for DMs: how do you maintain Greyhawk’s classic tone when your players are wielding more power than ever?</p>

<p>On the flip side, the new Bastion system introduced in the 2024 DMG could be a perfect fit for Greyhawk’s political landscape. Players might find themselves quickly rising to become lords of their own realms. Having a rich, detailed setting like Greyhawk to ground these newfound fiefdoms could be incredibly satisfying - provided your players buy into the world’s deep background and complex politics.</p>

<p>It’ll be fascinating to see WotC’s modern take on this classic setting. How will they balance nostalgia with the need to appeal to new players? How dedicated will they be to fully supporting Greyhawk beyond its initial reintroduction? And perhaps most intriguingly, how will the new Greyhawk interact with the evolving Open Gaming License (OGL)? These are questions that could shape not just how we play in Greyhawk, but how we engage with D&amp;D as a whole in the coming years.</p>

<p>For DMs, this means a wealth of opportunities. You’ll have access to a rich, detailed world with decades of lore to draw from. At the same time, you’ll face the challenge of adapting this classic setting to modern game mechanics and player expectations. It’s a chance to blend the best of old-school D&amp;D with the innovations of recent years.</p>

<p>For players, Greyhawk offers a world ripe for exploration and conquest. Whether you’re delving into the depths of Castle Greyhawk, navigating the political intrigues of the Free City, or carving out your own baronies with the Bastion system, there’s no shortage of adventures waiting for you.</p>

<p>Ultimately, the return of Greyhawk is more than just a nostalgic throwback. It’s an opportunity to bridge the gap between D&amp;D’s roots and its future, to explore how a classic setting can evolve to meet the needs of modern players while still retaining its unique charm. Whether this experiment succeeds will depend not just on WotC’s execution, but on how we as a community embrace and shape this new incarnation of a beloved world.</p>

<p>So, are you ready to make your mark on the Flanaess? To walk the streets of the Free City, to face the horrors lurking in Castle Greyhawk, to shape the fate of empires? Greyhawk is calling, adventurers. And this time, it’s calling from the very core of D&amp;D itself. The question is: how will you answer?</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="rpg resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore Greyhawk's return as D&D's default setting in 2024. Discover its rich history, unique features, and what it means for players and DMs alike.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/greyhawkmap_1024x585.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/greyhawkmap_1024x585.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/29/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-09-29T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-29T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/29/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/29/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>As we dive into the latest developments in the tabletop RPG landscape, there’s a wealth of exciting news that every TTRPG fan should be aware of. From significant releases in the Dungeons &amp; Dragons universe to the resurgence of classic games, this week has proven to be pivotal for both new and seasoned players. Here’s a detailed look at the most relevant stories from September 22, 2024, to September 29, 2024.</p>

<h3 id="drunkards-druggies--delinquents-titmouse-the-studio-behind-vox-machina-launches-a-new-ttrpg">Drunkards, Druggies, &amp; Delinquents: Titmouse, the Studio Behind Vox Machina, Launches a New TTRPG</h3>
<p><em>September 24, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168668/drunkards-druggies-delinquents-titmouse-the-the-legend-of-vox-machina-studio-launch-a-ttrpg/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>; #TTRPG #LegendofVoxMachina #NewRelease</p>

<p>Titmouse, the animation studio renowned for “The Legend of Vox Machina,” has launched a new tabletop RPG titled “Drunkards, Druggies, &amp; Delinquents.” This game promises to deliver a unique blend of humor and adventure, reflecting the studio’s creative ethos.</p>

<p>This introduction showcases the crossover potential between animation and tabletop gaming, appealing to fans of both mediums. For those interested in exploring this new game, more information can be found in the article at <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168668/drunkards-druggies-delinquents-titmouse-the-the-legend-of-vox-machina-studio-launch-a-ttrpg/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>.</p>

<h3 id="wotc-inflates-sales-numbers-for-players-handbook">WOTC Inflates Sales Numbers for Player’s Handbook</h3>
<p><em>September 23, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tabletopgamingnews.com/wotc-inflates-sales-numbers-for-players-handbook-real-figures-might-be-shockingly-low/" target="_blank">Tabletop Gaming News</a>; #D&amp;D #Sales #PlayersHandbook</p>

<p>Recent reports suggest that Wizards of the Coast may have exaggerated sales figures for the new Player’s Handbook, with real physical sales potentially falling short of expectations. This news raises concerns about the marketing strategies employed by WOTC and the overall health of tabletop RPG sales in an increasingly digital marketplace.</p>

<p>Understanding these dynamics is crucial for fans and retailers alike, as it could impact future releases and the types of products that get prioritized. For a deeper dive into the implications of these sales figures, check out the full article on <a href="https://www.tabletopgamingnews.com/wotc-inflates-sales-numbers-for-players-handbook-real-figures-might-be-shockingly-low/" target="_blank">Tabletop Gaming News</a>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>This week has seen a vibrant mix of new releases, classic revivals, and significant industry shifts that will shape the future of tabletop RPGs. Whether you’re a long-time player or new to the scene, there’s plenty to explore and engage with in the world of TTRPGs. Stay tuned for more updates as the community continues to evolve!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><category term="DnD" /><category term="Kickstarter" /><category term="WOTC" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Catch up on the latest TTRPG news, including new releases, classic revivals, and industry developments from September 22-29, 2024.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/22/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-09-22T21:31:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-22T21:31:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/22/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/22/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back, TTRPG enthusiasts! This week has been buzzing with exciting developments in the world of tabletop roleplaying games. Whether you’re a Dungeon Master looking for new material or a player eager to dive into fresh adventures, we’ve got you covered. Let’s dive into the latest trends and news from the TTRPG community.</p>

<p><strong>Lets dive into the latest News you may have missed last week!</strong></p>

<h4 id="backerkit---gaslight-victorian-fantasy-revised-and-expanded-for-5e">Backerkit - Gaslight Victorian Fantasy Revised and Expanded for 5E</h4>
<p><strong>September 15, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>, <em>Tags: 5E, Victorian Fantasy, Backerkit</em></p>

<p>The much-loved Gaslight Victorian Fantasy setting for 5th Edition is getting a significant upgrade. The revised and expanded edition promises new mechanics and adventures, breathing fresh life into this unique genre. Victorian fantasy fans and 5E players alike will find something to love in this new release.</p>

<p><strong>Why Read More:</strong> Dive into the details of what new content and mechanics are being introduced and get ready to back this project on Backerkit. <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/backerkit-gaslight-victorian-fantasy.html" target="_blank">Read more here</a>.</p>

<h4 id="44-year-old-ttrpg-rolemaster-finally-launches-on-roll20">44-year-old TTRPG “Rolemaster” Finally Launches on Roll20</h4>
<p><strong>September 16, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>; <em>Tags: Rolemaster, Roll20, Classic TTRPG</em></p>

<p>Rolemaster, the iconic TTRPG known for its detailed mechanics and depth, has finally made its debut on Roll20. This launch allows a new generation of players to experience the intricate gameplay of Rolemaster online, making it more accessible than ever before.</p>

<p><strong>Why Read More:</strong> Learn about the features and enhancements that come with the Roll20 adaptation and see how you can integrate this classic into your online gaming sessions. <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168554/44-year-old-ttrpg-rolemaster-finally-launches-on-roll20/" target="_blank">Read more here</a>.</p>

<h4 id="the-other-osr-sanction">The Other OSR: Sanction</h4>
<p><strong>September 16, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://rlyehreviews.blogspot.com/" target="_blank">R’lyeh Reviews</a>; <em>Tags: OSR, Sanction, TTRPG</em></p>

<p>This article explores the latest offerings in the OSR (Old School Revival) scene, focusing on a new game titled “Sanction,” which is designed to engage players with classic gameplay mechanics while introducing fresh narratives and challenges.</p>

<p><strong>Why You Should Read More:</strong> For fans of the OSR movement, “Sanction” offers a blend of nostalgia and innovation. <a href="https://rlyehreviews.blogspot.com/2024/09/the-other-osr-sanction.html" target="_blank">Read the full article</a>.</p>

<h4 id="2024-dungeons--dragons-players-handbook-now-available-fresh-upgrades-and-enhancements-await">2024 Dungeons &amp; Dragons Player’s Handbook Now Available: Fresh Upgrades and Enhancements Await!</h4>
<p><strong>September 17, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.geeksaresexy.net/" target="_blank">Geeks Are Sexy</a>; <em>Tags: D&amp;D, Player’s Handbook, New Edition</em></p>

<p>The new edition of the Dungeons &amp; Dragons Player’s Handbook is now available, packed with significant upgrades, enhancements, and new content aimed at enriching the gameplay experience. This release is set to redefine the core of D&amp;D gameplay with fresh rules and expanded lore.</p>

<p><strong>Why Read More:</strong> Discover the new features and content that will enhance your D&amp;D sessions and find out where you can get your hands on the latest edition. <a href="https://www.geeksaresexy.net/2024/09/17/2024-dungeons-dragons-players-handbook-now-available-fresh-upgrades-and-enhancements-await/" target="_blank">Read more here</a>.</p>

<h4 id="dd-2024-players-handbook-debuts-with-mixed-success">D&amp;D 2024 Players Handbook Debuts with Mixed Success</h4>
<p><strong>September 18, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>; #DungeonsAndDragons #PlayersHandbook #CommunityFeedback</p>

<p>Following the release of the 2024 Player’s Handbook, mixed reactions have surfaced within the community. While many appreciate the updates, others express concerns about certain changes that may alter the balance of gameplay. This analysis highlights the ongoing dialogue between developers and players, underscoring the importance of community input in the evolution of such a beloved game.</p>

<p>For a closer examination of the feedback and the implications for the D&amp;D community, read the full analysis <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168589/dd-2024-players-handbook-debuts-with-mixed-success/" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h4 id="state-of-play-kobold-press-issues-the-no-ai-pledge">State of Play: Kobold Press Issues the No AI Pledge</h4>
<p><strong>September 19, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://koboldpress.com/" target="_blank">Kobold Press</a>; <em>Tags: Kobold Press, No AI, TTRPG</em></p>

<p>Kobold Press has officially pledged to not utilize AI in their game design processes, emphasizing their commitment to human creativity and the importance of original content in the tabletop gaming community.</p>

<p><strong>Why You Should Read More:</strong> This pledge highlights a significant stance in the industry, reinforcing the value of human creativity in game design. <a href="https://koboldpress.com/state-of-play-kobold-press-issues-the-no-ai-pledge/" target="_blank">Read the full article</a>.</p>

<p>See my artifcle on my thoughts on <a href="/2024/09/20/ethical-ai-in-ttrpgs/">Ethical use of AI in TTRPGs</a>.</p>

<h4 id="trench-crusade-kickstarter-release-date--campaign-details">Trench Crusade Kickstarter Release Date &amp; Campaign Details</h4>
<p><strong>September 19, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.destructoid.com" target="_blank">Destructoid</a>; #Kickstarter #TrenchCrusade #TTRPG</p>

<p>The upcoming Kickstarter for Trench Crusade has been announced, building excitement for a new TTRPG that promises to blend tactical gameplay with rich storytelling. This campaign will offer unique rewards and stretch goals, aiming to capture the interest of both veteran gamers and newcomers alike. The project reflects a growing trend of crowdfunding in the RPG space, allowing creators to directly engage with their audience.</p>

<p>For details on the campaign specifics and how to participate, check out the full article <a href="https://www.destructoid.com/trench-crusade-kickstarter-release-date-campaign-details/?utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=trench-crusade-kickstarter-release-date-campaign-details" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>This week’s TTRPG news highlights the dynamic and evolving nature of our beloved hobby. From new editions and settings to significant industry pledges, there’s plenty to be excited about. Stay tuned to Optionalrule.com for more updates, and don’t forget to check out the detailed articles linked above to stay ahead of the game. Happy adventuring!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><category term="5E" /><category term="Victorian Fantasy" /><category term="Backerkit" /><category term="Rolemaster" /><category term="Roll20" /><category term="D&amp;D" /><category term="Player&apos;s Handbook" /><category term="Kobold Press" /><category term="AI" /><category term="Game Design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly TTRPG news roundup: Victorian Fantasy, Rolemaster, D&D, Kobold Press, AI, Game Design]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>