<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-30T02:32:11+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Optional Rule</title><subtitle>Optional Rule is a blog for DMs and Players alike of DnD 5e and any tabletop  roleplaying game. It offers rules, insight, analysis, and resources that help people run games and enhance their play.</subtitle><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/29/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-09-29T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-29T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/29/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/29/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>As we dive into the latest developments in the tabletop RPG landscape, there’s a wealth of exciting news that every TTRPG fan should be aware of. From significant releases in the Dungeons &amp; Dragons universe to the resurgence of classic games, this week has proven to be pivotal for both new and seasoned players. Here’s a detailed look at the most relevant stories from September 22, 2024, to September 29, 2024.</p>

<h3 id="drunkards-druggies--delinquents-titmouse-the-studio-behind-vox-machina-launches-a-new-ttrpg">Drunkards, Druggies, &amp; Delinquents: Titmouse, the Studio Behind Vox Machina, Launches a New TTRPG</h3>
<p><em>September 24, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168668/drunkards-druggies-delinquents-titmouse-the-the-legend-of-vox-machina-studio-launch-a-ttrpg/">Geek Native</a>; #TTRPG #LegendofVoxMachina #NewRelease</p>

<p>Titmouse, the animation studio renowned for “The Legend of Vox Machina,” has launched a new tabletop RPG titled “Drunkards, Druggies, &amp; Delinquents.” This game promises to deliver a unique blend of humor and adventure, reflecting the studio’s creative ethos.</p>

<p>This introduction showcases the crossover potential between animation and tabletop gaming, appealing to fans of both mediums. For those interested in exploring this new game, more information can be found in the article at <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168668/drunkards-druggies-delinquents-titmouse-the-the-legend-of-vox-machina-studio-launch-a-ttrpg/">Geek Native</a>.</p>

<h3 id="wotc-inflates-sales-numbers-for-players-handbook">WOTC Inflates Sales Numbers for Player’s Handbook</h3>
<p><em>September 23, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tabletopgamingnews.com/wotc-inflates-sales-numbers-for-players-handbook-real-figures-might-be-shockingly-low/">Tabletop Gaming News</a>; #D&amp;D #Sales #PlayersHandbook</p>

<p>Recent reports suggest that Wizards of the Coast may have exaggerated sales figures for the new Player’s Handbook, with real physical sales potentially falling short of expectations. This news raises concerns about the marketing strategies employed by WOTC and the overall health of tabletop RPG sales in an increasingly digital marketplace.</p>

<p>Understanding these dynamics is crucial for fans and retailers alike, as it could impact future releases and the types of products that get prioritized. For a deeper dive into the implications of these sales figures, check out the full article on <a href="https://www.tabletopgamingnews.com/wotc-inflates-sales-numbers-for-players-handbook-real-figures-might-be-shockingly-low/">Tabletop Gaming News</a>.</p>

<h3 id="kickstarter-launches-for-warlock-knight-dfrpg">Kickstarter Launches for Warlock Knight (DFRPG)</h3>
<p><em>September 25, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/kickstarter-warlock-knight-dfrpg.html">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>; #TTRPG #Kickstarter #DFRPG</p>

<p>A new Kickstarter campaign has launched for “Warlock Knight,” a game designed for the DFRPG system. This project promises thrilling adventures and unique gameplay mechanics, appealing to fans of the fantasy genre.</p>

<p>Kickstarter has become a vital platform for indie developers to introduce innovative RPGs, and this campaign is no exception. Interested readers can find more about this project and how to support it on <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/kickstarter-warlock-knight-dfrpg.html">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>This week has seen a vibrant mix of new releases, classic revivals, and significant industry shifts that will shape the future of tabletop RPGs. Whether you’re a long-time player or new to the scene, there’s plenty to explore and engage with in the world of TTRPGs. Stay tuned for more updates as the community continues to evolve!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><category term="DnD" /><category term="Kickstarter" /><category term="WOTC" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Catch up on the latest TTRPG news, including new releases, classic revivals, and industry developments from September 22-29, 2024.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/OR_Screenshot-870x570.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/OR_Screenshot-870x570.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/22/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-09-22T21:31:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-22T21:31:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/22/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/22/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back, TTRPG enthusiasts! This week has been buzzing with exciting developments in the world of tabletop roleplaying games. Whether you’re a Dungeon Master looking for new material or a player eager to dive into fresh adventures, we’ve got you covered. Let’s dive into the latest trends and news from the TTRPG community.</p>

<p><strong>Lets dive into the latest News you may have missed last week!</strong></p>

<h4 id="backerkit---gaslight-victorian-fantasy-revised-and-expanded-for-5e">Backerkit - Gaslight Victorian Fantasy Revised and Expanded for 5E</h4>
<p><strong>September 15, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>, <em>Tags: 5E, Victorian Fantasy, Backerkit</em></p>

<p>The much-loved Gaslight Victorian Fantasy setting for 5th Edition is getting a significant upgrade. The revised and expanded edition promises new mechanics and adventures, breathing fresh life into this unique genre. Victorian fantasy fans and 5E players alike will find something to love in this new release.</p>

<p><strong>Why Read More:</strong> Dive into the details of what new content and mechanics are being introduced and get ready to back this project on Backerkit. <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/backerkit-gaslight-victorian-fantasy.html" target="_blank">Read more here</a>.</p>

<h4 id="44-year-old-ttrpg-rolemaster-finally-launches-on-roll20">44-year-old TTRPG “Rolemaster” Finally Launches on Roll20</h4>
<p><strong>September 16, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>; <em>Tags: Rolemaster, Roll20, Classic TTRPG</em></p>

<p>Rolemaster, the iconic TTRPG known for its detailed mechanics and depth, has finally made its debut on Roll20. This launch allows a new generation of players to experience the intricate gameplay of Rolemaster online, making it more accessible than ever before.</p>

<p><strong>Why Read More:</strong> Learn about the features and enhancements that come with the Roll20 adaptation and see how you can integrate this classic into your online gaming sessions. <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168554/44-year-old-ttrpg-rolemaster-finally-launches-on-roll20/" target="_blank">Read more here</a>.</p>

<h4 id="the-other-osr-sanction">The Other OSR: Sanction</h4>
<p><strong>September 16, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://rlyehreviews.blogspot.com/" target="_blank">R’lyeh Reviews</a>; <em>Tags: OSR, Sanction, TTRPG</em></p>

<p>This article explores the latest offerings in the OSR (Old School Revival) scene, focusing on a new game titled “Sanction,” which is designed to engage players with classic gameplay mechanics while introducing fresh narratives and challenges.</p>

<p><strong>Why You Should Read More:</strong> For fans of the OSR movement, “Sanction” offers a blend of nostalgia and innovation. <a href="https://rlyehreviews.blogspot.com/2024/09/the-other-osr-sanction.html" target="_blank">Read the full article</a>.</p>

<h4 id="2024-dungeons--dragons-players-handbook-now-available-fresh-upgrades-and-enhancements-await">2024 Dungeons &amp; Dragons Player’s Handbook Now Available: Fresh Upgrades and Enhancements Await!</h4>
<p><strong>September 17, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.geeksaresexy.net/" target="_blank">Geeks Are Sexy</a>; <em>Tags: D&amp;D, Player’s Handbook, New Edition</em></p>

<p>The new edition of the Dungeons &amp; Dragons Player’s Handbook is now available, packed with significant upgrades, enhancements, and new content aimed at enriching the gameplay experience. This release is set to redefine the core of D&amp;D gameplay with fresh rules and expanded lore.</p>

<p><strong>Why Read More:</strong> Discover the new features and content that will enhance your D&amp;D sessions and find out where you can get your hands on the latest edition. <a href="https://www.geeksaresexy.net/2024/09/17/2024-dungeons-dragons-players-handbook-now-available-fresh-upgrades-and-enhancements-await/" target="_blank">Read more here</a>.</p>

<h4 id="dd-2024-players-handbook-debuts-with-mixed-success">D&amp;D 2024 Players Handbook Debuts with Mixed Success</h4>
<p><strong>September 18, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>; #DungeonsAndDragons #PlayersHandbook #CommunityFeedback</p>

<p>Following the release of the 2024 Player’s Handbook, mixed reactions have surfaced within the community. While many appreciate the updates, others express concerns about certain changes that may alter the balance of gameplay. This analysis highlights the ongoing dialogue between developers and players, underscoring the importance of community input in the evolution of such a beloved game.</p>

<p>For a closer examination of the feedback and the implications for the D&amp;D community, read the full analysis <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168589/dd-2024-players-handbook-debuts-with-mixed-success/" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h4 id="state-of-play-kobold-press-issues-the-no-ai-pledge">State of Play: Kobold Press Issues the No AI Pledge</h4>
<p><strong>September 19, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://koboldpress.com/" target="_blank">Kobold Press</a>; <em>Tags: Kobold Press, No AI, TTRPG</em></p>

<p>Kobold Press has officially pledged to not utilize AI in their game design processes, emphasizing their commitment to human creativity and the importance of original content in the tabletop gaming community.</p>

<p><strong>Why You Should Read More:</strong> This pledge highlights a significant stance in the industry, reinforcing the value of human creativity in game design. <a href="https://koboldpress.com/state-of-play-kobold-press-issues-the-no-ai-pledge/" target="_blank">Read the full article</a>.</p>

<p>See my artifcle on my thoughts on <a href="/2024/09/20/ethical-ai-in-ttrpgs/">Ethical use of AI in TTRPGs</a>.</p>

<h4 id="trench-crusade-kickstarter-release-date--campaign-details">Trench Crusade Kickstarter Release Date &amp; Campaign Details</h4>
<p><strong>September 19, 2024</strong>, <a href="https://www.destructoid.com" target="_blank">Destructoid</a>; #Kickstarter #TrenchCrusade #TTRPG</p>

<p>The upcoming Kickstarter for Trench Crusade has been announced, building excitement for a new TTRPG that promises to blend tactical gameplay with rich storytelling. This campaign will offer unique rewards and stretch goals, aiming to capture the interest of both veteran gamers and newcomers alike. The project reflects a growing trend of crowdfunding in the RPG space, allowing creators to directly engage with their audience.</p>

<p>For details on the campaign specifics and how to participate, check out the full article <a href="https://www.destructoid.com/trench-crusade-kickstarter-release-date-campaign-details/?utm_source=rss&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=trench-crusade-kickstarter-release-date-campaign-details" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>This week’s TTRPG news highlights the dynamic and evolving nature of our beloved hobby. From new editions and settings to significant industry pledges, there’s plenty to be excited about. Stay tuned to Optionalrule.com for more updates, and don’t forget to check out the detailed articles linked above to stay ahead of the game. Happy adventuring!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><category term="5E" /><category term="Victorian Fantasy" /><category term="Backerkit" /><category term="Rolemaster" /><category term="Roll20" /><category term="D&amp;D" /><category term="Player&apos;s Handbook" /><category term="Kobold Press" /><category term="AI" /><category term="Game Design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly TTRPG news roundup: Victorian Fantasy, Rolemaster, D&D, Kobold Press, AI, Game Design]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Embracing AI in TTRPGs - Enhancing, Not Replacing, Creativity</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/20/ethical-ai-in-ttrpgs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embracing AI in TTRPGs - Enhancing, Not Replacing, Creativity" /><published>2024-09-20T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-20T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/20/ethical-ai-in-ttrpgs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/20/ethical-ai-in-ttrpgs/"><![CDATA[<p>The TTRPG community has been abuzz with discussions about AI, and understandably so. The mere mention of artificial intelligence in our beloved hobby often sparks heated debates and anxiety. There’s a palpable fear that AI might replace the human creativity that forms the very essence of tabletop roleplaying games. In these discussions, we’ve sometimes been too quick to judge, too harsh in our criticisms, and perhaps a bit too reactionary. Without doubt, there’s Fear, Uncertainty, and Doubt (FUD) surrounding AI, but there are also great possibilities when used thoughtfully. As with many topics in our community, we need to approach the AI conversation with more open-mindedness and less cruelty towards those with differing views. After all, the spirit of TTRPGs is one of collaboration and imagination – qualities we should bring to these important discussions as well.</p>

<p>Recently, Hasbro’s CEO mentioned exploring ways to <a href="https://www.enworld.org/threads/hasbro-ceo-chris-cocks-talks-ai-usage-in-d-d-updated.706638/" target="_blank">incorporate AI into D&amp;D</a>, which predictably caused a significant backlash. Many assumed this meant replacing creative teams with AI-generated content. However, it’s worth noting that this wasn’t explicitly stated, and there are numerous potential applications of AI that could enhance, rather than replace, the TTRPG experience.</p>

<p>While I share the community’s concerns about AI-generated books, adventures, or artwork, I believe we’re overlooking some genuinely beneficial uses of AI that could improve our gaming experiences. Let’s explore some of these possibilities:</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/ttrpg_players_and_robot_480x600.webp" alt="People playing dungeons and dragons with a robot looking on." height="600" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<h3 id="1-a-dndbeyond-search-that-actually-works">1. A DnDBeyond Search that Actually Works!</h3>

<p>Imagine a D&amp;D Beyond with a truly functional search feature powered by AI. A Perplexity-like AI could revolutionize how we access and utilize the vast amount of information in the digital toolset. This would save DMs and players countless hours of frustration trying to locate specific rules, spells, or creature stats.  Extend this to your library of PDFs, GM Notes, and Campaign Logs and now you’ve got a truly useful personal assistant. <em>“Show me examples of area effect zones in grid based combat from the DMG.”</em></p>

<h3 id="2-lore-summarization">2. Lore Summarization</h3>

<p>One of the most exciting potential applications of AI in TTRPGs is summarizing published content. An AI chatbot that could provide concise summaries of lore from various settings like the Forgotten Realms, Dark Sun, or Eberron would be invaluable. This tool could help DMs quickly refresh their memory or give players a brief overview of a setting without spoiling key plot points. <em>“Summarize the history of the city of Waterdeep from the Dungeon Master’s Guide.”</em>, <em>“Give me a list of the named wizards from the city of Thay.”</em></p>

<h3 id="3-advanced-random-tables">3. Advanced Random Tables</h3>

<p>We already use random tables for various aspects of our games. AI could take this concept further, generating more complex and contextually appropriate random elements on the fly. This could include NPC personalities, location details, or even plot hooks that align with the current game state. Better yet, if you have access to your campaign notes you can do things like ask it to related a random encounter to a specific NPC or location. <em>“Generate a random encounter along the Triboar trail that involves bandits and smugglers and add a complication to the encounter based on the notes for the mountain gnome enclave.”</em></p>

<h3 id="4-game-management-assistant">4. Game Management Assistant</h3>

<p>AI could be a game-changer for the administrative side of running a TTRPG campaign. Imagine an AI assistant that helps with:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Scheduling games and managing player availability</li>
  <li>Keeping track of session logs and important plot points</li>
  <li>Organizing campaign notes and player character information</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="5-vtt-scene-preparation-and-management">5. VTT Scene Preparation and Management</h3>

<p>Virtual Tabletop (VTT) platforms have opened up new possibilities for online play, but they’ve also increased the workload for DMs. An AI assistant could help streamline VTT preparation and management by:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Suggesting appropriate maps and tokens based on the planned encounter</li>
  <li>Automating lighting and fog of war settings</li>
  <li>Handling initiative tracking and turn management</li>
</ul>

<p>This kind of AI integration could significantly reduce the time DMs spend wrestling with VTT logistics, allowing them to focus more on storytelling and player engagement.</p>

<h3 id="6-managing-characters-and-game-content">6. Managing Characters and Game Content</h3>

<p>At their core, TTRPGs are essentially analog databases. We constantly reference character abilities, skills, equipment, and various other game elements. This often involves tedious record-keeping and calculations that, while necessary, aren’t particularly enjoyable. AI opens up exciting new possibilities to streamline these processes and make our game data more accessible and useful.</p>

<p><strong>Character Sheet Management</strong></p>

<p>Imagine an AI assistant that can instantly provide you with any information from your character sheet, summarize it, transform it into a different format. Need to know your current load and carrying capacity? Just ask. Want a quick summary of all flammable items in your inventory? Need a version of your character with abilities after you’ve been polymorphed into a purple octopus? The AI can compile that for you in seconds.</p>

<p><strong>Equipment Details On-Demand</strong></p>

<p>Ever wondered exactly what’s in your component pouch or what that obscure magic item does? An AI could provide detailed breakdowns of equipment contents and magical properties on command. For example:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“List all the components in my component pouch.”</li>
  <li>“What are the exact effects of the Ring of Spell Storing I just found?”</li>
  <li>“Calculate how many days of rations I can carry at my current strength.”</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Group Information Aggregation</strong></p>

<p>DMs often need to compile information about the entire party quickly. An AI assistant could be invaluable for this:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“Create a table with all characters’ ability modifiers, initiative bonuses, and passive perception scores.”</li>
  <li>“List all party members’ languages and their tool proficiencies.”</li>
  <li>“Summarize the party’s current inventory of healing potions and scrolls.”</li>
  <li>“I have 4 days of downtime and 300gp, what could I craft in that time?”</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Rules and Mechanics Clarification</strong></p>

<p>When disputes or questions about rules arise, an AI could quickly provide relevant information from the rulebooks, saving time spent leafing through pages or searching PDFs.</p>

<p><strong>Campaign Note Organization</strong></p>

<p>For DMs, keeping track of campaign notes, NPCs, and plot threads can be challenging. An AI assistant could help organize and recall this information effortlessly, allowing DMs to focus more on storytelling and less on bookkeeping.</p>

<ul>
  <li>“I need to know what plot threads I left open in the city of Thornwick.”</li>
  <li>“Give me a list of funny quotes from the campaign.”</li>
  <li>“Randomly remove 3 items from from the inventory of every character.”</li>
  <li>“I need to know what my party is currently carrying. Give me a compiled list of everything.”</li>
  <li>“What was the last mention of an NPC named Kaelin in the campaign notes?”</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>

<p>While it’s crucial to remain vigilant about preserving the human creativity at the heart of TTRPGs, we shouldn’t dismiss AI entirely. By focusing on applications that enhance rather than replace human input, we can leverage AI to make our games more accessible, efficient, and enjoyable.</p>

<p>The key is to view AI as a tool that empowers DMs and players, not as a replacement for the imagination and storytelling that make our hobby unique. As we continue to explore the potential of AI in TTRPGs, let’s keep an open mind about how it can be used to elevate our gaming experiences while preserving the essence of what makes tabletop roleplaying special.</p>

<p>By leveraging AI for data management tasks, we can focus more on the creative and interactive aspects of the game. The tedious record-keeping becomes just a prompt away from being useful, allowing players and DMs to immerse themselves more fully in the storytelling and roleplaying experience.</p>

<p>It’s important to note that while AI can greatly enhance our ability to manage and access game information, it doesn’t replace the need for human decision-making and creativity. The AI serves as a powerful tool to support and streamline the game, allowing us to spend more time on the aspects of TTRPGs that we truly enjoy.</p>

<p>What are your thoughts on AI in TTRPGs? Are there other applications you think could be beneficial? Hit me on on X and let me know!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="rpg resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore positive AI applications in TTRPGs. Discover how AI can enhance gameplay, streamline admin tasks, and support creativity without replacing human input.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/ttrpg_players_and_robot_1200x600.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/ttrpg_players_and_robot_1200x600.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/15/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-09-15T20:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-15T20:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/15/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/15/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back to Insight Check! This is my experiment in a weekly roundup of TTRPG news and trends you may have missed. From nostalgic franchises making their tabletop debut to beloved indie darlings expanding their realms, we’ve got a little magic for every gaming group. This week’s roundup covers everything from a transformative bundle that’s more than meets the eye to Root’s woodland creatures delving into dungeons, community highlights from Tabletop Scotland, and even a liminal deal that bridges our world and the next. So, grab your character sheets and settle into your comfiest chair (I’ve got my trusty tankard of coffee right here) as we explore the latest happenings in the TTRPG world. Whether you’re a dungeon master looking for new tools or a player seeking your next great campaign, I promise there’s something here to spark your imagination and fuel your next adventure.</p>

<p>Ready to roll? Let’s dive into stories for the week of September 15th 2024!</p>

<h3 id="humble-bundle---transformers-rpg">Humble Bundle - Transformers RPG</h3>
<p><em>September 8, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/humble-bundle-transformers-rpg.html" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>, #HumbleBundle #Transformers #RPG #Deals</p>

<p>A new Humble Bundle featuring a Transformers RPG has been launched, providing fans with a unique gaming experience. This bundle offers a range of materials and resources that can help you dive deep into the world of Transformers, making it a must-have for fans of the franchise. If you’re a Transformers fan or just looking for a new RPG to explore, this bundle offers excellent value. Check out the <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/humble-bundle-transformers-rpg.html" target="_blank">full article here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="root-the-roleplaying-game--ruins-and-expeditions-adds-dungeons-and-delves-and-monsters">‘Root: The Roleplaying Game’ – “Ruins and Expeditions” Adds Dungeons and Delves and Monsters</h3>
<p><em>September 9, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/09/root-the-roleplaying-game-ruins-and-expeditions-adds-dungeons-and-delves-and-monsters.html" target="_blank">Bell of Lost Souls</a>, #RootRPG #Expansion #Dungeons #Monsters</p>

<p>The latest expansion for ‘Root: The Roleplaying Game’ introduces new adventures, including dungeons, delves, and monsters, expanding the gameplay for fans. This addition brings a fresh layer of excitement and complexity to an already beloved game. If you’re a fan of Root, this expansion is a game-changer. Discover more about the new features <a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/09/root-the-roleplaying-game-ruins-and-expeditions-adds-dungeons-and-delves-and-monsters.html" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="audio-exp-podcast-253--the-tabletop-scotland-download">Audio EXP Podcast: #253 – The Tabletop Scotland download</h3>
<p><em>September 10, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168503/audio-exp-podcast-253-the-tabletop-scotland-download/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>, #Podcast #TabletopScotland #Community</p>

<p>The latest episode of the Audio EXP Podcast discusses recent developments in the tabletop gaming community, including highlights from Tabletop Scotland. This episode is packed with insights and updates that are sure to interest any TTRPG fan. Stay updated with the latest community news and events by listening to this episode. Find out more <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168503/audio-exp-podcast-253-the-tabletop-scotland-download/" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="voting-open-for-the-rpg-publisher-spotlight-october-2024">Voting open for the RPG Publisher Spotlight October 2024</h3>
<p><em>September 11, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168249/voting-open-for-the-rpg-publisher-spotlight-october-2024/" target="_blank">Geek Native</a>, #RPGPublisher #Voting #Community</p>

<p>Voting has opened for the RPG Publisher Spotlight, allowing fans to recognize their favorite publishers in the industry. This is a fantastic opportunity to support the creators who bring your favorite games to life. Show your support for your favorite RPG publishers by participating in the voting. Learn how you can cast your vote <a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168249/voting-open-for-the-rpg-publisher-spotlight-october-2024/" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="kickstarter---warlock-knight-dfrpg">Kickstarter - Warlock Knight (DFRPG)</h3>
<p><em>September 12, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/kickstarter-warlock-knight-dfrpg.html" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>, #Kickstarter #WarlockKnight #DFRPG</p>

<p>A new Kickstarter campaign for ‘Warlock Knight’ has launched, aiming to bring fresh content and adventures to the DFRPG community. This campaign promises to add exciting new elements to the game, making it a worthwhile investment for fans. Support the Kickstarter and be among the first to experience the new content. Check out the campaign details <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/kickstarter-warlock-knight-dfrpg.html" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h3 id="bundle-of-holding---liminal-modiphius">Bundle of Holding - Liminal (Modiphius)</h3>
<p><em>September 13, 2024</em>, <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/bundle-of-holding-liminal-modiphius.html" target="_blank">Tenkar’s Tavern</a>, #BundleOfHolding #Liminal #Modiphius #Deals</p>

<p>A new Bundle of Holding featuring the Liminal RPG from Modiphius is available, providing great deals for players looking to explore new settings. This bundle offers a rich and immersive experience at a fraction of the cost. Don’t miss out on this fantastic deal. Learn more about what’s included in the bundle <a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/bundle-of-holding-liminal-modiphius.html" target="_blank">here</a>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>This week has been a whirlwind of exciting news and developments in the TTRPG world. Whether you’re a fan of Transformers, Root, or looking to support new projects on Kickstarter, there’s something for everyone. Stay tuned to OptionalRules.com for more updates and insights into the ever-evolving world of tabletop roleplaying games.</p>

<p>Happy gaming!</p>

<p>I hope this roundup helps you stay informed and inspired for your next gaming session. Don’t forget to check out the links for more detailed information and consider supporting the creators who make our favorite games possible. Until next time, roll those dice and embark on new adventures!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[TTRPG News and Trends you may have missed for the week ending of September 15th 2024.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/09/insight-check/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Insight Check - TTRPG News &amp;amp; Events" /><published>2024-09-09T20:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-09T20:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/09/insight-check</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/09/insight-check/"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the first Insight Check! A small experiment I’m trying out to see if there is any interest in a weekly news and trends series. In this first weekly round-up, we’ve got everything from digital tools leveling up (and changing their character name) to video game developers crossing the planes into our tabletop realm. We’ll explore how D&amp;D is rolling natural 20s in helping folks with autism, and we’ll peek behind the DM screen at a horror game that’s sure to give your Charisma score a fright.</p>

<p>So, pull up a chair, order your favorite fantasy brew, and let’s embark on this quest together. Who knows? You might just gain advantage on your next roll at the gaming table. Ready your dice, and let’s dive in!</p>

<h3 id="study-playing-dungeons--dragons-helps-autistic-players-in-social-interactions">Study: Playing Dungeons &amp; Dragons helps autistic players in social interactions</h3>
<p><strong>September 4, 2024</strong>, Ars Technica; #D&amp;D #Autism<br />
A recent study reveals that playing D&amp;D significantly aids autistic players in developing social skills. The study provides empirical evidence that the game’s mechanics and narrative-driven engagement help players navigate social cues and build friendships. This aligns with a growing trend within the RPG community to promote inclusivity and accessibility, echoing historical movements towards making gaming environments more welcoming for diverse players. The therapeutic potential of RPGs is becoming more recognized, demonstrating a shift in how games are perceived beyond mere entertainment.<br />
<a href="https://arstechnica.com/science/2024/09/study-playing-dungeons-dragons-helps-autistic-players-in-social-interactions/" target="_blank">Read more</a></p>

<h3 id="splinter-cell-and-far-cry-2-developer-launches-new-ttrpg--mythmaster-rpg-now-in-beta">‘Splinter Cell’ and ‘Far Cry 2’ Developer Launches New TTRPG – ‘Mythmaster RPG’ Now In Beta</h3>
<p><strong>September 5, 2024</strong>, Bell of Lost Souls; #TTRPG #Mythmaster RPG<br />
In an exciting development for tabletop gaming, the developers behind popular video games like ‘Splinter Cell’ and ‘Far Cry 2’ have launched ‘Mythmaster RPG,’ now in beta testing. This move signifies a growing trend of crossover between video games and tabletop RPGs, where established brands are exploring new formats to engage with fans. The historical connection between video games and tabletop RPGs has been long-standing, with many mechanics and storytelling techniques crossing over. The influx of video game developers into the TTRPG space could lead to innovative gameplay experiences and attract a broader audience to tabletop gaming.<br />
<a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/09/splinter-cell-and-far-cry-2-developer-launches-new-ttrpg-mythmaster-rpg-now-in-beta.html" target="_blank">Read more</a></p>

<h3 id="sleepy-hollow-kids-in-the-attic-fund-folk-horror-ttrpg">Sleepy Hollow: Kids in the Attic fund folk horror TTRPG</h3>
<p><strong>September 5, 2024</strong>, Geek Native; #TTRPG #Sleepy Hollow<br />
The successful funding of a folk horror tabletop RPG set in the ‘Sleepy Hollow’ universe speaks to the nostalgia-driven themes that continue to captivate gamers. This project taps into the rich history of folklore and horror in RPGs, which has been a staple since the inception of the genre. As tabletop RPGs increasingly explore unique and culturally rich settings, the ‘Sleepy Hollow’ game exemplifies how historical narratives can be reimagined through interactive storytelling. This trend highlights a revival of interest in genre-specific games, blending traditional folklore with modern gaming mechanics.<br />
<a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168259/sleepy-hollow-kids-in-the-attic-fund-folk-horror-ttrpg/" target="_blank">Read more</a></p>

<h3 id="hedron-worldbuilding-platform-raises-51000-and-changes-name">Hedron: Worldbuilding platform raises $51,000 (and changes name)</h3>
<p><strong>September 6, 2024</strong>, Geek Native; #TTRPG #Worldbuilding<br />
The worldbuilding platform ‘Hedron’ has successfully raised $51,000 and announced a name change, reflecting the evolving needs of tabletop RPG creators. This funding success illustrates the increasing reliance on crowdfunding within the tabletop community, a trend that has reshaped how games are developed and marketed. Historically, many RPGs began as grassroots initiatives, and this model continues to empower creators by providing direct access to funding and community support. Hedron’s evolution signifies a commitment to enhancing the creative process for RPG developers, ensuring a diverse range of games and settings for players.<br />
<a href="https://www.geeknative.com/168313/hedron-worldbuilding-platform-raises-51000-and-changes-name/" target="_blank">Read more</a></p>

<h3 id="cyberpunk-2077-the-board-game-smashes-crowdfunding-goals-with-over-3-million-raised-and-counting">‘Cyberpunk 2077: The Board Game’ Smashes Crowdfunding Goals With Over $3 Million Raised, And Counting</h3>
<p><strong>September 6, 2024</strong>, Bell of Lost Souls; #Cyberpunk 2077 #Board Game<br />
The crowdfunding campaign for ‘Cyberpunk 2077: The Board Game’ has exceeded expectations by raising over $3 million. This monumental success underscores the enduring popularity of the Cyberpunk franchise and its transition into the board game realm. Historically, adaptations from video games to tabletop formats have seen varied success, but the massive backing for this project indicates a robust interest in hybrid gaming experiences. This trend reflects a broader movement within the industry to capitalize on popular IPs and engage fans in new and interactive ways, merging the excitement of video gaming with traditional tabletop experiences.<br />
<a href="https://www.belloflostsouls.net/2024/09/cyberpunk-2077-the-board-game-smashes-crowdfunding-goals-with-over-3-million-raised-and-counting.html" target="_blank">Read more</a></p>

<h3 id="new-release---humans-humans-1st-edition-for-monsters-monsters">New Release - Humans! Humans! 1st Edition (For Monsters! Monsters!)</h3>
<p><strong>September 7, 2024</strong>, Tenkar’s Tavern; #TTRPG #Humans! Humans!<br />
The release of ‘Humans! Humans!’, designed as a companion for ‘Monsters! Monsters!’, expands the narrative options available to tabletop RPG enthusiasts. This new release is part of a growing trend towards creating interconnected games that enhance player experience by allowing different perspectives and gameplay styles. Historically, the RPG genre has thrived on the expansion of lore and mechanics, with numerous games branching off from established titles. The introduction of this new edition signifies the ongoing evolution of RPG systems, promoting diversity in storytelling and gameplay experiences for all types of players.<br />
<a href="https://www.tenkarstavern.com/2024/09/new-release-humans-humans-1st-edition.html" target="_blank">Read more</a></p>

<p>That’s it for the past week, ping me on twitter if you found anything interesting!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="insight check" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Latest TTRPG News and Trends for the week of September 7th 2024.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/InsightCheck.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Crafting Cultural Depth Through Food in TTRPGs</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/08/worldbuilding-through-food/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crafting Cultural Depth Through Food in TTRPGs" /><published>2024-09-08T13:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-08T13:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/08/worldbuilding-through-food</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/08/worldbuilding-through-food/"><![CDATA[<p>The recent artwork depicting the Hero’s Feast spell has sparked a heated debate within the TTRPG community. While some argue that the inclusion of modern dishes like sushi and tacos breaks immersion, others welcome this expansion of the game’s aesthetics to make the setting familiar to more people. However, this debate overlooks a powerful worldbuilding tool: using food to create a deeper sense of culture and tradition in our fantasy worlds.</p>

<p>Food is a universal connector across cultures, and it can be an excellent vehicle for humanizing and adding depth to the communities in your TTRPG settings. This post will explore how to effectively use food descriptions to enhance your worldbuilding, providing concrete strategies and examples to implement in your games.</p>

<h2 id="the-power-of-food-in-worldbuilding">The Power of Food in Worldbuilding</h2>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/heroes-feast_480x302.webp" alt="A group of adventurers enjoying a hearty feast." height="302" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Heros Feast by Wizards of the Coast</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Food can instantly create a sense of verisimilitude about the communities in your world. It’s not just about what people eat, but the particular styles and traditions behind it, which can suggest a great deal about a culture. Here are some key reasons why food is an effective worldbuilding tool:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Universal relatability</li>
  <li>Cultural signifier</li>
  <li>Historical context</li>
  <li>Social dynamics</li>
  <li>Environmental indicators</li>
</ol>

<p>By incorporating food into your descriptions, you can subtly convey information about all these aspects of your world.</p>

<h2 id="strategies-for-using-food-in-worldbuilding">Strategies for Using Food in Worldbuilding</h2>

<h3 id="1-describe-dont-label">1. Describe, Don’t Label</h3>

<p>The key to effective food-based worldbuilding is to let the player draw connections to the familiar without explicitly naming real-world dishes. Instead of saying “taco,” describe the dish:</p>

<ul>
  <li>“Spiced meats nestled in a warm, soft flatbread”</li>
  <li>“Tender chunks of seasoned meat cradled in a folded, griddled cornmeal cake”</li>
  <li>“Sliced cooked vegitables in a rich sauce of light oils and spices, with a spongy bread used to grab and eat the dish.”</li>
</ul>

<p>This approach allows players to make connections while maintaining the fantasy atmosphere.</p>

<h3 id="2-use-food-to-hint-at-cultural-practices">2. Use Food to Hint at Cultural Practices</h3>

<p>Food preparation and consumption can reveal a lot about a culture. Consider the following examples:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A culture that values community might have traditions of communal cooking and shared meals</li>
  <li>A nomadic society might favor preserved foods and portable meals</li>
  <li>A hierarchical society might have strict rules about who can eat certain foods</li>
  <li>A society may have particular traditions about the use of animals as food</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="3-incorporate-food-into-religious-or-magical-practices">3. Incorporate Food into Religious or Magical Practices</h3>

<p>Food often plays a role in religious rituals and magical practices. Some ideas to consider:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Sacred plants or animals that are never eaten</li>
  <li>Medicinal plants or animals that are always eaten</li>
  <li>Specific preparations required for magical ingredients</li>
  <li>Fasting or feasting traditions tied to religious observances</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="4-use-food-to-indicate-social-status">4. Use Food to Indicate Social Status</h3>

<p>What people eat can say a lot about their place in society. Think about:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Rare or expensive ingredients reserved for the elite</li>
  <li>“Peasant foods” that become delicacies</li>
  <li>Taboos around certain foods for different social classes</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="5-let-food-reflect-the-environment">5. Let Food Reflect the Environment</h3>

<p>The available food can tell players a lot about the local environment. Consider:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Coastal regions with abundant seafood</li>
  <li>Arid areas with drought-resistant grains and preserved foods</li>
  <li>Lush forests with a variety of fruits and game meats</li>
  <li>Hot climates using spices and drying techniques for food preservation</li>
  <li>Cold climates relying on smoking, salting, and fermentation for food storage</li>
  <li>Temperate regions developing cheese-making and curing methods for dairy and meat preservation</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="implementing-food-based-worldbuilding">Implementing Food-Based Worldbuilding</h2>

<p>To effectively use these strategies in your game, consider the following steps:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Create a food profile for each major culture in your world</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>List three staple ingredients used in most meals</li>
      <li>Describe common cooking methods, unique tools, or how food is stored</li>
      <li>Note any significant food-related traditions of who can eat, what, and why</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Incorporate food descriptions into your scene-setting</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Describe smells and sounds of cooking in market scenes</li>
      <li>Mention what characters are eating during social interactions</li>
      <li>Highlight an NPCs preferences through how they eat their food (greedy, cautious, supiciously smell every bite, etc)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Use food as a plot device</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>A rare ingredient as a quest item</li>
      <li>Diplomatic incidents over unfamiliar food customs</li>
      <li>Poisoned feasts as a dramatic set-piece</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Encourage player engagement with food</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Ask players what their characters typically eat</li>
      <li>Allow cooking skill checks for mechanical benefits, like helping in negotiations</li>
      <li>Use food preferences as character development opportunities</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>By thoughtfully incorporating food into your worldbuilding, you can create a richer, more immersive experience for your players. This approach allows you to subtly convey cultural information without resorting to direct real-world analogues or risking the trivialization of actual cultures.</p>

<p>Remember, the goal is to create something new that feels familiar enough to be believable. By sprinkling in these culinary details, you’re not just describing food; you’re hinting at entire cultures and histories that can make your world come alive.</p>

<p>Next time you’re describing a feast in your game, consider how you can use food to paint a picture of your world’s cultures. It’s an excellent way to add depth to your game without breaking immersion.</p>

<h2 id="resources-for-further-exploration">Resources for Further Exploration</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://mythcreants.com/blog/podcasts/385-food-in-spec-fic/" target="_blank">Mythcreants ep385 - Food in Speculative Fiction</a> podcast</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Food-History-Reay-Tannahill/dp/0517884046" target="_blank">Food in History</a> Book by Reay Tannahill</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.tumblr.com/inky-duchess/188520337528/fantasy-guide-to-feasts-food-and-drink" target="_blank">Fantasy Guide to Feasts</a> tumblr by inky-duchess</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.innatthecrossroads.com/" target="_blank">The Inn at the Crossroads</a> blog on ficitional foods of all kinds.</li>
</ul>

<p>These resources can provide inspiration and depth to your food-based worldbuilding efforts. Remember, the key is to use these ideas as springboards for your own creativity, tailoring them to fit the unique aspects of your game world.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="rpg resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn how to use food descriptions in TTRPGs to create rich, immersive worlds. Practical tips for DMs to enhance cultural worldbuilding through cuisine.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/heroes-feast_1200x757.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/heroes-feast_1200x757.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mounted Combat in Shadowdark TTRPG</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/04/mounted-combat-in-shadowdark/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mounted Combat in Shadowdark TTRPG" /><published>2024-09-04T11:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-04T11:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/04/mounted-combat-in-shadowdark</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/09/04/mounted-combat-in-shadowdark/"><![CDATA[<p>Greetings, brave crawlers! Whether you’re charging into battle, making daring escapes, or simply looking for a reliable way to haul your hard-earned loot, mounts are an essential part of any fantasy adventurer’s toolkit. They add a thrilling dimension to gameplay, especially during overland adventures where a simple yet engaging mounted combat system can elevate the excitement of your <a href="https://www.thearcanelibrary.com/pages/shadowdark" target="_blank">Shadowdark</a> game.</p>

<p>In the spirit of Shadowdark’s minimalist yet evocative style, I’ve crafted these concise rules for mounted combat and travel. They’re designed to seamlessly integrate with the Shadowdark TTRPG, offering a brief but descriptive framework that expands your options without bogging down gameplay.
These mounted combat rules are part of a larger project, where I’m compiling various travel-related mechanics. In addition to what you’ll find here, I’ve posted some rules for <a href="/2024/08/26/expanded-herb-list-for-shadowdark/">hebs &amp; foraging</a>, and will be writing some rules on setting up camps, and interactive travel. The goal is to create a comprehensive supplement that enriches your overland adventures in the Shadowdark universe.</p>

<p>I’m excited to share these rules with you and eager to hear your thoughts! Please reach out to me on <a href="https://x.com/optionalrule" target="_blank">X (Twitter)</a> to share your feedback, experiences, or suggestions. I’m also in the Shadowdark Discord, so hit me up there. Your input is invaluable as we continue to expand and refine the Shadowdark experience.</p>

<h2 id="the-power-of-a-trusty-steed">The Power of a Trusty Steed</h2>

<p>Crawling in Shadowdark is dangerous buisness, but it’s not always delving underground. A reliable mount can be the difference between glory and a cold, lonely grave in the dark forests and dangerous countryside. But how exactly do these majestic beasts enhance your combat prowess? Let’s break it down.</p>

<p>When you’re astride your mount, you gain a +1 bonus to hit with melee weapons. It’s amazing what a little extra height can do for your swing!</p>

<h4 id="charge">Charge!</h4>

<p>Wielding a polearm atop a charging mount? Add your mount’s Strength modifier to your damage. This devastating move requires a straight charge of at least Near distance.</p>

<p>But beware, brave rider! This tactic cuts both ways. If you’re on the receiving end of a charging foe while wielding a polearm, you can add the enemy mount’s Strength modifier to your damage to an attack on any rider that has charged you. It’s a high-risk, high-reward situation!</p>

<h4 id="mounted-movement">Mounted Movement</h4>

<p>When mounted, you use your trusty steed’s movement as your own. This can significantly increase your tactical options on the battlefield or help you outrun that pesky goblin that’s been tailing you… Let’s just hope they don’t have shortbows.</p>

<h4 id="the-perils-of-riding">The Perils of Riding</h4>

<p>However, mounted combat isn’t all glory and triumph. There are risks to consider:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Bolting</strong>: If your mount gets spooked (either by fright or by taking half its hit points in damage), you’ll need to make a Morale check. Fail, and your mount bolts, carrying you away from the fray—whether you like it or not!</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Staying Ahorse</strong>: When your mount rears or stumbles, you’ll need to make a hard Strength check to avoid being thrown. No proper saddle? You’re rolling with disadvantage, cowboy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Unseating a Rider</strong>: Enemies can try to knock you off your high horse with a contested Strength check. You get advantage on your roll, but if you fail, it’s a long way down.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="burdens-carry-capacity-of-mounts">Burdens: Carry Capacity of Mounts</h3>

<p>Mounts are not just for riding; they’re excellent pack animals too:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Riderless mounts can carry triple the normal Gear Slots.</li>
  <li>Mounts with riders use standard Gear Slots.</li>
</ul>

<p><em>(For more details on Gear Slots, check out page 35 of the Shadowdark rulebook.)</em></p>

<h2 id="meet-the-mounts">Meet the Mounts</h2>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/charing-warrior_480x782.png" alt="A black and white image of a warrior charging on a warhorse. AI Image." height="782" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<p>Horses are the most common mount or pack animal in most setting, but by no means the only.  In addition to the normal riding Horse presented on <em>p227</em> in the Shadowdark TTRPG, here are a few more options for your adventurer.</p>

<blockquote class="sd-stat-block wide">
  <h2 id="ponymule">Pony/Mule</h2>
  <p><em>The Crawler’s Trusty Companion. Neutral</em></p>

  <ul>
    <li><strong>AC</strong> 12</li>
    <li><strong>HP</strong> 11, <strong>LV</strong> 2</li>
    <li><strong>ATK</strong> hooves +2 (1d6)</li>
    <li><strong>MV</strong> Double Near, <strong>AL</strong> N</li>
  </ul>

  <table>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td><strong>S:</strong> +2</td>
        <td><strong>D:</strong> +2</td>
        <td><strong>C:</strong> +2</td>
        <td><strong>I:</strong> -3</td>
        <td><strong>W:</strong> +1</td>
        <td><strong>C:</strong> -2</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>

  <p><strong>Surefooted.</strong> ADV on any roll to avoid tripping or falling.</p>

  <p><strong>Stout.</strong> (<em>Mules only</em>) Mules carry quadruple their normal Gear Slots when riderless.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="sd-stat-block wide">
  <h2 id="war-horse">War Horse</h2>
  <p><em>Bred for battle and Fury. Neutral</em></p>

  <ul>
    <li><strong>AC</strong> 12</li>
    <li><strong>HP</strong> 16, <strong>LV</strong> 3</li>
    <li><strong>ATK:</strong> hooves +4 (1d8)</li>
    <li><strong>MV</strong> Double Near</li>
  </ul>

  <table>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td><strong>S:</strong> +4</td>
        <td><strong>D:</strong> +2</td>
        <td><strong>C:</strong> +3</td>
        <td><strong>I:</strong> -3</td>
        <td><strong>W:</strong> +1</td>
        <td><strong>C:</strong> -2</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>

  <p><strong>Fearless.</strong> ADV on Morale checks.</p>

  <p><strong>Fury.</strong> Attack with hooves during rider’s turn.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="gearing-up-your-mount">Gearing Up Your Mount</h2>

<p>Mounts require a bit of gear and care. Tack is generally required to ride or guide a mount, and all actions are at disadvantage without it. Barding is available to safeguard your mount in battle, but only War horses can wear Chain or Plate. While most mounts can forage in a normal or wooded environment, they’ll need Feed to gain the benefits of a rest.</p>

<table class="table table-striped">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">Gear</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Cost</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Slots</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Tack (Saddle, stirrups, bridle, halter, rein, bit, and harness)</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">15 gp</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">2</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Barding (Leather, Chain, or Plate armor)</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">4x</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">2x</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Feed (3 days)</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">2 sp</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">1</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h4 id="buying-a-mount">Buying a Mount</h4>

<table class="container table table-striped">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: left">Mount</th>
      <th style="text-align: center">Cost</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Horse</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">100 gp</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Mule</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">25 gp</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">Pony</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">20 gp</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: left">War Horse</td>
      <td style="text-align: center">300 gp</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="adding-flavor-mount-coats">Adding Flavor: Mount Coats</h2>

<p>Want to make your mount stand out? Roll a d10 and consult this table for your mount’s coat color:</p>

<table class="table">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: center">d10</th>
      <th>Coat Color</th>
      <th>Description</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">1</td>
      <td>Midnight Black</td>
      <td>A deep, lustrous black that seems to absorb light. Often associated with mysterious or powerful mounts.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">2</td>
      <td>Chestnut Brown</td>
      <td>A rich, warm brown color reminiscent of polished wood. Common among sturdy, reliable steeds.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">3</td>
      <td>Dapple Gray</td>
      <td>A mesmerizing pattern of dark spots on a light gray background, creating a cloudy effect. Often seen on elegant, mature horses.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">4</td>
      <td>Pure White</td>
      <td>A brilliant, unblemished white coat that seems to glow. Rare and often associated with noble or magical mounts.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">5</td>
      <td>Golden Palomino</td>
      <td>A shimmering golden body color with a white mane and tail. Prized for their beauty and often favored by nobles.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">6</td>
      <td>Roan</td>
      <td>A striking mix of red-brown and white hairs, creating a speckled appearance. Known for their hardy nature.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">7</td>
      <td>Bay</td>
      <td>A classic look with a red-brown body and black mane, tail, and lower legs. Versatile and common among various breeds.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">8</td>
      <td>Pinto</td>
      <td>Dramatic large patches of white and dark colors (often black, brown, or chestnut). Each pattern is unique, like a living canvas.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">9</td>
      <td>Buckskin</td>
      <td>A golden tan body with black mane, tail, and lower legs. Often associated with tough, enduring mounts of the frontier.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">10</td>
      <td>Appaloosa</td>
      <td>Distinctive spotted pattern, often with a white or light-colored body covered in dark spots. Historically bred by the Nez Perce people and known for their intelligence and stamina.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>So there you have it, brave adventurers! With these rules, you’re ready to thunder across the battlefield, charge down your foes, and explore the far reaches of your Shadowdark world on horseback. Remember, a well-trained mount is more than just a means of transportation—it’s a loyal companion and a formidable weapon in the right hands.</p>

<p>Now, saddle up and ride forth to glory! May your steeds be swift, your aim be true, and your shadows less… er… darkly!</p>

<p>Anyway, let me know what you think!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="Shadowdark" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Enhance your Shadowdark RPG adventures with new mounted combat rules. Learn about different mounts, gear, and tactics for thrilling horseback battles and travel.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/KnightsCharging.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/KnightsCharging.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Roleplaying Origins of Early Dungeons and Dragons</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/28/rolepalying-origins-of-dnd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Roleplaying Origins of Early Dungeons and Dragons" /><published>2024-08-28T08:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-28T08:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/28/rolepalying-origins-of-dnd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/28/rolepalying-origins-of-dnd/"><![CDATA[<p>There’s a common misconception floating around that narrative roleplaying in tabletop games is a relatively modern invention, something that only came into focus with the later editions of <a href="https://www.dndbeyond.com/" target="_blank">Dungeons &amp; Dragons</a> and other game systems like <a href="https://evilhat.com/product/blades-in-the-dark/" target="_blank">Blades in the Dark</a>. This belief, while understandable, couldn’t be further from the truth. From its earliest days, DnD was designed with roleplaying at its core—a distinction that set it apart from the wargames that preceded it. Sure, early DnD had its share of combat (often brutal and unforgiving), but if you think it was all about kicking down doors and hacking away at monsters, you’ve missed the point, and probably rolled a lot of new characters. The truth is, combat was risky, and survival often depended on players being more thoughtful, more cunning. Roleplaying wasn’t an option; it was a necessity, at least in the way early DnD framed it but more on that later. <em>Many of the early modules assumed players would be talking, negotiating, and thinking their way out of danger as often than they’d be fighting.</em></p>

<h3 id="the-assumptions-behind-early-roleplaying">The Assumptions Behind Early Roleplaying</h3>

<p>Modern gamers didn’t invent roleplaying—they inherited it. However, it’s fair to say that what we now consider “roleplaying” has evolved significantly since the earliest days of DnD. Back then, roleplaying was less about theatrical performance and more about practical problem-solving and character goals. The roots of DnD in wargaming meant that much of the roleplaying was centered around diplomacy, negotiation, and building relationships—things that didn’t need a lot of rules because the system trusted players to bring their own creativity to the table.</p>

<p>Characters in early DnD didn’t have a list of skills to guide them. They didn’t have a “persuasion” or “Insight” roll to determine if they could talk their way out of trouble or detect lies. The system didn’t do the thinking for the player. Instead, it was up to the players to decide what their characters would do in any given situation. Want to negotiate a truce between two warring factions? That’s on you, the player, to figure out. The DM was there to adjudicate the outcome, but the process was driven entirely by the player’s ideas and actions. This was a FEATURE of the early game design and one of the reasons I find games with an OG design philosophy like <a href="https://www.thearcanelibrary.com/pages/shadowdark" target="_blank">Shadowdark</a> so compelling. I think others do as well, which is why there is such an explosion of <a href="https://www.drivethrurpg.com/en/browse?legFilter1=45582" target="_blank">OSR games</a>, each with it’s own community and appeal.</p>

<p><em>Skills were not included in these early editions because it was assumed the characters thoughts, talents, goals, and decisions were entirely the domain of the player, with help from the DM to fit them to the setting.</em>  This was not seen as the domain of the rules, and some can credibly argue that the introduction of skills deminished that.  More on that below.</p>

<h3 id="examples-of-roleplaying-in-early-dnd-adventure-modules">Examples of Roleplaying in Early DnD Adventure Modules</h3>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/keep-on-the-borderlands_480x621.jpg" alt="An image of the cover of the early DnD adventure module, The Keep on the Borderlands by TSR." height="621" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Lets Hug it out Bro!</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>As proof, I offer you the early classic adventures of B/X and AD&amp;D, where roleplaying and negotiation were front and center:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>B2: The Keep on the Borderlands (1979)</strong>: Here, the Caves of Chaos are populated by various humanoid tribes, and players are encouraged to negotiate or manipulate these groups. Forming alliances wasn’t just possible—it was an assumed strategy for success. I know this module was selected as the basis for the new DnD 2024 Starter Kit and I don’t think it was an accident. I expect the negotiation and roleplaying elements are a big part of why this selected.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>T1: The Village of Hommlet (1979)</strong>: The village itself is teeming with NPCs who have their own motivations and secrets. The players are expected to engage with these NPCs, gather information, and solve the underlying mysteries—diplomacy and social interaction were key.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>X1: The Isle of Dread (1981)</strong>: This module blends exploration with opportunities for diplomacy. Players can negotiate with native factions, and how they handle these interactions can dramatically affect their survival.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>I1: Dwellers of the Forbidden City (1981)</strong>: The Forbidden City is a complex environment where factions vie for power. Players can navigate this web of intrigue through negotiation, making roleplaying a crucial component of the adventure.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>L1: The Secret of Bone Hill (1981)</strong>: Restenford, the town featured in this module, is a hotbed of NPC interaction. Players are encouraged to investigate and solve local mysteries by engaging with the townsfolk—again, roleplaying takes the lead.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>A1: Slave Pits of the Undercity (1980)</strong>: Although this series is known for its combat, A1 offers opportunities for infiltration, negotiation, and deception. Players can choose to engage slavers diplomatically, leveraging social skills over combat.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>C1: The Hidden Shrine of Tamoachan (1980)</strong>: Survival in this module often hinges on the players’ ability to think creatively and roleplay effectively. It’s not just about fighting—it’s about engaging with the world in a way that bypasses danger.  This is perfect as a “survival and planning as roleplaying” type of module where action isn’t just funny quips and voices.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>S1: Tomb of Horrors (1978)</strong>: This infamous module is packed with deadly traps, but it also demands intellectual engagement. Players must decipher clues and solve puzzles through roleplaying and creative thinking. So even the glassic “meat grinder” module itself, at least assumed a heavy amount of though from the point of view of the character.  Again, roleplaying isn’t just about what a character says, it’s about what a character thinks and why.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>B3: Palace of the Silver Princess (1981)</strong>: The palace is home to various factions, and players can navigate the adventure through diplomacy and alliance-building. Roleplaying is essential to making it through this module.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>These examples make it clear: Roleplaying wasn’t just an optional extra in early DnD—it was baked into the design. The game expected players to engage with the world and its inhabitants in dynamic, creative ways, using their characters’ social skills just as much as their swords.</p>

<h3 id="something-gained-and-something-lost">Something Gained and Something Lost</h3>

<p>As DnD and TTRPGs have evolved, we’ve gained a lot in terms of narrative depth and character development. Today’s games often put a stronger emphasis on storytelling, character backstories, and interpersonal dynamics. This shift towards a more narrative-driven form of roleplaying has brought a richness and emotional depth that I personally enjoy.</p>

<p>But is it better? It’s hard to say. On one hand, the theatricality of modern roleplaying can be incredibly rewarding when done right, creating immersive and memorable experiences. On the other hand, it’s fair to acknowledge that this shift has come with some trade-offs. The rise of skill rolls and predefined abilities has made problem-solving more about mechanics than player creativity. In the early days, the game required players to think, plan, and strategize their way through challenges, often through group discussion and collective decision-making. Today, roleplaying can sometimes feel more like a series of individual performances rather than a collaborative effort.</p>

<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>I’m not saying one way is better than the other, but I do think we’ve lost sight of some of the core elements that made early DnD what it was. Roleplaying was always a central pillar of the game, and it didn’t need the elaborate systems we see today. Instead, it relied on the players’ own ingenuity and the social dynamic at the table. In moving towards a more performative style of roleplaying, we’ve gained a lot, but we’ve also left something behind. It’s worth remembering that the strategic, puzzle-solving aspect of the game—the part where players had to think their way through a problem—was just as important as the roleplaying itself. And in losing that, we may have lost a bit of the magic that made the early game so special.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Uncover how early D&D modules emphasized roleplaying, diplomacy, and problem-solving, shaping the evolution of the game from its wargaming roots.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/keep-on-the-borderlands_480x621.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/keep-on-the-borderlands_480x621.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Foraging for Herbs in Shadowdark</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/26/expanded-herb-list-for-shadowdark/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Foraging for Herbs in Shadowdark" /><published>2024-08-26T06:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-26T06:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/26/expanded-herb-list-for-shadowdark</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/26/expanded-herb-list-for-shadowdark/"><![CDATA[<p>Foraging for herbs has long been a cherished aspect of the Old-School Renaissance (OSR) gaming experience, offering players the chance to interact with their environment in meaningful ways. In the spirit of this tradition, these Herb Foraging rules for <a href="https://www.thearcanelibrary.com/pages/shadowdark" target="_blank">Shadowdark</a> aim to add an option for strategic play and enhance the immersive nature of your campaigns.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-shadowdark">What is Shadowdark?</h2>

<p>For those unfamiliar, Shadowdark is a rules-light, OSR-inspired roleplaying game that emphasizes dungeon crawling, resource management, and player ingenuity. It’s designed to capture the feel of classic fantasy RPGs while streamlining mechanics for modern play. I peronsally like it because it’s evokative of a grim dark tone I enjoy, fast to play, and I like the high risk gameplay. In this context, herbalism adds another layer of depth to character abilities and resource management, in an otherwise dangerous world.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/herbalist_bench_480x240.png" alt="A black and white drawing of a bench with herbs, equipment, and books on it. AI Image." height="240" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<h2 id="herbalism-in-shadowdark">Herbalism in Shadowdark</h2>

<p>Herbalism is the skill of locating, identifying, and using naturally occurring plants, fungi, and roots from the environment. These rules are designed as an extension—rather than a replacement—of the Herbalism ability introduced with the <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/scl/fi/z58yei3n055mblyzp6p4n/Bard-and-Ranger-Classes-V1-2.pdf" target="_blank">Ranger</a> class, providing additional options and choices for players looking to gather valuable resources during their adventures.</p>

<p>Game Masters should determine which classes or backgrounds may have access to this ability or allow characters to obtain the Herbalism skill, such as by spending money or trading a trait roll. Classes like the Witch, Priest of Nature, Seer, or others may have access to the ability. Likewise, the ability would fit well with backgrounds like Herbalist (of course), Ranger, Scholar, or Chirurgeon.</p>

<h2 id="foraging-rules">Foraging Rules</h2>

<p>Characters who wish to forage for herbs must spend 1 hour in-game and choose between two options:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Focused Foraging:</strong> Search for a specific herb in the area.
    <ul>
      <li>Roll an INT check against the herb’s DC.</li>
      <li>If successful, find a single dose, and an additional dose for every 3 points above the DC.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>General Foraging:</strong> Search an area for any herbs you can find.
    <ul>
      <li>Roll an INT check. Anything less than a Normal result is a failure, otherwise note the success range Normal (12+), Hard (15+), or Extreme (18+).</li>
      <li>Find 1 dose of a random herb of the rolled difficulty level, 1d3 herbs of the next lower difficulty, and 1d4 herbs from the lowest difficulty, as applicable.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p><em>Foraging Examples:</em></p>
<blockquote class="text-bg-light mb-3 p-3 fst-italic">
  <p><strong>Focused Foraging</strong>: Thorne, a skilled herbalist, is searching for Ghostweed (DC 13). He rolls a 16 on his INT check, succeeding by 3. Thorne finds 2 doses of Ghostweed.</p>

  <p><strong>General Foraging</strong>: Joyclin searches a location for herbs and rolls a 17, a Hard success. She finds 1 herb from the Hard column, and 1d3 herbs from the Normal column.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Any given area or location can only be searched once. A failure in either case means the character must complete a rest before searching again.</p>

<h3 id="untrained-characters">Untrained Characters</h3>

<p>Characters without the Herbalism ability can still attempt to forage for herbs, but:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Make INT checks at disadvantage</li>
  <li>Limited to finding herbs of Normal difficulty (DC 14 and below)</li>
  <li>Suffer 1d4 of poison damage if rolling a natural 1 due to encountering a “bad batch”</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="potency-and-preservation">Potency and Preservation</h2>

<p>An herb retains its potency for <em>1 real-life hour</em> after being harvested. A character with the herbalism ability and an Herbalist Kit may attempt to extend an herb’s potency by spending 1 in-game hour and making another INT check agains the herb’s DC. On a success, the herb’s potency is extended indefinitly as determined by the Game Master.  On a failure, the dose of herb is lost and the character must complete a rest before trying to preserve an herb’s potency again.</p>

<h2 id="herbalist-kit">Herbalist Kit</h2>

<p>An herbalist kit is a small collection of tools essential for the practice of herbalism such as clippers, specialized knoves, pouches, grinding stones, and a mortar and pestle.</p>

<blockquote class="text-bg-light mb-3 p-3 fst-italic">
  <p><strong>Herbalist Kit</strong>: 10 gp, 1 Gear Slot.W</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="extended-list-of-herbs">Extended List of Herbs</h2>

<p><strong>Table 1. Herb List</strong></p>

<table class="table table-striped table-hover table-sm">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: center">DC</th>
      <th style="text-align: left">Herb Description</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">11</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Lifeleaf Jelly</strong>. Heal 1 HP or 2 HP fire damage; can’t smell or taste for 1 hour.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">12</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Darkroot</strong>. Gain darkvision (Near) for 1 hour; blinded in light.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">12</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Murkweed</strong>. Hold breath up to 10 minutes or until you breathe.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">12</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Shakewort</strong>. Can’t be surprised, DISADV on stealth for 1 hour.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">13</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Foebane</strong>. ADV on attacks/damage vs one creature type; DISADV on death timer roll for 1d6.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">13</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Ghostweed</strong>. See invisible; DISADV on other Spot checks for 10 minutes.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">13</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Ghoul’s Cap</strong>. First attack in 10 min +2d6 Necrotic; DC 13 CON or take 1d4 Necrotic.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">13</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Stonebark</strong>. AC +2, DISADV on DEX checks for 1 hour.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">13</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Wraith’s Whisper</strong>. Speak with dead, but can’t understand living for 10 minutes.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">13</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Yeti’s Crown</strong>. ADV to resist cold, can’t see color for 1 hour.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">14</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Demon’s Tongue</strong>. Understand all speech, but speak a random language for 10 minutes.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">14</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Lichlichen</strong>. Immune to fear and charm for 10 minutes; DISADV on CHA checks for 1 hour.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">14</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Purgeroot</strong>. Ends poison/disease; DISADV on all rolls for 1d4 rounds from retching.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">15</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Bloodmoss</strong>. ADV on death timer roll, DISADV on healing for 1 hour.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">15</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Creeping Lily</strong>. Speak only to plants and fungi for 10 minutes.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">15</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Everburn Moss</strong>. Emit bright light (Near), dim light (Far); ranged attacks have ADV to hit you for 1 hour.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">15</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Serpent’s Sap</strong>. Blood is 2d4 poison to others for 1 hour; take 1d4 damage after.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">15</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Slumberberry</strong>. Heals like Potion of Healing; adds hours to rest equal to half damage healed.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">16</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Halfling’s Foil</strong>. Invisible for 1d4 rounds or until wounded/attacking.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">17</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Shune’s Breath</strong>. Voice heard by one known person up to 1 mile for 10 minutes. Can only whisper for 1 hour.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">18</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Banshee’s Hair</strong>. Scream for 1d4 rounds, DC 13 CHA or 2d6 Necrotic to all Near. Mute for 1 hour.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">18</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Satyr’s Root</strong>. You cannot be paralyzed for 1 hour and cannot rest for 12 hours.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">19</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Medusa’s Foil</strong>. You cannot be petrified for 1 hour and cannot rest for 24 hours.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">19</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Dream Nettle</strong>. Read surface thoughts (Close) for 1d6 rounds; DISADV on INT and WIS checks for 1 hour.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">20</td>
      <td style="text-align: left"><strong>Heartleaf</strong>. Extra action next turn; bleed for 1d4 if wounded in 10 minutes.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p><strong>Table 2. Random Herbs</strong></p>

<table class="table table-striped table-hover table-sm">
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th style="text-align: center">d12</th>
      <th>Normal (12)</th>
      <th>Hard (15)</th>
      <th>Extreme (18)</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">1</td>
      <td>Lifeleaf Jelly</td>
      <td>Purgeroot</td>
      <td>Satyr’s Root</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">2</td>
      <td>Darkroot</td>
      <td>Bloodmoss</td>
      <td>Banshee’s Hair</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">3</td>
      <td>Murkweed</td>
      <td>Bloodmoss</td>
      <td>Dream Nettle</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">4</td>
      <td>Shakewort</td>
      <td>Creeping Lily</td>
      <td>Medusa’s Foil</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">5</td>
      <td>Foebane</td>
      <td>Shune’s Breath</td>
      <td>Satyr’s Root</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">6</td>
      <td>Ghostweed</td>
      <td>Everburn Moss</td>
      <td>Banshee’s Hair</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">7</td>
      <td>Ghoul’s Cap</td>
      <td>Serpent’s Sap</td>
      <td>Dream Nettle</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">8</td>
      <td>Stonebark</td>
      <td>Serpent’s Sap</td>
      <td>Medusa’s Foil</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">9</td>
      <td>Wraith’s Whisper</td>
      <td>Slumberberry</td>
      <td>Satyr’s Root</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">10</td>
      <td>Yeti’s Crown</td>
      <td>Slumberberry</td>
      <td>Banshee’s Hair</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">11</td>
      <td>Demon’s Tongue</td>
      <td>Slumberberry</td>
      <td>Dream Nettle</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td style="text-align: center">12</td>
      <td>Lichlichen</td>
      <td>Halfling’s Foil</td>
      <td>Heartleaf</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>These tables are also <a href="/assets/downloads/shadowdar_extended_herblist_v1.pdf" target="_blank">available in PDF</a> form for easy reference at your table.</p>

<h2 id="ranger-herbalism">Ranger Herbalism</h2>

<p>This rule is not intended to supersede the Ranger Herbalism ability. Instead, it’s designed to complement and enhance the Ranger’s unique skills while providing options for other characters. Here’s how it maintains balance:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ranger’s Efficiency</strong>: Rangers can find and consume herbs as a multitask, which is significantly faster than the 1-hour foraging time for other characters.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ranger’s Expertise</strong>: The Ranger Herb list includes no drawbacks, maintaining their edge in herbalism.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Expanded Options</strong>: Rangers can use their search ability on any herb of DC 15 or less from the expanded list, and do not suffer the drawbacks listed.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Time Management</strong>: While other characters spend significant time foraging, Rangers can perform other tasks, maintaining their versatility.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>This design philosophy ensures that Rangers remain the masters of herbalism while allowing other characters to engage with the system in a meaningful way.</p>

<h2 id="gameplay-tips-for-gms">Gameplay Tips for GMs</h2>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Narrative Integration</strong>: Describe the foraging process vividly. The snap of twigs underfoot, the earthy scent of overturned soil, or the vibrant colors of discovered herbs all add to the immersive experience.</li>
  <li><strong>Random Encounters</strong>: Introduce a level of risk and reward to searching an environment. Classify the area as Unsafe, Risky, or Deadly as with normal random encounters.  Roll for random encounters at disadvantage for Unsafe areas, 1 check in a Risky area, and 2 checks in a Deadly area.</li>
  <li><strong>Environmental Challenges</strong>: Introduce complications during foraging. Perhaps certain herbs only grow in dangerous locations, or weather conditions affect the difficulty of finding herbs.</li>
  <li><strong>Herb-Related Quests</strong>: Create missions centered around rare herbs. A town might desperately need a cure that requires a legendary plant, or a noble might pay handsomely for a particularly rare specimen.</li>
  <li><strong>Seasonal Variations</strong>: Consider making certain herbs more common or rare depending on the season, encouraging players to plan their expeditions carefully.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="customization-creating-your-own-herbs">Customization: Creating Your Own Herbs</h2>

<p>GMs are encouraged to create unique herbs tailored to their campaign settings. When designing new herbs, consider the following:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Thematic Fit</strong>: Ensure the herb aligns with your world’s flora and magical properties.</li>
  <li><strong>Balance</strong>: New herbs should offer interesting benefits with appropriate drawbacks or challenges to obtain.</li>
  <li><strong>Rarity</strong>: Consider how common or rare the herb should be, and adjust its DC accordingly.</li>
  <li><strong>Cultural Significance</strong>: Think about how different cultures or regions in your world might use or value the herb.</li>
</ol>

<p><em>Example Custom Herb</em>:</p>
<blockquote class="text-bg-light mb-3 p-3 fst-italic">
  <p><strong>Moonglow Moss (DC 13)</strong>: Glows with silvery light when touched by moonlight. Grants darkvision while under moonlight for 1 hour, but user glows faintly, giving disadvantage on Stealth checks in darkness.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>These expanded Herbalism rules are designed to introduce new layers of strategy and risk management for your Shadowdark characters. Whether you’re a Ranger with the Herbalism ability or a character simply trying to scrape by, these options provide meaningful choices that can shape your adventure.</p>

<p>As a GM, feel free to adapt these rules to fit your campaign—adjust herb availability based on region, introduce wandering encounters during foraging, or even offer rare herbs as rewards for daring quests. Remember, the ultimate goal is to enhance the game and the enjoyment of your players. Use these rules if they add to the experience, and don’t hesitate to set them aside if they don’t.</p>

<p>We’d love to hear about your experiences with these herbalism rules! Have you created any unique herbs for your campaign? How have your players used herbalism to overcome challenges? Share your stories and suggestions in the comments below, and happy foraging!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="Shadowdark" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An expanded guide to herb foraging rules for the Shadowdark TTRPG, with additional gameplay tips and customization options.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/herbalist_bench_480x240.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/herbalist_bench_480x240.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Analyzing the DnD 2024 Dire Wolf</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/22/dire-wolf-alpha/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analyzing the DnD 2024 Dire Wolf" /><published>2024-08-22T08:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-22T08:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/22/dire-wolf-alpha</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/22/dire-wolf-alpha/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.dndbeyond.com/" target="_blank">Dungeons &amp; Dragons 5th edition</a> has long been criticized for having bland or poor monster design, and people have had high hopes that D&amp;D 2024 would resolve that. The Challenge Rating system has been unhelpful in building encounters, or creating challenging encounters, particularly at high level. The lack of variety in monster abilities and tactics has led to a bland and repetitive feeling in combat. Additionally, monsters lack a dynamic and interactive feeling that evokes a sense of adventure. Nothing demonstrates this so much as the success of the “<a href="https://shop.mcdmproductions.com/collections/flee-mortals-the-mcdm-monster-book" target="_blank">Flee Mortals</a>” supplement from MCDM, that reworked or added monsters in the game in a way that builds very exciting adventures.</p>

<p>So when people started posting monster stat blocks from the upcoming D&amp;D 2024 Players Handbook, I was naturally curious to see where things are headed.</p>

<h2 id="a-sheep-in-wolfs-clothing">A Sheep in Wolf’s Clothing</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://x.com/optionalrule/status/1826621242323108240" target="_blank">Dire Wolf stat block</a> started making the rounds on social media yesterday to significant criticism. I will not show it here as WotC has gotten over-enthusiastic with takedown notices, but overall I felt like the stat block was watered down compared to the 5e version, a bit more streamlined but in no meaningful way. The 2024 Dire Wolf has only about half the hit points of the original 5e version, and does 20% less damage. The only significant improvement is knocking a foe prone is automatic on a bite now, reducing the number of rolls needed to resolve an attack. However, many have pointed out that prone isn’t as valuable a condition since pack tactics already grants them advantage when an ally is near.</p>

<p>In my opinion, this change feels more bland and less exciting than the original 5e version. One data point isn’t a trend, and I have no idea how much of an indicator this is toward the redesign of monsters across the entire 2024 edition, but it doesn’t make me hopeful.</p>

<p>I thought this indicates a big missed opportunity. With just a few small tweaks, I think this could have been at least a bit more exciting. In my past 5e games, I’ve used the community optional rule that all monsters double their damage and half their hit points. In my groups this has led to much faster and much more exciting combats. However, I’m not going to get that extreme in my design suggestions here and stick to more simple changes in alignment with the direction the design seems to be going. So you understand my bias though, my group did enjoy the above change quite a bit and I may continue to use it in D&amp;D 2024 with the right players.</p>

<h2 id="adding-a-bit-of-bite">Adding a bit of Bite</h2>

<p>If I were to suggest some simple change to wolves overall, it would be to lean into fast encounters that showcase the dangers of the pack. So taking the Dire Wolf stat block as an example, it’s reasonable to guess that all wolves will automatically apply the Prone condition to a target on a successful bite. This is one of those effects that reads well in a book, but doesn’t result in a lot of difference in an encounter. The big advantage of Prone is that it grants advantage to an attacker, and disadvantage to the prone target on attacks. However, wolves already receive advantage if an ally is within 5 feet of the target, and the target is likely to stand up before the wolves’ next attack, meaning Prone doesn’t really add much to the encounter.</p>

<p>So I suggest adding the following ability to all wolves:</p>

<p><strong>Nimble Predator.</strong> The wolf doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks from prone creatures when it moves out of their reach.</p>

<p>This is a simple change and lets wolves, or a pack, dart in, make an attack and dart away. Interaction with packs become interesting now, because the next attacker gets the advantage without needing their ally to stay in attack range. However, for targets the wolves can’t bring down, they have to surround and engage. This creates a bit of dynamic play to wolves in combat. Not earth-shattering but a bit of an improvement for sure.</p>

<h2 id="adding-a-bit-of-spice">Adding a bit of Spice</h2>

<p>What is a wolf pack without an Alpha to lead it? To spice things up, I designed this Dire Wolf Alpha you can add to any pack of Dire Wolves to create a real challenge for your group. Not only does the Nimble Predator ability apply to all wolves, but it adds a Howl ability to grant the pack temporary hit points, and let the pack coordinate their attacks better while they have those temporary hit points.</p>

<p>Mix this creature in as the head of a regular pack of wolves to add some bite, or put them at the head of a pack of Dire Wolves for that extra thrill.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/monsters/dire_wolf_alpha_480x856.png" alt="A large snarling wolf with a pack trailing behind them. AI Image." height="856" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">It's the hope that kills you... and the teeth... okay, mostly the teeth. (AI Image)</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<blockquote class="stat-block wide">
  <h2 id="dire-wolf-alpha">Dire Wolf Alpha</h2>
  <p><em>Large beast, unaligned</em></p>

  <hr />

  <ul>
    <li><strong>AC</strong> 15 (natural armor)</li>
    <li><strong>Initiative</strong> +3</li>
    <li><strong>HP</strong> 38 (5d10 + 10)</li>
    <li><strong>Speed</strong> 60 ft.</li>
  </ul>

  <hr />

  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th style="text-align: center"> </th>
        <th style="text-align: center">STR</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">DEX</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">CON</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">INT</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">WIS</th>
        <th>CHA</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: center"> </td>
        <td style="text-align: center">18</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">16</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">15</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">4</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">14</td>
        <td>8</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: center"><strong><em>MOD</em></strong></td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+4</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+3</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+2</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">-3</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+2</td>
        <td>-1</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: center"><strong><em>SAVE</em></strong></td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+4</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+3</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+2</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">-3</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+2</td>
        <td>-1</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>

  <hr />

  <ul>
    <li><strong>Skills</strong> Perception +6, Stealth +5</li>
    <li><strong>Senses</strong> darkvision 90 ft., passive Perception 16</li>
    <li><strong>Languages</strong> None</li>
    <li><strong>Challenge</strong> 4 (1,100 XP, PB+2)</li>
  </ul>

  <h3 id="traits">Traits</h3>

  <p><strong>Pack Tactics.</strong> The wolf has advantage on attack rolls against a creature if at least one of the wolf’s allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn’t incapacitated.</p>

  <p><strong>Relentless (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest).</strong> If the wolf takes damage that would reduce it to 0 hit points, it is reduced to 1 hit point instead.</p>

  <p><strong>Nimble Predator.</strong> The wolf doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks from prone creatures when it moves out of their reach.</p>

  <p><strong>Leader of the Hunt.</strong> When the Dire Wolf Alpha knocks a target prone with a bite attack, any allies within 5 feet of the prone creature, who have temporary hit points, may make a single attack as a reaction.</p>

  <h3 id="actions">Actions</h3>

  <p><strong>Multiattack.</strong> The wolf makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its claws.</p>

  <p><strong>Bite.</strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage, and the target has the Prone condition if it is Huge or smaller.</p>

  <p><strong>Claws.</strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 9 (2d4 + 4) slashing damage.</p>

  <p><strong>Howl of the Pack (1/Day).</strong> The wolf lets out a chilling howl. Each allied wolf within 60 feet of this wolf that can hear it gains 10 temporary hit points and advantage on attack rolls until the start of the Dire Wolf Alpha’s next turn.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="packing-it-together">Packing it Together</h2>
<p>These changes add significantly more options and a dynamic flavor to wolf encounters. Under the old design, wolves basically rush in and bite, then stand in place to ensure they get the ally bonus. With Nimble Predator, however, their tactics become more fluid and interesting:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Wolves can dash in and bite.</li>
  <li>If the target is knocked prone, they can dart out of danger, leaving advantage to their ally on the prone target.</li>
  <li>If the target doesn’t get knocked prone, they stay in place to give the bonus instead.</li>
</ol>

<p>The Alpha’s “Leader of the Pack” ability adds an even broader dimension and tactical consideration to the fight. It increases the mobility and overall dynamic nature of a wolf encounter in an enjoyable way.</p>

<p>These modifications transform wolf encounters from static, predictable affairs into dynamic, tactical challenges. Players will need to think more carefully about their positioning and actions, while DMs can create more engaging and memorable combat scenarios. The pack now feels more like a coordinated unit, reflecting the true nature of wolves in the wild.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Finding ways to make combat exciting is one of the biggest challenges a DM has when putting a D&amp;D game together. If the Dire Wolf stat block is any indication, we may have more work cut out for us in the 2024 edition of the game. With a bit of thought and some tweaking though, I think we can bring some excitement to the game and create engaging encounters for our parties.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="Monsters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Analyze the new D&D 2024 Dire Wolf stat block. Discover why it's a missed opportunity and how to improve it. Learn about a simple "Nimble Predator" ability and Dire Wolf Alpha to spice up your encounters.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/monsters/dire_wolf_alpha_480x856.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/monsters/dire_wolf_alpha_480x856.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>