<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-08-22T21:02:33+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Optional Rule</title><subtitle>Optional Rule is a blog for DMs and Players alike of DnD 5e and any tabletop  roleplaying game. It offers rules, insight, analysis, and resources that help people run games and enhance their play.</subtitle><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><entry><title type="html">Analyzing the DnD 2024 Dire Wolf</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/22/dire-wolf-alpha/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analyzing the DnD 2024 Dire Wolf" /><published>2024-08-22T08:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-22T08:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/22/dire-wolf-alpha</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/22/dire-wolf-alpha/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.dndbeyond.com/" target="_blank">Dungeons &amp; Dragons 5th edition</a> has long been criticized for having bland or poor monster design, and people have had high hopes that D&amp;D 2024 would resolve that. The Challenge Rating system has been unhelpful in building encounters, or creating challenging encounters, particularly at high level. The lack of variety in monster abilities and tactics has led to a bland and repetitive feeling in combat. Additionally, monsters lack a dynamic and interactive feeling that evokes a sense of adventure. Nothing demonstrates this so much as the success of the “<a href="https://shop.mcdmproductions.com/collections/flee-mortals-the-mcdm-monster-book" target="_blank">Flee Mortals</a>” supplement from MCDM, that reworked or added monsters in the game in a way that builds very exciting adventures.</p>

<p>So when people started posting monster stat blocks from the upcoming D&amp;D 2024 Players Handbook, I was naturally curious to see where things are headed.</p>

<h2 id="a-sheep-in-wolfs-clothing">A Sheep in Wolf’s Clothing</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://x.com/optionalrule/status/1826621242323108240" target="_blank">Dire Wolf stat block</a> started making the rounds on social media yesterday to significant criticism. I will not show it here as WotC has gotten over-enthusiastic with takedown notices, but overall I felt like the stat block was watered down compared to the 5e version, a bit more streamlined but in no meaningful way. The 2024 Dire Wolf has only about half the hit points of the original 5e version, and does 20% less damage. The only significant improvement is knocking a foe prone is automatic on a bite now, reducing the number of rolls needed to resolve an attack. However, many have pointed out that prone isn’t as valuable a condition since pack tactics already grants them advantage when an ally is near.</p>

<p>In my opinion, this change feels more bland and less exciting than the original 5e version. One data point isn’t a trend, and I have no idea how much of an indicator this is toward the redesign of monsters across the entire 2024 edition, but it doesn’t make me hopeful.</p>

<p>I thought this indicates a big missed opportunity. With just a few small tweaks, I think this could have been at least a bit more exciting. In my past 5e games, I’ve used the community optional rule that all monsters double their damage and half their hit points. In my groups this has led to much faster and much more exciting combats. However, I’m not going to get that extreme in my design suggestions here and stick to more simple changes in alignment with the direction the design seems to be going. So you understand my bias though, my group did enjoy the above change quite a bit and I may continue to use it in D&amp;D 2024 with the right players.</p>

<h2 id="adding-a-bit-of-bite">Adding a bit of Bite</h2>

<p>If I were to suggest some simple change to wolves overall, it would be to lean into fast encounters that showcase the dangers of the pack. So taking the Dire Wolf stat block as an example, it’s reasonable to guess that all wolves will automatically apply the Prone condition to a target on a successful bite. This is one of those effects that reads well in a book, but doesn’t result in a lot of difference in an encounter. The big advantage of Prone is that it grants advantage to an attacker, and disadvantage to the prone target on attacks. However, wolves already receive advantage if an ally is within 5 feet of the target, and the target is likely to stand up before the wolves’ next attack, meaning Prone doesn’t really add much to the encounter.</p>

<p>So I suggest adding the following ability to all wolves:</p>

<p><strong>Nimble Predator.</strong> The wolf doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks from prone creatures when it moves out of their reach.</p>

<p>This is a simple change and lets wolves, or a pack, dart in, make an attack and dart away. Interaction with packs become interesting now, because the next attacker gets the advantage without needing their ally to stay in attack range. However, for targets the wolves can’t bring down, they have to surround and engage. This creates a bit of dynamic play to wolves in combat. Not earth-shattering but a bit of an improvement for sure.</p>

<h2 id="adding-a-bit-of-spice">Adding a bit of Spice</h2>

<p>What is a wolf pack without an Alpha to lead it? To spice things up, I designed this Dire Wolf Alpha you can add to any pack of Dire Wolves to create a real challenge for your group. Not only does the Nimble Predator ability apply to all wolves, but it adds a Howl ability to grant the pack temporary hit points, and let the pack coordinate their attacks better while they have those temporary hit points.</p>

<p>Mix this creature in as the head of a regular pack of wolves to add some bite, or put them at the head of a pack of Dire Wolves for that extra thrill.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/monsters/dire_wolf_alpha_480x856.png" alt="A large snarling wolf with a pack trailing behind them. AI Image." height="856" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">It's the hope that kills you... and the teeth... okay, mostly the teeth. (AI Image)</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<blockquote class="stat-block wide">
  <h2 id="dire-wolf-alpha">Dire Wolf Alpha</h2>
  <p><em>Large beast, unaligned</em></p>

  <hr />

  <ul>
    <li><strong>AC</strong> 15 (natural armor)</li>
    <li><strong>Initiative</strong> +3</li>
    <li><strong>HP</strong> 38 (5d10 + 10)</li>
    <li><strong>Speed</strong> 60 ft.</li>
  </ul>

  <hr />

  <table>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th style="text-align: center"> </th>
        <th style="text-align: center">STR</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">DEX</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">CON</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">INT</th>
        <th style="text-align: center">WIS</th>
        <th>CHA</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: center"> </td>
        <td style="text-align: center">18</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">16</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">15</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">4</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">14</td>
        <td>8</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: center"><strong><em>MOD</em></strong></td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+4</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+3</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+2</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">-3</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+2</td>
        <td>-1</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td style="text-align: center"><strong><em>SAVE</em></strong></td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+4</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+3</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+2</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">-3</td>
        <td style="text-align: center">+2</td>
        <td>-1</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>

  <hr />

  <ul>
    <li><strong>Skills</strong> Perception +6, Stealth +5</li>
    <li><strong>Senses</strong> darkvision 90 ft., passive Perception 16</li>
    <li><strong>Languages</strong> None</li>
    <li><strong>Challenge</strong> 4 (1,100 XP, PB+2)</li>
  </ul>

  <h3 id="traits">Traits</h3>

  <p><strong>Pack Tactics.</strong> The wolf has advantage on attack rolls against a creature if at least one of the wolf’s allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn’t incapacitated.</p>

  <p><strong>Relentless (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest).</strong> If the wolf takes damage that would reduce it to 0 hit points, it is reduced to 1 hit point instead.</p>

  <p><strong>Nimble Predator.</strong> The wolf doesn’t provoke opportunity attacks from prone creatures when it moves out of their reach.</p>

  <p><strong>Leader of the Hunt.</strong> When the Dire Wolf Alpha knocks a target prone with a bite attack, any allies within 5 feet of the prone creature, who have temporary hit points, may make a single attack as a reaction.</p>

  <h3 id="actions">Actions</h3>

  <p><strong>Multiattack.</strong> The wolf makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its claws.</p>

  <p><strong>Bite.</strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage, and the target has the Prone condition if it is Huge or smaller.</p>

  <p><strong>Claws.</strong> <em>Melee Weapon Attack:</em> +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. <em>Hit:</em> 9 (2d4 + 4) slashing damage.</p>

  <p><strong>Howl of the Pack (1/Day).</strong> The wolf lets out a chilling howl. Each allied wolf within 60 feet of this wolf that can hear it gains 10 temporary hit points and advantage on attack rolls until the start of the Dire Wolf Alpha’s next turn.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="packing-it-together">Packing it Together</h2>
<p>These changes add significantly more options and a dynamic flavor to wolf encounters. Under the old design, wolves basically rush in and bite, then stand in place to ensure they get the ally bonus. With Nimble Predator, however, their tactics become more fluid and interesting:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Wolves can dash in and bite.</li>
  <li>If the target is knocked prone, they can dart out of danger, leaving advantage to their ally on the prone target.</li>
  <li>If the target doesn’t get knocked prone, they stay in place to give the bonus instead.</li>
</ol>

<p>The Alpha’s “Leader of the Pack” ability adds an even broader dimension and tactical consideration to the fight. It increases the mobility and overall dynamic nature of a wolf encounter in an enjoyable way.</p>

<p>These modifications transform wolf encounters from static, predictable affairs into dynamic, tactical challenges. Players will need to think more carefully about their positioning and actions, while DMs can create more engaging and memorable combat scenarios. The pack now feels more like a coordinated unit, reflecting the true nature of wolves in the wild.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Finding ways to make combat exciting is one of the biggest challenges a DM has when putting a D&amp;D game together. If the Dire Wolf stat block is any indication, we may have more work cut out for us in the 2024 edition of the game. With a bit of thought and some tweaking though, I think we can bring some excitement to the game and create engaging encounters for our parties.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="Monsters" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Analyze the new D&D 2024 Dire Wolf stat block. Discover why it's a missed opportunity and how to improve it. Learn about a simple "Nimble Predator" ability and Dire Wolf Alpha to spice up your encounters.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/monsters/dire_wolf_alpha_480x856.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/monsters/dire_wolf_alpha_480x856.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Simplifying Runequest’s Critical System</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/02/simplifying-runequests-critical-system/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simplifying Runequest’s Critical System" /><published>2024-08-02T11:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-02T11:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/02/simplifying-runequests-critical-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/08/02/simplifying-runequests-critical-system/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve always been drawn to systems that offer depth and engagement. <a href="https://www.chaosium.com/runequest-rpg/" target="_blank">Runequest</a>, with its skills-based approach, certainly fits the bill. It encourages players to think creatively about their characters’ abilities in every situation, rather than waiting for the perfect moment to use a class-specific power as in D&amp;D. However, even the most beloved systems can have their quirks, and for me, Runequest’s handling of criticals has always been a sticking point.</p>

<p>I am taking inspiration from the way another percentile system I’m fond of does crticials, Harnmaster. The system is flows so naturally, I thought using something similar here could be very useful for Runequest any any of the systems under Chaosium’s banner.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/Runequest_480x626.jpg" alt="Cover of the Runequest TTRPG. A group of gods and adventurers decending from the clouds." height="626" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<h2 id="the-current-system-a-brief-overview">The Current System: A Brief Overview</h2>

<p>For those unfamiliar with Runequest, <a href="https://www.chaosium.com/call-of-cthulhu-rpg/" target="_blank">Call of Cthulhu</a>, or the <a href="https://www.chaosium.com/basic-roleplaying/" target="_blank">Basic Roleplaying System</a> from Chaosium, here’s a quick rundown:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Each skill has a percentage value, usually based on 5x an Ability Score.</li>
  <li>Rolling equal to or below that value is a success; above is a failure.</li>
  <li>Critical successes, Special successes, and Fumbles are determined by ranges calculated individually for each skill based on the current percentage value.</li>
</ol>

<p>While this system works, it can lead to some tedious moments during gameplay. Players often need to pause after each roll to consult their character sheet, checking if their result falls within these specific ranges. An efficient player might look this up and have it in mind when they go to roll, but my experience is most roll then look up those several values. This interruption can disrupt the flow of the game and pull players out of the immersive experience we all strive for.</p>

<h2 id="a-proposal-for-streamlined-critical-resolution">A Proposal for Streamlined Critical Resolution</h2>

<p>What if we could maintain the depth of the Runequest system while simplifying this particular aspect? I’d like to propose a standardized pattern for critical results that could speed up play and reduce the need for constant reference checking. Here’s how it would work:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Roll for success or failure as normal.</li>
  <li>If the roll is successful:
    <ul>
      <li>Multiples of 10 (10, 20, 30, etc.) = Critical Success</li>
      <li>Numbers ending in 5 (05, 15, 25, etc.) = Special Success</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>If the roll is a failure:
    <ul>
      <li>Multiples of 10 = Critical Failure</li>
      <li>Numbers ending in 5 = Special Failure (a new concept we could introduce)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Or in more simple terms:  A 10s value is always a Critical Success or Failure, and a 5s value is always a Special Success or Failure.  It’s that simple.</p>

<p>This system offers several advantages:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Ease of Use</strong>: Players only need to remember a simple pattern rather than consulting individual skill ranges.</li>
  <li><strong>Consistent Application</strong>: The same rule applies across all skills, reducing confusion.</li>
  <li><strong>Quick Resolution</strong>: Players can immediately recognize special results without pausing the game.</li>
  <li><strong>Maintains Depth</strong>: We’re not removing the concept of criticals or specials, just changing how we determine them.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="potential-impacts-and-considerations">Potential Impacts and Considerations</h2>

<p>It’s worth noting that this system, while similar in spirit to the original rules, doesn’t map exactly to the intended probabilities of the Runequest system. However, I believe the slight statistical differences would be a small price to pay for the significant boost in gameplay fluidity.</p>

<p>Also, it’s worth nothing that if a skill value is 9% or below, the character can’t score a Critical Success.  To me this is fine because, at that point, be grateful you succeeded at all!</p>

<p>Additionally, this system introduces the concept of a “Special Failure,” which could add an interesting new dimension to gameplay. Perhaps these could represent near-misses or failures that still provide some benefit or information to the character.  For instance, if a game uses the “push” mechanic from Call of Cthulhu, the GM could rule that a Special Failure is the same a critical failure.  Alternatively, a GM could use Special Failure to mean only a partial failure.  For example, the character might have failed to make that jump but instead of falling they are holding on by their fingertips and about to fall.  This could add another intersting dimension to gameplay.</p>

<h2 id="implementing-the-change">Implementing the Change</h2>

<p>If you’re intrigued by this idea and want to try it in your Runequest game, here are a few suggestions:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Discuss with Your Group</strong>: Any rule change should be a group decision. Present the idea and get feedback.</li>
  <li><strong>Trial Run</strong>: Consider trying the new system for a session or two before fully implementing it.</li>
  <li><strong>Adjust as Needed</strong>: If you find the new system changes the game balance too much, consider tweaking the numbers. Maybe criticals could be on rolls ending in 1 instead of multiples of 10, for instance.</li>
</ol>

<p>Remember, the goal of any house rule should be to enhance your group’s enjoyment of the game. If this system doesn’t work for your table, that’s perfectly okay!</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Chaosium has an excellent system in Runequest and Call of Cthulhu but I find it a little cumbersom to look up and juggle the current result system values. By streamlining this, we can potentially make it even more accessible and enjoyable. Whether you decide to try this proposed system or stick with the original rules, the most important thing is that you’re out there rolling dice and creating amazing stories with your friends.</p>

<p>What do you think about this proposed change? Have you used similar systems in other games? I’d love to hear your thoughts and experiences in the comments below. Happy gaming!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Streamline Runequest's critical system with a simple pattern. Boost gameplay speed, reduce confusion, and keep the depth. A small tweak for smoother adventures.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/Runequest_480x626.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/Runequest_480x626.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">12 Rules for TTRPG Players to Live By</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/07/16/twelve-rules-for-players-to-live-by/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="12 Rules for TTRPG Players to Live By" /><published>2024-07-16T22:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-16T22:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/07/16/twelve-rules-for-players-to-live-by</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/07/16/twelve-rules-for-players-to-live-by/"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, a great thread was <a href="https://x.com/jangowolf/status/1805978656533057793" target="_blank">floating around on X</a> (<em>formerly known as Twitter and largely still called that but… oh, nevermind</em>) lamenting the lack of meaningful Player Guides on TTRPG blogs. We have a plethora of guides on how to be a great Game Master but few on how to be a great player. Okay, that’s not entirely true - there are plenty of YouTube videos by <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SiywNrOABbQ" target="_blank">DungeonCraft</a> or <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UiCxyBi8lRk&amp;list=PL25p5gPY6qKVWbFtR-Crct97hg5DFekZQ&amp;index=8" target="_blank">Seth Skorkowsky</a> offering great player advice, and a few blog posts on the topic, but they’re drowned out by the volume of DM advice content.</p>

<p>These guides universally offer similar advice: show up on time, be prepared, don’t be “that guy,” and more. They’re all right, of course.</p>

<p>But I thought I’d try something a bit different, hopefully fun, and insightful to offer my own guide on how to be a better player. Though I’m trying to have some fun, I mean all of this sincerely. I hope these rules make you grin but also make you think. And most importantly, I hope they help you find ways to enjoy your games more.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/A_group_playing_a_TTRPG_togeher_480x581.png" alt="A group of adventurers leaning into talk and plan. (AI Art)" height="581" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<p>So here are my <strong>12 Rules for Players to Live By, an Antidote to Chaotic Aweful Games</strong>: (queue inspiring music!)</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Sit up straight and look at the person speaking:</strong> Ground yourself in the game physically, even if it’s online. Sit straight up and look at whoever’s speaking, even if they’re on camera. Other players notice when you’re physically present and engaged, even through a camera, and it inspires them to be too.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Treat your game like it’s something you’re responsible for:</strong> It’s an intimidating fact that it takes the entire group to make a great game, but only one player to ruin it. Take responsibility for your part in making the game great and easy. Show up on time, offer to bring snacks, reach out to struggling players, and help coordinate the game. These aren’t just the DM’s domain.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Make friends with people who want to play a good game too:</strong> Find or foster other players who share your commitment. This doesn’t mean finding clones of yourself - differences, expressed healthily, can improve a game. What matters is having friends who share similar enough play styles and have internalized the goals of getting along and having a good time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Enjoy your character for what they are, not what they will be:</strong> The key to having fun is… having fun. It’s that simple. Don’t wait for some future ability or vision of what your character will be like in 5 more levels. Think of fun ways to use your current abilities now. Working around constraints can be one of the most creative and enjoyable exercises for anyone.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Don’t let your character do anything that makes other players dislike them:</strong> Yes, that’s right - other players, not just characters. Games have a vibe. Don’t ruin it by playing a character contrary to that vibe. This doesn’t mean you can’t have conflict in the group, but understand when it starts to bleed out of character. Remember, “it’s what my character would do” is the lamest excuse in gaming.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Focus on your own game before criticizing anyone else’s:</strong> If you feel dissatisfied, start by asking yourself what you can do about it. Are you taking enough initiative? Sharing the spotlight enough? By all means, discuss your goals and ideas, but never start from a place of criticizing others without considering your own actions first.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Pursue what leads to the next adventure beat, not what is expedient:</strong> Players can often be ultimate optimizers, but that’s not always the most interesting way to play. Make choices that create interesting beats in the game, instead of forcing yet another initiative roll.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Be upfront about your goals for the character, or at least develop some:</strong> Character arcs set TTRPGs apart from tactical games. Your goals can be simple or elaborate, but they should be something you can actively pursue in-game to form rich story hooks for the DM and connections to other characters.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Assume the other players have good ideas:</strong> TTRPG groups descend into endless debate far too often. Remember, every game has a DM secretly conspiring with you to make you look awesome. So put your ideas on the table, but more often than not, pick the plan that will be the wildest adventure. We can be too careful not to make the <em>wrong</em> decision without acknowleging that the best gaming stories are usually a comedy of errors.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>State your intentions with your actions:</strong> Tell the DM you’re doing X because you’re hoping for Y. They can’t work with you if they don’t know where you’re going with an action. Making them guess what you want is a sure fire way to miss out on it. (Also, have an intention when you take an action.)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Don’t bother the group when they’re having fun:</strong> Not every moment is for you. If the group wants to spend most of the session shopping and roleplaying, and that isn’t your thing, try to participate as best you can but otherwise let them have their fun. As long as the game changes things up and had balanced beats, it’s okay to go with the flow.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Befriend a Wandering Monster:</strong> You don’t have to attack everything you see or kill everything you fight. Try parlaying, frightening it off to track back to its lair, or showing mercy and asking for a boon. Push for more interaction with the world - it can open up more story later on, find valuable allies, or just make the eventual fight more fun and exciting.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Remember, these rules are meant to make your game more enjoyable for everyone at the table. They’re not commandments carved in stone, but guidelines to help you navigate the sometimes chaotic waters of TTRPGs. So sit up straight, take responsibility, make friends, and most importantly, have fun!</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover my 12 rules for TTRPG players to enhance their gaming experience. Learn how to be a better player and create more enjoyable sessions for everyone at the table.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/A_group_playing_a_TTRPG_togeher_480x581.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/A_group_playing_a_TTRPG_togeher_480x581.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Summary of DnD 2024 Spell Changes</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/07/01/dnd-2024-spell-changes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Summary of DnD 2024 Spell Changes" /><published>2024-07-01T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-01T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/07/01/dnd-2024-spell-changes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/07/01/dnd-2024-spell-changes/"><![CDATA[<p>The Dungeons &amp; Dragons 5th Edition ruleset is being revised and rereleased this year. Termed DnD 2024, there have been a series of videos on <a href="https://dndbeyond.com" target="_blank">DnDBeyond</a>, announcing and summarizing some of the changes in the latest revision. While each of those videos have a nice corresponding blog summary of changes, I couldn’t find one after the recent Spell change video. So I am summarizing the changes discussed below for easier reference, and so you don’t have to watch the 25 minute video just for 5 minutes of vague content. Enjoy.</p>

<p>The new Players Handbook brings significant changes to the spell system, expanding and refining the magical options available to players and Dungeon Masters alike. The spell chapter has been greatly expanded, with at least 30 new spells added. Existing spells have been revisited and often upgraded, with improvements in damage, healing, range, or concentration requirements. The presentation of spells has been overhauled for better clarity and usability, addressing common rules questions within the descriptions themselves. New summoning spells, revamped conjuration magic, and spells tied to named spellcasters add fresh flavor to the magical landscape of D&amp;D. Let’s dive into the specific changes mentioned in the video below:</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/Fireball_480x642.png" alt="A woman standing, her hand wreathed in flame, ready to cast a spell. (AI Image)" height="642" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Expanded spell chapter: The new spell chapter is larger, containing at least 30 more spells than the 2014 Players Handbook. (<em>However, you will still only cast the same 4 spells</em>)</p>
  </li>
  <li>Spell revisions and upgrades:
    <ul>
      <li>Many returning spells have been revisited and functionally upgraded. (<em>Flips right to True Strike?</em>)</li>
      <li>Some spells deal more damage, heal more, have extended range, or have changes to concentration requirements.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Improved clarity and usability:
    <ul>
      <li>Common rules questions are now addressed within the spell descriptions. (<em>Flips right to Counterspell?</em>)</li>
      <li>Spell descriptions have been tightened up, using fewer words to convey information more efficiently. (<em>Flips right to Simulacrum</em>)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Presentation improvements:
    <ul>
      <li>More artwork showing spells in use.</li>
      <li>Class lists are now included in each spell’s description.</li>
      <li>The ritual tag has been moved to the casting timeline for clarity.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>New and imported spells:
    <ul>
      <li>Brand new spells have been added. (<em>Goldeney Barbs?</em>)</li>
      <li>Some spells from other sourcebooks (like Xanathar’s Guide and Tasha’s Cauldron) have been incorporated and often upgraded. (<em>Not you Silvery Barbs!</em>)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Summoning spells overhaul:
    <ul>
      <li>New summoning spells with built-in stat blocks for summoned creatures. (<em>Army of pixey summoning pixies is now a stat block?</em>)</li>
      <li>Redesigned conjuration spells to focus on summoning spirits rather than concrete creatures.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Specific spell changes:
    <ul>
      <li>Healing spells have been buffed to be more effective.</li>
      <li>Cantrips like blade ward, resistance, and guidance have been improved.</li>
      <li>High-level damaging spells have had their damage increased.</li>
      <li>Shape-shifting spells (like polymorph) now grant temporary hit points instead of a second pool of hit points.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>New spells tied to named spellcasters:
    <ul>
      <li>Examples include Yan’s Regal Presence and Jar’s Storm of Radiance. (<em>Dave’s Illusion of chiming… material component, a bell.</em>)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Quality of life improvements:
    <ul>
      <li>Some spells, like cloud of daggers, can now be moved after casting. (<em>Please let it move with caster.</em>)</li>
      <li>Produce flame has been redesigned to be easier to cast.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Standardization:
    <ul>
      <li>More consistent wording for similar effects across different spells.</li>
      <li>Introduction of a new “emanation” area of effect.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Easter eggs and flavor:
    <ul>
      <li>Many spells have new flavor text or interesting details added. (<em>Fun fact, Leomund’s Tiny Hut was discovered after a disasterious misscast of Otiluke’s Resilient Sphere</em>)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>You can see the entire video here on YouTube.</p>

<!-- Feel free to change the width and height to your desired video size. -->

<div class="embed-container">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/P0rXo-Wp_II" height="360" width="640" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="">
  </iframe>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A summary of the recently announced DnD 2024 Spell Changes.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/Fireball_480x642.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/Fireball_480x642.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Experience Still Matters - The Benefits of using XP in 5e.</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/05/02/experience-matters-updated/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Experience Still Matters - The Benefits of using XP in 5e." /><published>2024-05-02T22:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-02T22:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/05/02/experience-matters-updated</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/05/02/experience-matters-updated/"><![CDATA[<p>As we eagerly await the release of the updated version of revised 5th Edition Dungeons &amp; Dragons in 2024, it’s an opportune time to re-examine some of the core systems that make our beloved TTRPG tick. One such system that often sparks debate among players and Dungeon Masters alike is the method of character advancement. In light of the recent surge in views on my previous articles discussing the benefits of using experience points (XP) in D&amp;D, I thought it would be valuable to delve deeper into this topic and explore how XP-based advancement can enhance your gaming experience.</p>

<p>I’ve seen a big increase in traffic to my two previous articles on how <a href="/2023/05/17/the-benefits-of-xp-in-5th-edition/" target="_blank">Experience Matters</a> in DnD, and the <a href="/2021/02/25/the-zen-of-awarding-experience-for-roleplaying/" target="_blank">Zen of Awarding Non-Combat Experience</a>.  So I thought it was worth updating and revisting my thoughts on the topic.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix p-3 mb-5">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/An_anxious_Dungeon_Master_480x480.jpg" alt="Image of a DM looking anxious." height="480" width="480" />
    
    
        <figcaption class="figure-caption text-center">Let go of the anxiety and embrace XP</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<h2 id="the-case-for-xp">The Case for XP</h2>
<p>Using XP as a means of character progression offers several unique advantages that can greatly improve your D&amp;D campaign. First and foremost, XP creates a tangible connection between the characters’ actions and their growth. Every monster slain, puzzle solved, and social encounter navigated rewards the characters with XP, reinforcing the idea that their choices and accomplishments have a direct impact on their development. This sense of agency can be incredibly satisfying for players, as they witness their characters become more powerful and skilled as a result of their own efforts.</p>

<p>Furthermore, XP-based advancement allows for a more organic and flexible pacing of the game. Rather than adhering to a rigid narrative structure, XP enables the story to unfold at a pace that feels natural and responsive to the players’ actions. Generally, XP based advancement moves a bit slower than other forms. I consider this a good thing because some games level so fast, players never have an opportunity to get use to their new abilities before advancing.  In particular, 5e D&amp;D can become an entirely different game as characters level up. So if your sweet spot is lower level play, or you just want to linger a bit more to tell the kinds of stories that fit into that tier of play, you’re out of luck with other forms of advancement.</p>

<p>Particularly for newer players, having XP directly related to thier character actions is a soft way of promoting active gameplay.  This has the added benefit of incresaing player agency from the start, as players learn that choices and action are the heard of the game. Though, as I point out in the next section, DMs should be careful not to create the impression that combat is the only way to earn XP.</p>

<h2 id="awarding-xp-for-non-combat-encounters">Awarding XP for Non-Combat Encounters</h2>
<p>One common misconception about XP-based advancement is that it solely rewards combat encounters. However, this couldn’t be further from the truth. As I discussed in my article “The Zen of Awarding XP for Non-Combat Encounters,” there are numerous ways to grant XP for a wide variety of in-game accomplishments. Here are a few examples:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Roleplaying Encounters: Assign difficulty ratings to significant roleplaying encounters based on the stakes involved and the potential for world-altering consequences. The higher the difficulty, the more XP awarded.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Exploration and Discovery: Reward players for uncovering hidden locations, solving intricate puzzles, or obtaining valuable information. The XP granted should reflect the complexity and importance of the discovery.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Skill Challenges: Design multi-step challenges that require players to utilize a variety of skills to overcome obstacles. Successful completion of these challenges should yield XP proportional to the difficulty and creativity involved.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>By diversifying the sources of XP, you encourage players to engage with the game world in meaningful ways beyond just combat, fostering a more immersive and well-rounded roleplaying experience.</p>

<h2 id="a-log-of-memories">A Log of Memories</h2>
<p>One often overlooked benefit of tracking XP is the creation of a de facto campaign journal. By noting down the sources of XP, you inadvertently document the major events and turning points of your game. This record can serve as a nostalgic reminder of the party’s shared adventures, allowing players to look back on their journey with a sense of pride and accomplishment.</p>

<h2 id="other-articles">Other Articles</h2>
<p>For an alternative take on how to award experience in your D&amp;D Game, check out these articles but other bloggers.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://dmdavid.com/tag/using-experience-points-to-make-your-dd-game-more-compelling/" target="_blank">Using Experience Points To Make D&amp;D More Compelling</a> by DM David that details his method for awarding easier and more consistant experience in his DnD games.</li>
  <li><a href="https://yumdm.com/xp-and-levelling/" target="_blank">How I Do Experience Points And Leveling In D&amp;D</a> by Yum DM who demonstrates a simple system for awarding session based experience to incentivize showing up to the game.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>As we stand on the cusp of a new era in D&amp;D, it’s crucial to recognize the enduring value of XP-based advancement. By connecting character growth to the players’ actions and providing a flexible framework for pacing and rewards, XP can greatly enhance the immersion, engagement, and overall enjoyment of your D&amp;D campaign. So, as you prepare for the exciting changes that lie ahead, consider giving XP a chance to breathe new life into your gaming experience.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="DM Advice, Player Advice, Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Uncover the benefits of XP-based advancement in D&D. Enhance player agency, pacing, and diverse gameplay. Learn to award XP for a well-rounded experience.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/An_anxious_Dungeon_Master_480x480.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/An_anxious_Dungeon_Master_480x480.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">TTRPG Tools for Collboration and Change</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/04/28/ttrpg-tools-for-collaboration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="TTRPG Tools for Collboration and Change" /><published>2024-04-28T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-28T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/04/28/ttrpg-tools-for-collaboration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/04/28/ttrpg-tools-for-collaboration/"><![CDATA[<p>Why do some Dungeons &amp; Dragons groups struggle so hard to cooperate and enjoy a game together? Even well-meaning players can have spotty outcomes and TTRPG groups can have a hard time staying together for more than a few sessions. Particularly in an era of safety tools, and assertions of the importance of inclusive play, we seem to be struggling harder now than any other time in the hobby. Many take the position that this is because we are clearing the toxicity of one culture or another from the gaming space, but I would suggest this is wrong-minded. As a community, too many people have given up on the idea that collaboration or real tolerance of different opinions has any value at all. Some may blame an inherent cultural evil for this division but I am not convinced. I suggest the TTRPG community doesn’t have a good set of frameworks or tools to promote collaboration. Yes we have safety tools and, while those can be useful, safety and collaboration are completely different things.</p>

<p>So, how do we get the right collaboration tools for the right group? We have to understand how strongly players, which includes the DM, agree on:</p>

<ol>
  <li>How the world works.</li>
  <li>What kind of experiences they enjoy.</li>
</ol>

<p>Groups that share a similar view of both these axis, tend to fit together naturally and develop a culture of cooperation and enjoyment. These groups are rare in my experience, and often come together by trying different players out until they reach the right group configuration. They build on in-group tradition, self-regulate well, leverage similar norms, and normalize group habits through a shared folklore to any new players that might join the group. These are the easiest kinds of games to run, but some of the most difficult to find and build.</p>

<p>For most groups, we need to observe and assess how well they align along those two axis.</p>

<p>Collectively this is often a product of Tone (i.e. the vibe a game world has) and Style (i.e. the type of action in the game).</p>

<h2 id="plotting-this-out">Plotting This Out</h2>

<p>I’ll go into some detail below, describing the axis and different tools you could consider using, but I’m a visual guy and I think this quad chart can sum it up well and give you the TLDR. If you find it helpful, print it out and keep it in your DM Notebook. I think it’s worth a moment to use this thinking to assess where players are.</p>

<figure class="figure rounded mx-auto clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/ToolsforCollaborationChangeTTRPGs_960x540.png" alt="Image of a quad chart with different tools plotted along the axis." height="540" width="960" />
    
    
</figure>

<h2 id="how-the-world-works">How the World Works</h2>

<p>There is a saying that “Assumptions are the mother of all screw-ups”. This is true because people take an action with an assumption that others will see it in a particular way or have a specific outcome, only to be shocked it didn’t turn out that way. People may see actions as having a different motivation than you intend, or blind spots cause people to miss other factors, all leading to the dreaded “unintended consequences”. The same is true in TTRPGs and amplified because we don’t have the complex factors of reality at play. Our actions in any game are filtered through the expectations of other players’ assumptions about how the world works, with the DM having a large impact because they are the filter for the entire world.</p>

<p>Games without a good alignment of expectations can be incredibly frustrating for everyone at the table. There is a constant cycle of action, and unintended outcome, that leads to more actions and more unintended outcomes and the whole thing can spiral out of control quickly. In these cases alignment can be hard. Players have to put aside the idea that the world works any one specific way, and have some way to understand how it works differently from their natural assumptions, or even understanding what those natural assumptions are.</p>

<p>Tools that can be helpful here, uncover assumptions, illustrate differences in a meaningful way, and help reach a consensus on how situations will be resolved. Techniques might include:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Explaining</strong> what outcome they expect from the action and why. “I steal the gem off the table while nobody is looking because I think the Lord will blame their housekeeper.” Something like this brings the base level assumptions to the top so players can either clear up assumptions (“Well the Lord has had this housekeeper for decades and only just met you, they are more likely to blame a stranger”), or they can negotiate (“Yes, but without some kind of supporting evidence they may not blame anyone specifically and choose to search everyone.”). This helps normalize everyone’s point of view about how the world works enough to align character actions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>In World <strong>Examples</strong>. As a DM tool, providing examples of how the world sees things in broad strokes can help players understand the assumptions of the world. Do tavern brawls normally turn into sword fights, or do they just try to knock each other out? Do guards arrest criminals or just kill them? Are (insert race or culture) just a bunch of murderous psychopaths or do they have traditions and nuances of their own? These are all very common things players should know at a table but can start with very different assumptions. The smart DM uses “random encounters” to create examples that proactively answer these questions ahead of time. A constant stream of examples not only clears up the assumptions but gives the world a sense of life and a point of view and DMs should lean into this tool heavily.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Debate</strong>. Players love to debate at a table, and often the DM sits aside and listens. This is an important tool for a DM as they often pick up new ideas, but it’s also an opportunity to either clear up bad assumptions on the part of the players, or bend the world to integrate an assumption the DM hadn’t had previously. Sure these debates can degrade into a timewaste, but not always, and an artful group will spend at least some time talking about their assumptions with each other.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Storytelling</strong>. In-world storytelling is a powerful technique for demonstrating how you think the world perceives specific actions. For players this can happen as part of their backstory development, how the world reacted to their previous actions. The DM can related stories or lore in the world that express important information about how the world works. The most powerful way to use lore is to integrate it to something important for a current adventure.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>DM/Player <strong>Vision</strong>. A game suffers the most when the DM, the de facto guide to how the world works in a campaign, is out of alignment with one or more players. This is a particularly difficult situation because so much influence is on the DM’s shoulders and ability to change. In these cases, DMs taking some time to express some of their vision for how the world works can be of great value. It at least establishes a baseline of where the world is starting from and should be a jumping off point for a conversation. Players can then do the same about how they see the world works and the group can hopefully keep that in mind to filter their experiences, or modify expectations to be in better alignment.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="what-experiences-are-enjoyable">What Experiences are Enjoyable</h2>

<p>There is another saying, “Style is a way of saying who you are without having to speak.” In TTRPG terms this means that games are defined by what kinds of actions they focus on. Games can be heavy on action, dialog, survival, or any number of other types of actions that players find most fun and usually where the rewards of a game are most concentrated. System definitely plays a strong part in this but is more influenced by player choices because Systems are finite, while Narrative is infinite. Therefore players can differ on this in an almost infinite variety of ways.</p>

<p>Games without a good alignment of what actions players find fun often seem boring, tedious, or a waste of time. People may roll their eyes when the Barbarian’s player gets bored and starts a fight during negotiations. Alternatively players may cringe at some inappropriate bit of roleplay on the part of another player and feel put off by it. This can lead to endless arguments about character behavior, and can sometimes spiral out of control into an eventual DnD Horror Stories or AITA Reddit post.</p>

<p>Tools that can be helpful here reward the kind of play the group is looking for, create a shared sense of fun, or give players the moment to shine in their individual actions. Techniques might include:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Planning.</strong> Players love to plan and it’s a good idea for them to work one out. Even if they don’t follow it, this tends to be an exercise in the players defining what they think would be most fun. DMs should listen carefully, a plan is an explicit statement about what players would think is fun. DMs should consider giving players the kind of information that leads them to the kind of play the DM would think is fun. For example, is a local troll intelligent and willing to negotiate? Then give the players some kind of hint “A local caravaner said the troll asked why they were there and chased them away with a rock.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Spotlight.</strong> Give each other a moment to shine in the spotlight and understand this is a group activity. This means players can either play along or give someone space (maybe even take a break) while another player has their moment. DMs should create opportunities for these moments and help make sure they don’t run too long and moments are shared appropriately across the entire party. This isn’t to say DMs should create small solo adventures for each player, but that shifting the spotlight based on the kind of action specific players like is a way that allows the entire group to participate.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>System Incentives.</strong> System design has a lot of influence on what types of activities players seek out. DnD is often said to be a game about combat, I’m not going to argue about identity here but there sure are a whole lot of rules about combat so you shouldn’t be surprised if players choose violence. Finding the right system or playing with house rules that reward the right kind of action with interesting gameplay can be very useful.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Rewards &amp; Consequences.</strong> This is as simple as it sounds. When players take actions that align with something you find fun, just tell them. “Hey, that was a lot of fun.” Likewise, the game world or characters can do the same, praising a character for their actions, and seeing the world changed in an appropriate way because of it. On the flip side, consequences are another tool. If you have a party that wants to roleplay often, having no consequences for the character that chooses violence frequently will just cause problems. This isn’t to say you should knuckle down on a player, but you can resolve uninteresting actions quickly and focus the time on interesting ones.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Be Explicit.</strong> The party should talk to one another about what kinds of actions they find fun. Give examples of other games where great fun was had and why you enjoy it. This helps groups find common ground, or at least understand when another player needs a moment for their action to play out in an enjoyable way.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Campaign Setup.</strong> When a game is being pitched, it’s good to talk about the style and action everyone is looking for. The DM should put out their idea for the action in a campaign. DMs may be tempted to say ‘it depends on the party’, which is true but it’s likely the DM has some point of view in a campaign they developed and a personal style as well. It’s better to be explicit about those before the game even begins than to pretend you’re an empty vessel waiting for the players to fill you up with their choices.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Character Setup.</strong> Look at the top skill of each of the characters, and the top skill of the villains prepared for a game. These are explicit statements about what kinds of actions that character wants, or that villain will trigger. I don’t know how many games I’ve had where I never had the opportunity to even use my highest skill. Character builds are often an explicit statement of what kinds of action the player is going to seek out. Likewise for monsters. Don’t ignore that.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>The Buddy System.</strong> One of the best ways to form an agreement on what kinds of actions are fun, is for one player to bring another player into their plots and schemes. Using some of these other tools, you create a sense of connection between each other and build off of each other’s fun.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="a-note-on-safety-tools">A Note on Safety Tools</h3>

<p>It’s hard to discuss the topic of tools at the table without talking about safety tools. These are discussed, debated, and fought over across the entire TTRPG community. Tools are tools. I think they’re fine when used correctly. I also acknowledge there is a sub-culture of using safety tools to bludgeon each other and, though I’ve long advocated for them, I wonder if the whole conversation has gotten counter-productive.</p>

<p>That said though, I still suggest you use safety tools appropriately, but realize their limitations. What we’re trying to do here is get on common ground about what kinds of actions we think are fun. This is a positive way to establish from the start that we’re trying to have fun together. Using the term safety tool can sometimes have the unintended outcome of establishing we are dangerous to one another and that we need to seek safety. Without doubt, there are times where this is true, but having that usually the exception and not the rule.</p>

<p>Also, I think people may be tempted to assume that things covered under traditional safety tools are arguments about how the world works or how the world SHOULD work. It is not. In most games the entire range of human experiences can be assumed to happen somewhere in the world, but any particular game is only going to focus on a sub-set of experiences they find most fun. It doesn’t matter what those experiences are, it just matters that they are fun to the group. So most online arguments about what should or shouldn’t be in a game aren’t about what should or should be in the world, but about what is and isn’t fun to spend time on as a group.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>At the end of the day, finding the right tools to foster collaboration at the TTRPG table is all about communication, understanding, and a willingness to work together. It’s about being clear on how we think the game world works and what kind of experiences we each find enjoyable. It’s also about being open to trying new things and finding that sweet spot where everyone is having a good time.</p>

<p>No single tool is going to be a magic bullet, but by employing a variety of techniques - from in-world examples and debates to spotlight moments and the buddy system - we can start to build that shared understanding and sense of fun that makes for truly great gaming experiences.</p>

<p>So let’s keep talking to each other, keep experimenting with different approaches, and most importantly, let’s keep remembering that at the heart of it all, we’re here to have a good time together. With the right tools in our kit, and the right attitude at the table, there’s no limit to the adventures we can have and the stories we can tell.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="DM Advice, Player Advice, Community Discussion, Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover collaborative tools for aligning expectations and enhancing fun in your TTRPG and DnD games. Improve cooperation and enjoyment at your table.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/ToolsforCollaborationChangeTTRPGs_960x540.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/ToolsforCollaborationChangeTTRPGs_960x540.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Gritty DnD Injuries - Expanding Exhaustion</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/02/16/revised-exhausted-condition/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gritty DnD Injuries - Expanding Exhaustion" /><published>2024-02-16T16:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-16T16:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/02/16/revised-exhausted-condition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2024/02/16/revised-exhausted-condition/"><![CDATA[<p>In Dungeons and Dragons 5th edition, the introduction of lasting injuries and effects promises to revitalize the way players approach the game. By infusing combat with the possibility of enduring consequences, this elevates the significance of each skirmish beyond the individual encounter. Health is no longer just hit points to be replenished with the wave of a hand or a nap; it becomes a strategic element of play managed through clever player choices. This shift introduces a layer of tactical depth missing in the vanilla game, requiring players to think critically about their characters actions and their potential long-term impacts on how the adventure plays out.</p>

<p>An enhanced focus on increasing tension through lasting injuries does more than just increase stakes; it weaves a tighter bond between the player characters. Characters are encouraged build allies and actively participate in the healing and protection of their comrades, adding a rich layer of interdependence that was somewhat underdeveloped in the core rules. The sense of triumph following a narrowly won battle is exponentially heightened when the victory is hard-earned and comes with its own set of challenges to overcome. Through this approach, Dungeons and Dragons 5th edition rekindles the flame of classic sword and sorcery adventures, making every step of the journey feel impactful and every success a testament to the players’ strategic prowess and camaraderie.</p>

<h2 id="exhaustion-condition-and-the-modern-adventurer">Exhaustion Condition and the Modern Adventurer</h2>

<p>The D&amp;D design team presented an intriguing update to the exhaustion rules during their <a href="https://media.dndbeyond.com/compendium-images/one-dnd/expert-classes/kpx0MvyfBGHe0XKk/UA2022-Expert-Classes.pdf">Expert Class Unearthed Arcana Playtest</a> in 2022. In it, they replaced the confusing six-level exhaustion rules, which many thought were useless and confusing, with a more gradual system adding a simple -1 per level of exhaustion. A typical house rule in many D&amp;D games has been to add a level of exhaustion to each character who drops to 0 HP or fails a death save. Using a similar house rule with this new Exhaustion Condition, but requires a bit more thought and modification to make it enjoyable, manageable, and fit well into the game.</p>

<p>Having never included the Exhausted Condition in subsequent UA releases, it looks like this may not be included in the DnD 2024 update, set to release later this year.  Possibly they may make it into the DMG as an optional rule, but this expansion adjusts to the rules change in a way that integrates better with class abilities and the intent of the overall rules. It also integrates with the natural and mechanical healing rules in a natural way.</p>

<p>To that end, I suggest the following house rule I have been refining over the last year. (You may have seen some of my previous injury condition posts).</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4 clearfix">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/wounded_ranger_480x600.png" alt="A woman with bow and arrow, standing defiantly, with scrapes and bruises on her face." height="600" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<h3 id="exhausted-condition">Exhausted [Condition]</h3>

<p>Characters accumulate exhaustion through various means that slowly reduce their effectiveness.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Levels of Exhaustion.</strong> Exhaustion is cumulative. Each time a character receives the condition, they gain 1 level of exhaustion. A character may have a <strong><em>maximum of 10 levels</em></strong> of exhaustion and die once they exceed that. As an optional rule, the DM may choose to use the character’s CON score as the maximum level of exhaustion.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>d20 Rolls Affected.</strong> The character subtracts their levels of exhaustion from all d20 tests.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Spell Save DCs Affected.</strong> The character subtracts their level of exhaustion from their spell save DCs for any spell they personally cast.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Gaining the Condition.</strong> A character gains 1 level of exhaustion whenever they fail a death save or when they suffer a critical hit. Characters killed through the Massive Damage rules gain their maximum level of exhaustion. The DM may also rule a character acquires a level of exhaustion though other means like strenuous activity, difficult travel, or other circumstances.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Recovering.</strong> A character removes 1 level of exhaustion per Long Rest.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Recovering.</strong> (Optional Variant) Immediately after finishing a Long Rest, the character may make a DC 10 Constitution test, removing 1 level of exhaustion on a success. Characters who fail by rolling a 1 gain an additional exhaustion level. A character may gain advantage on a recovery roll if they are being provided medical care, provided hot meals, and in a restful environment, or other conditions as determined by the DM. Characters without adequate shelter or in a very stressful environment roll recovery at disadvantage. When their exhaustion level reaches 0, the character is no longer injured.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="class-ability">Class Ability</h4>

<p><strong>Shake It Off.</strong> Fighters, Paladins, Barbarians, Monks, and Rangers gain the ‘Shake It Off’ ability at 1st level. As a free action, the character can choose to tap their deep reserves of fortitude to prevent taking one level of exhaustion. They can use this ability once and regain the ability to do so after a Long Rest. These classes gain an additional use of Shake It Off each time they gain the Extra Attack ability.</p>

<h4 id="magic">Magic</h4>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Healing Exhaustion with Magic.</strong> One level of exhaustion may be removed by casting Lesser Restoration. Greater Restoration removes all levels of exhaustion.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Bring Out Your Dead.</strong> Any levels of exhaustion remain with a character brought back to life through Revivify or Raise Dead, up to their maximum. Resurrection, True Resurrection, and Wish bring characters back to life with 0 levels of exhaustion.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="much-ado-about-death-spirals">Much Ado about Death Spirals</h2>

<p>Some express a concern of creating a “Death Spiral” through cumulative injury rules, where penalties lead to further failures in a seemingly endless cycle, is valid yet potentially overstated in the context of these new exhaustion mechanics. The incremental nature of a -1 penalty per level of exhaustion allows for a gradual impact, delaying significant detriment until several levels are accumulated. Moreover, characters possess abilities such as Bardic Inspiration or Aid, offering strategic options to offset even several levels of penalties at a cost. Additionally, the game does not operate in isolation; DMs can incorporate downtime for recovery, and players can proactively seek rest, fostering deeper engagement with the game world. Thus, while vigilance is necessary to prevent overwhelming challenges, these rules are designed to enrich gameplay, not hinder it.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>In conclusion, incorporating and expanding the exhaustion rules in a Dungeons and Dragons game adds a whole new layer of strategic depth and emotional engagement. It elevates the stakes of every combat encounter, pushing players to think more critically about their actions and encouraging a greater sense of camaraderie within the party. This not only enhances the realism of the game but also enriches the storytelling, creating a more immersive and memorable experience. While it’s a more challenging way to play, the rewards are substantial, making each victory a testament to the players’ resilience and teamwork.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="Game Mechanics, Homebrew Content, DM Advice, Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore gritty DnD 5e injuries, adding strategic depth and encouraging camaraderie without spiraling into defeat.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/wounded_ranger_480x600.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/wounded_ranger_480x600.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Yes, if … the true secret of crafting adventures</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/12/20/the-magic-of-yes-if/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yes, if … the true secret of crafting adventures" /><published>2023-12-20T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-20T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/12/20/the-magic-of-yes-if</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/12/20/the-magic-of-yes-if/"><![CDATA[<p>In Dungeons &amp; Dragons, a common practice among Dungeon Masters (DMs) is to hand-wave new rulings for the sake of convenience, or with the belief that they’re enhancing the game by simply saying yes. However, I’ve come to realize that this approach, while seemingly beneficial, may actually be more limiting than many of us think. Simple answers keep things moving but ignore the fundamental truth about creating adventures. Running a TTRPG isn’t just about adjudicating the rules, it’s about creating opportunities for characters to risk it all to pursue their goals. Every question asked in a game is an opportunity to create a new adventure, so let’s talk a bit about this.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/A_group_playing_a_TTRPG_togeher_480x581.png" alt="A group of adventurers researching something magical." height="581" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<h3 id="the-underappreciated-art-of-saying-no">The Underappreciated Art of Saying No</h3>

<p>The art of saying “no” in modern D&amp;D doesn’t get the appreciation it deserves. A straightforward “yes” can be a quick fix, a way to feel good in the moment because it seems like we’re enabling our players, who in turn feel gratified for getting their way. But this isn’t the kind of game-play that fosters deep enjoyment or lasting investment. It’s a basic facet of human psychology: the easy win often fails to satisfy in the long run.</p>

<p>Additionally, it ignores the very important role the rules play. That is to define a common core experience for everyone at the table. Establishing a common and consistent vision of how the world works is an extremely important element of creating any shared experience. Tossing that aside with a simple yes, while easier, undermines the shared experience.</p>

<p><strong>But while “No” is a complete sentence, it also doesn’t mean things have to end there.</strong></p>

<h3 id="the-missed-opportunity-in-the-simple-answer">The Missed Opportunity in the Simple Answer</h3>

<p>While saying “yes” or “no” can keep the game moving and be an adequate solution in some cases, I believe we’re missing a significant opportunity. Rulings that fall into the grey areas – the edge cases – offer a golden chance to weave new elements into the world and present challenges to players by creating new adventures. Imagine a scenario where learning a new technique, acquiring a magical item, or forming a bond with a key character becomes part of the quest. These are opportunities to use abilities in innovative ways, enriching the game’s narrative.</p>

<p><strong>From a DM’s point of view, the best answer to every question isn’t a yes or no, it’s a new adventure.</strong></p>

<h3 id="yes-if-vs-yes-and-and-yes-but">“Yes, If…” vs. “Yes, And” and “Yes, But”</h3>

<p>Many advocate for “Yes, and” or “Yes, but” as the secret sauce to effective GMing. While these approaches have their merits, I propose that “Yes, if…” holds significantly more potential value for a game. The phrases “and” and “but” often lead to immediate, transactional outcomes, which, though useful, don’t contribute substantially to the overall adventure. On the other hand, <strong>“Yes, if…” places the onus back on the players, challenging them to pursue something more, to push their boundaries and achieve new results.</strong></p>

<p><em>As a single example, I had a player in my D&amp;D game who believed they could counterspell an ability if they had the same spell prepared. That’s not how it works, and I wasn’t going to rewrite the entire counterspell system on a whim. However, the player was communicating something they thought was interesting to me, so I would be a fool to ignore it. So, I had them make a history roll to recall writings of wizards who seemed to have been able to do this, and they could find out more by researching in the library at Candlekeep. This led to an entire adventure to recover lost lore of that Wizard order who could modify their spell focus to give them this ability. Ruling-wise, it was just a bound magic item. The whole thing worked out very well and it gave the entire party a new adventure to pursue.</em></p>

<p>(For the record, I realize ‘Yes, if…’ is just ‘No, but …’ in disguise but keeping things framed as a yes is powerful to frame things in the players mind as an opportunity.)</p>

<h3 id="the-real-thrill-of-dd-beyond-convenience">The Real Thrill of D&amp;D: Beyond Convenience</h3>

<p>By resorting to easy rulings for the sake of convenience, we risk diluting the true excitement of D&amp;D. The essence of the game lies in using every opportunity to create new adventures, presenting challenges that players can overcome and be rewarded for. “Yes, if…” is more than just a response; it’s a philosophy that encourages deeper engagement, creativity, and a richer gaming experience.</p>

<p>In conclusion, embracing the “Yes, if…” approach can transform our D&amp;D sessions from simple pastimes into epic adventures filled with meaningful challenges and rewarding experiences.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discover how flexible D&D rulings enhance gameplay, as a DM turns a player's unique counterspell idea into an exciting new adventure.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/A_group_playing_a_TTRPG_togeher_480x581.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/A_group_playing_a_TTRPG_togeher_480x581.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Unlocking the Magic of TTRPG Design</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/12/11/guidelines-for-great-ttrpg-design/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Unlocking the Magic of TTRPG Design" /><published>2023-12-11T12:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-12-11T12:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/12/11/guidelines-for-great-ttrpg-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/12/11/guidelines-for-great-ttrpg-design/"><![CDATA[<p>Brandon Sanderson, celebrated for his exceptional worldbuilding and intricate <a href="https://faq.brandonsanderson.com/knowledge-base/what-are-sandersons-laws-of-magic/" target="_blank">magic system design</a>, stands out as a titan in modern fantasy literature. His principles, while crafted for literary creation, offer invaluable insights for TTRPG design. In an era brimming with new TTRPG systems being developed and crowdfunded, I frequently ponder how Sanderson’s concepts could shape better game design, or at least preserve a diversity in gaming experiences rather than  yet another play on heroic-fantasy without risk of failure. Specifically, I contemplate the potential of these foundational ideas to captivate players through effective game design—a crucial aspect often missed in the foundational design of many emerging games.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/dice_and_eberron_480x640.jpg" alt="A map of eberron with dice on top of it." height="640" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<p><strong>Sanderson’s Guidelines for Creating a Compelling Magic System</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li>An author’s ability to resolve conflicts with magic is directly proportional to how well the reader understands that magic.</li>
  <li>Weaknesses, limits, and costs are more intriguing than powers.</li>
  <li>Authors should first expand on existing elements of the magic system before adding entirely new aspects, as these could significantly alter how the system integrates into the fictional world.</li>
</ol>

<p>I often reflect on this in relation to TTRPG system design, especially given the influx of new systems that emphasize powers and abilities, downplaying failure as a core aspect of Heroic Fantasy. This trend seemed to gain momentum during the 5e D&amp;D era, as the notion that any form of failure was undesirable began to surface in online discussions. However, I believe this line of thinking leads to uninspired and uninteresting game design.</p>

<h3 id="the-heroic-fantasy-conundrum">The Heroic Fantasy Conundrum</h3>
<p>We’re in an era of evolving TTRPG landscapes, marked by a trend of assuming powers and minimizing the role of failure. It seems like everyone wants to be Hercules without the trials and tribulations. This shift, gaining traction in the 5e D&amp;D era, rendered the concept of failure almost taboo in some gaming circles.</p>

<p>It’s important to note that Heroic Fantasy traditionally involves risks and the possibility of failure. The recent shift away from these elements is a modern deviation, but let’s not get sidetracked by that right now.</p>

<p>The best tales are spun from sacrifice, struggle, and the looming threat of defeat. These elements are the lifeblood of drama, action, and even comedy. So, how do we craft TTRPG systems that embrace these aspects?</p>

<h3 id="creating-worlds-that-thrive-on-challenge">Creating Worlds That Thrive on Challenge</h3>
<p>A well-designed TTRPG is more than just rolling dice and casting spells. It involves creating engaging group gameplay and weaving a narrative rich with compelling storytelling elements – be it risky decisions, character flaws, or facing daunting obstacles. The tension arising from these interactions is what elevates a game, and systems designed to leverage these elements can foster some of the most rewarding experiences at the gaming table.</p>

<p><strong>Optional Rule’s Guidelines for Creating a Compelling TTRPG</strong></p>

<ol>
  <li>The depth of a player’s immersion is a function of how well the system fosters meaningful interactions within the game world.</li>
  <li>The best TTRPG experiences arise from grappling with limitations, creatively offsetting weaknesses, and skillfully navigating the ever-present risk of failure.</li>
  <li>A compelling system is captivating through the intricate interplay of existing subsystems, rather than through the addition of new ones.</li>
</ol>

<p>There isn’t just one way to design a good TTRPG, and it seems we’ve lost sight of that. In a race to create the most ‘heroic’ designs, the importance of struggle and success as core elements of good game design has been overlooked. There should still be room in the hobby for systems that embrace these challenges. Being overshadowed by ‘easy-mode’ systems, where players never fail, isn’t beneficial for the hobby. I hope more designers will consider these guidelines in their creations, and I also hope the community discussion will acknowledge the importance of this type of system design, recognizing the need for a variety of philosophies in game design.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="RPG Resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore how Brandon Sanderson's magic system principles can revolutionize TTRPG design for deeper, more engaging gameplay experiences.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/dice_and_eberron_480x640.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/dice_and_eberron_480x640.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">DMing is not a Covert Power Grab</title><link href="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/11/27/dming-isnt-a-conspiracy-to-control-you/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DMing is not a Covert Power Grab" /><published>2023-11-27T13:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-11-27T13:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/11/27/dming-isnt-a-conspiracy-to-control-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.optionalrule.com/2023/11/27/dming-isnt-a-conspiracy-to-control-you/"><![CDATA[<p>The DM is the First Mover in any Dungeons &amp; Dragons campaign. It’s not that they’re superior or more important; rather, the game hinges on the DM’s involvement. As the game’s primary driving force, DMs significantly influence its tone and genre. Moreover, since they orchestrate the world, it naturally reflects their point of view and judgment. This aspect of game-running is a feature, not a flaw. While it’s perfectly valid for players to have preferences about the game’s style, the DM’s creative perspective is not inherently wrong.</p>

<figure class="figure float-end ms-4">
    
    <img class="img-fluid figure-img " src="/assets/img/A_group_playing_a_TTRPG_togeher_480x581.png" alt="A group of adventurers playing a game together." height="581" width="480" />
    
    
</figure>

<p>Many people seem uncomfortable with this reality, but it’s time to accept it. <strong>DMing is not a covert power grab</strong>; it’s a role undertaken for enjoyment and creative fulfillment. Often, DMs step into this role simply because they cannot find a suitable game, so they opt to create one. <em>This is not a conspiracy; it’s how games get played</em>.</p>

<p>D&amp;D 5e reiterated a social norm that has been integral to DMing since the hobby’s inception. Informally known as “Rule 0,” the <a href="https://www.dndbeyond.com/sources/dmg/introduction#TheDungeonMaster" target="_blank">core rules state</a>: <em>“The rules aren’t in charge. You, the Dungeon Master, are the final arbiter of the rules.”</em> However, it also advises the DM to maintain consistency in rulings and ensure players understand the decisions and applied rules. This highlights that while DMs may initiate the game, its success depends on player engagement. All TTRPGs  are inherently collaborative experiences.</p>

<p>“<a href="https://media.wizards.com/2023/downloads/dnd/Peril_in_Pinebrook_COMPLETE.pdf" target="_blank">Perils in Pinebrook</a>,” the latest D&amp;D adventure, subtly but significantly modifies Rule 0. This adventure explicitly includes a new version of Rule 0:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong class="card blockquote blockquote-caption fst-italic text-center p-3"><em>“Rule 0 of D&amp;D is simple: Have fun. It’s fine if everyone agrees to change the rules, as long as doing so makes the game more enjoyable for everyone.”</em></strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>While this statement captures the essence of gaming, it doesn’t fully acknowledge the typical process of game formation and momentum building. DMs usually originate the campaign or game idea, developing it until it’s robust enough to present to players. This isn’t a scheme to control players; it’s a natural part of the creative process. Of course, DMs must entice potential players with their game, revising their ideas if necessary to attract the desired audience. However, suggesting that DMs need player approval before even formulating their campaign idea could be detrimental, especially for new DMs.</p>

<p>Additionally, this shift underscores what many perceive as a troubling trend in the evolution of DnD in recent years. The core game, rather than uniting players, appears to be setting the community against itself, fostering an atmosphere of mutual suspicion and policing. While no single change in the game is solely responsible for this, there seems to be an aspect of DnD’s development that inadvertently caters to the ‘social point-scoring’ behavior rampant in online cultures. Although the underlying intentions behind these changes are commendable, it’s crucial to recognize how toxic elements of online culture can exploit these changes in ways detrimental to the hobby.</p>

<p>Games are inherently about negotiation, but the initial idea must come from someone. Observing this rule and the evolving toxic behaviors on social media, I see a potential for harm. There’s a risk that some community segments might expect DMs to seek permission for their ideas, potentially stifling games before they begin.</p>]]></content><author><name>Scott Turnbull</name></author><category term="rpg resources" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore how the DM's role as the First Mover shapes DnD games, impacts player dynamics, and evolves with changing rules and online culture.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/A_group_playing_a_TTRPG_togeher_480x581.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.optionalrule.com/assets/img/A_group_playing_a_TTRPG_togeher_480x581.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>